<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-gb">
  <title>No Script Show</title>
  <subtitle>Building solid websites simply.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://noscript.show/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://noscript.show/" />
  <updated>2025-03-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://noscript.show/</id>
  <author>
    <name>No Script Show</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Indie Web: a people focussed alternative to the &quot;corporate web&quot;</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/16/" />
    <updated>2025-03-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/16/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;indie-web-a-people-focussed-alternative-to-the-corporate-web&quot;&gt;Indie Web: a people focussed alternative to the &amp;quot;corporate web&amp;quot;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-it&quot;&gt;What is it?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/&quot;&gt;Indieweb.org.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IndieWeb&quot;&gt;Indieweb on Wikipedia.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://briefs.video/videos/why-the-indieweb/&quot;&gt;Heydon Pickering&#39;s hilarious explaination.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A movement focussed on the web as an egalitarian tool for all. From search to social media to AI, communication on the web is in the hands of a few who get to set the algorithms. The Indie Web represents an alternative to that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-it-a-growing-movement&quot;&gt;Is it a growing movement?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps this can not be judged by the numbers of those officially involved, but is seen in various reactions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shifts to Bluesky (AT Protocol) and Mastodon (ActivityPub).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Renewed interest in the creative personal website. ie. &lt;a href=&quot;https://glitch.com/&quot;&gt;Glitch&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsletter.ownyourweb.site/&quot;&gt;Own Your Web&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.htmlforpeople.com/&quot;&gt;HTML for people&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State intervention: the EU with data protection and accessibility and the US with monopoly concerns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other manifestos such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://humanewebmanifesto.com/&quot;&gt;The Humane Web Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Awareness that search wants us to stay on their domain and that social platforms change and die.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-can-we-do&quot;&gt;What can we do?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;details&gt; 
&lt;summary&gt; Heydon Pickering&#39;s conclusion:&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a content creator, you can reclaim your content from big corporate silos and self-host it. This way your content is your content and you don’t lose anything when Mega Surveillance Media Co decides to kick you off their platform or goes bust. You get to do simple things like edit your content after it’s published and you won’t inadvertently lure people into the clutches of nazi propagandists sharing the same contaminated space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because you publish independently, doesn&#39;t mean you have to be isolated. You can syndicate your content with technologies like RSS, and invite engagement by implementing a backfeed using standards like &lt;a href=&quot;https://indieweb.org/Webmention&quot;&gt;Webmentions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a consumer of content, do not engage with awful people saying awful things. Engaging with them, even to condemn them, only legitimates them and normalizes their bullshit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And finally: the man who entered the Capitol building and had a fatal heart attack did not do so by accidentally electrocuting his own dick with a taser. He just got himself overexcited from all the anger he was being told he should be feeling. Don’t believe everything you read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&quot;https://briefs.video/videos/why-the-indieweb/&quot;&gt;Why The Indieweb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additionally...&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;POSSE: Publish (on your) Own Site, Syndicate Elsewhere.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use web rings. Blogging communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buttons and badges such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://people.pledge.party/&quot;&gt;The people pledge&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://notbyai.fyi/&quot;&gt;Not by AI&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better search on our own site?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Blocking AI?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As web users...&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privacy focussed browsers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different search engines such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://marginalia-search.com/&quot;&gt;Marginalia search&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;details&gt; 
&lt;summary&gt; Transcript&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:05] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Hello there and welcome. Today we&#39;re talking about Indie Web, a people-focused alternative to the corporate web. We&#39;re asking ourselves what is it, and assuming it&#39;s a good thing, how can we get involved? We&#39;d appreciate any input by those who know more than we do, either as a future guest on this show or with comments on our YouTube post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which. Apologies to anybody who is audio only listening. They might be expecting something more on building 11 static sites. But yeah, we did two episodes on that, but they were only suitable for the YouTube channel. So we&#39;re gonna be talking about the indie web today, and as always. David Waumsley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How are you doing, David?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:46] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I&#39;m really good. I&#39;m pleased to be doing this one because, for the last couple, it&#39;s been on me to try and bluff my way through how to use this kind of new platform. And now this is something where, you introduced me to most things with the D web, but I&#39;m still trying to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grapple with what that is and how I can employ that in my work, particularly with client work. But yeah. Yeah, so it&#39;s nice. I can just hand much of this over to you, but we have got some show notes, which I&#39;ve prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:01:17] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. I&#39;ll show the show notes in a minute, but I want to be very careful to caveat mTOR, make the case that I don&#39;t really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Practice what I preach here. I follow the indie web stuff from a distance. and where I can, I, I participate not in terms of, time, but in terms of the, things that are out there. I try to use some of those things, but I am no means an expert in this. But it&#39;s a fascinating thing and it&#39;d be interesting to see how it, grows or otherwise in the future and what the incentives are and how it might be more aligned with, I don&#39;t know, a people first approach to the, internet, that kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shall I share our show notes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:01:55] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, absolutely. For me it&#39;s just that most of the things that come up here are things that you&#39;ve been onto ahead of me or pointed me to, so it&#39;s quite interesting this, yeah. So&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:02:05] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah, and, I get my information from a really broad range of sources. So some of them, really not very well aligned to the indie web, so proprietary social media platforms where these kind of bits of information commonly, but also from listening to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An eclectic range of podcasts around the, internet space. So obviously I primarily do WordPress based content, but listening to podcasts, more about the internet as a whole and what&#39;s going on out there. There&#39;s loads of information, and I think this is a really interesting topic, a topic of our time really, if you&#39;re involved in the internet, but you have a slight suspicion that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporations have taken over and made it into a place which isn&#39;t incentivized for humans, but for algorithms and profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:02:53] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, exactly. So I guess discovering what it is, we&#39;d have to go first to indie web.org. And for those who are viewing, I&#39;m just gonna go over to their site over here, and that&#39;s a title really of our show, is that it&#39;s a people focused alternative to the corporate web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a lot more here. it is. Still a very active thing. As we can see down here, there are still meetups and camps that go on with that. I can see this one here. I can see Jen Simmons here. Yeah. attending one of these, to me it feels like when I. I really haven&#39;t gone through this site, but when I was looking through, how to get started with it, a lot of the resources to get you going were ironically, I guess in the same way we&#39;re doing this on YouTube, but there were YouTube videos, from sort of 10 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I guess the, point behind this hasn&#39;t changed. It&#39;s just hard to judge how active this kind of thing is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:03:53] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. And also geographically, it&#39;s interesting as well. &#39;cause I, I dunno if you can just scroll down once more, and just pause there. If you just hover there for a minute, you&#39;ll see that quite a lot of it is based in, seems to be based at the minute, at least anyway in, in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, but I don&#39;t know if that&#39;s the case. It may be that this is more broadly spread out, but also it does seem to be underpinned by some kind of principle. Again, if you scroll to the top of the page, there&#39;s a link out right to the very, very top. There&#39;s a link to, where it says we are, a community of independent and personal websites, based on principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that obviously is a link. and the principles are owning your domain and using it as your primary online identity. Something I think most people in the WordPress space would align with publishing on your own site first, optionally elsewhere, and owning your own content. So it&#39;s this idea of, just you are the, gatekeeper of it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you don&#39;t first lean into some third party service like Facebook or Twitter. You do all of the publishing on your own content, which then you have control over. And if you choose to do anything, you would then cross post or what have you. from there, and obviously platforms like Mastodon and Activity Pub, the protocol behind it are enabling it so that your website can become a first ci, first citizen on the internet as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, there we go. That&#39;s roughly it. And also&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:05:24] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; something I didn&#39;t pick up on before until I went to Wikipedia. It actually lists out their 10 core principles, which I don&#39;t think we&#39;ll go through them all &#39;cause I don&#39;t know if I understand them all. But, It was interesting. Just before we press record, you were saying, oh, one of the guys who lives quite locally to you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:05:41] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah, not, really know so much, but I&#39;ve had a few interactions with him on social media. So a guy called Kevin Marks and he appeared. The, only reason I know Kevin is I don&#39;t know him, I&#39;ve never met him. I&#39;ve only had literally two or three exchanges on Twitter, but he, he used to appear regularly on a, podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s a video podcast that I watch and listen to called, it used to be called this Week in Google, and now it&#39;s changed to intelligent machines. But the, point is, it&#39;s the same thing. And so I heard of him and he, regularly came on that show and outlined a lot of the different bits and pieces that were going on in the indie website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that was my first point of contact. but there&#39;s Tanex, Selleck, Amber Case, Aaron I dunno how you pronounce that. KY or something like that. Yeah. crystal Beasley and, Kevin there, they seems to be the main proponents, but it seems to be a very human centered, approach, which aligns with what I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&#39;s nice. I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:06:40] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I think my, apart from some of the things that you mentioned, which really didn&#39;t click in as being part of the indie web, my first real introduction was, and I really didn&#39;t know about Hayden Pickering, but he did this video once, going back to 2021 called Why The Indie Web?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. And it is, his videos are all hilarious and he gets, he makes so many points in a very short video. They&#39;re usually only about seven, nearly eight minutes long on this one. And there&#39;s a transcript definitely worth watching. It&#39;s hilarious. It really goes through the whole history of the web and how we are where we are now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and highlights this with, the need to. Take the web, which was something free that we all became accustomed to, to make this into something profitable. So you can sell barbecue sets in his case video. But yeah, and he also has some main points about the indie web, about taking control of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:37] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; it&#39;s I think we need to be forgiving of ourselves. Like that video is really well done, by the way. It&#39;s a perfect encapsulation of the whole thing, but, it&#39;s. I don&#39;t think anybody knew what was gonna happen on the internet. I, don&#39;t think there was like this cabal of people robbing their hands together, aha, it&#39;s gonna go perfectly in this direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It just ended up the way it ended up, because it just did platforms like. Facebook and what have you. Came along and offered us something, which apparently we wanted, and then once it was established that we wanted it, the profit margin and, the incalculable easy for me to say, incalculable wealth that could be made from a platform which had no boundaries of geography, seemingly no ceiling on the number of users that were prepared to spend hours of their day involved in that platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And is it any wonder that. It became a corporate thing and billions of dollars were generated and that whole profit motive then seems to have a life of its own. And it gets worse. And it gets worse. And we are where we are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:47] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, exactly. I think a lot of talks on it, and I think possibly in that video of Hayden, he says, and now to introduce the villain capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in some ways we didn&#39;t really see it. We, see it now retrospectively as that because we realize that when you put something like the internet and what it&#39;s become over time, that obviously it&#39;s gonna get distorted by the, current mode of capitalism. people need to earn money from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&#39;s distorted this kind of essentially free web that we were given, to use for our own communication. It&#39;s got lost, In these big Yeah. Big giants who own the algorithms and obviously, change the way that all of us behave and the types of communication we have each other with each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. And&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:09:38] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;think, we&#39;ve slowly but surely given over our perception of what&#39;s normal on the internet. if you rewind right to the beginning when it was CERN and The, really going right back up on it and things like that where people were just academically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curiously. Oh hyperlinks. Tim Burners Lee. Oh, look at that. I can put a link behind this word and that will open up a page somewhere else on this diaspora of servers. And it, that was just faab fabulously philanthropic. It felt like, there&#39;s, there was no profit motive. And then. People discovered, oh, you can set cookies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, that&#39;s interesting. cookies I think probably were in initially just for state maintaining are you logged in? Are you not logged in? And then clever people thought, oh, we can do a little bit more with that. We can, we can track you across things and suddenly there&#39;s a profit motive for capturing your attention and keeping you on there longer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, we are where we are, but luckily. The underpinnings haven&#39;t changed. The tech, the technologies, the stack behind the internet may is the same. Yes. So we don&#39;t have to keep going in the direction that the corporations are pulling us. We can just reign it back and go back to it just being a bunch of links without cookies and without tracking and without, the millions of dollars generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:11:02] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; we&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:11:03] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; found&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:11:03] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; the need to do that. And big corporations like Google, Microsoft, Adobe, all of them are involved in. The building and, and working together on browsers, the building of CSS. And, in some ways, the, web is stronger than it&#39;s ever been because we all realize that it is what it was intended to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something for everybody on everything, this one, standard that we all use. So I think in some ways that&#39;s backing forth. So I think, it. In some ways the next question I put on the notes here, which we might as well move into, is this was my sense of it when going to the indie web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I hear about it. I, for me, it was Hayden&#39;s video. I go and look up the site of what&#39;s this indie web people are talking of, and then I don&#39;t really get a sense of whether it&#39;s growing and it&#39;s still very difficult to know that as a sort of movement, but. You said this, and I wrote it as exactly the same notes when we were talking earlier, that I don&#39;t think it can be measured as a sort of movement of the numbers of people or the meetings that they have there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It shows itself through different reactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:12:09] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, and I, my, my end. Expectation is that it, might be growing, but I, would imagine it&#39;s growing at a fairly slow rate. And what I mean by that is you don&#39;t really hear the mainstream talking about any of this stuff. It does seem to be, a collection, a small collection of people who are interested in this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And honestly, if you ask me to give you any commentary about. Almost any subject that humans talk about. I&#39;ve got no interest in 99.9% of those subjects. There&#39;s a handful of things that I&#39;m interested in, and I love those and I talk about &#39;em. the same&#39;s true about this, isn&#39;t it? Most people, you switch on your phone or you switch on the computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing they care about is does it work and not, what&#39;s the moral basis for it or what is the, underlying protocol and where&#39;s the data going? It&#39;s if I click this, can I buy it? Okay, that works. Who cares? I don&#39;t because it, there&#39;s no, there&#39;s no violence associated with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s no impediment to it working the fact that your data&#39;s being consumed here, there, and everywhere. I honestly think most people do not care so long as it works, and they&#39;re very happy with the trade off of you. Show me a ton of ads and I&#39;ll try to be inoculated against them. I&#39;ll try to ignore them, but if it&#39;s free, you show me ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s fine. I think most people have that impression. But you and I are slightly different, I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:13:34] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I think you are ahead of me on that one because I didn&#39;t care too much about that kind of stuff. And there is a kind of irony. I mean it&#39;s slightly off the point here, we don&#39;t have the same kind of high streets that you would have certainly in the uk, that there was in the old days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you think. You don&#39;t know at the time, do you? You, work at a shop, you&#39;re busy, you want to buy other stuff from other shops, but you are busy working and stuff, so you buy from Amazon. Amazon then slowly starts to put. That shop outta business eventually. You are all outta business and you are only all buying from Amazon, But it&#39;s also, it&#39;s, you don&#39;t know you&#39;re destroying your own&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:10] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; industry yourself if you, yeah, but we&#39;re also in a curious time, like if you think about it, mass communication, I guess really you could begin that with something like the telephone, but the telephone was very much a one-to-one and it didn&#39;t have a, like a, it wasn&#39;t recording anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It really is only in the last 15 or so years. That, yes, people have been able to s have some sort of global conversation, like normal people. Obviously if you&#39;re the prime minister of the UK or the president of the us you&#39;ve been able to have those conversations, but most of us don&#39;t. And now we&#39;re thrust into this scenario where you can, message people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anywhere in the world. And, I&#39;m not sure as a species, we&#39;re quite ready for it, frankly, in rewind the clock, I don&#39;t know, a hundred years, 200 years, something like that, which in the, in, in the history of. Our species is not that long. You probably didn&#39;t really get much further than your front door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a typical year, you might wander a few hundred yards here, there and everywhere. There&#39;s no trains, there&#39;s no cars. Would&#39;ve been an effort to own a horse and get anywhere on that would, it&#39;s still taken days, but the point is your world was. Much smaller. Yes. And we, have this impression that because it&#39;s now bigger and we&#39;re involved in global things, and I can, you are in Goa, I&#39;m in Yorkshire, north Yorkshire, and yet here we are talking as if we&#39;re next door to, literally you could be sat next to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can hear every word you&#39;re saying and every breath and everything. It&#39;s, yeah. Is that normal? I, don&#39;t know if that&#39;s. I don&#39;t know if that&#39;s a good idea in the end,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:15:49] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; but for us it feels like, I feel like I&#39;m in the UK anyway when I&#39;m talking to you because culturally I&#39;m still Yeah, very much in the UK and that so full of that kind of news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But anyways, yeah, so what&#39;s a couple? I was trying to get a few of the things where I think maybe the movement is shifting and I put some things down here. Which I think is quite interesting is, these kinda shifts that we&#39;ve seen to say Blue Sky using the AT Protocol and Mastodon, which again, you were really early on in using Mastodon, where I thought, what is this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is using Activity Pope, which is a standard, isn&#39;t it? It&#39;s a W three C standard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:16:29] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. So this is the idea of replacing platforms with protocols. So instead of using Twitter or X, you use. Activity pub. so you know, anybody can use the activity pub protocol and build their own thing on top of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So Mastodon isn&#39;t what&#39;s powering the technology, it&#39;s the activity pub protocol. And you&#39;ve seen moves in the WordPress space. We have the activity pub protocol, sorry, plugin. You have things like pixel fed and various things built on top. And so the idea is there&#39;s this interoperable layer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and it&#39;s standards based. Anybody can, work with it. you can own your own instance of Mastodon, but the protocol is the thing that you&#39;re interested in, not the platform. And at the at, or I think it&#39;s at Protocol, which is the one that Blue Sky&#39;s using is, is similar but different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the, one of the things that it hasn&#39;t yet done as of recording this, it hasn&#39;t, it hasn&#39;t gone. All in, in the same way that Activity Pub has, for example, I don&#39;t think you can move your account yet from one platform to another. so you don&#39;t own your data in that way. But the intention is that it will happen, but it hasn&#39;t happened yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think they&#39;re trying to get their docs in a row, but this is, these two are moves to open up social, interactions. and any interaction, really any kind of activity on the internet and it to be built upon an open platform, which anybody can use. And so you can go to Mastodon and you won&#39;t be bombarded with ads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s no algorithm there trying to game your feed. You basically get a chronological feed of content produced by people in the order in which they produced it. So if you follow no people, your timeline is empty. If you follow 12 people, it will be fairly quiet. If you follow a thousand people, it&#39;ll be noisy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but there won&#39;t be an algorithm trying to insert an ad or trying to say, this post will capture your attention. Let&#39;s put that in front of you &#39;cause you&#39;ll stay on for a bit longer. None of that. The thing is you could build that on top of activity pop, you could build that platform, but I expect not too many people would want to use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But anyway,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:47] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah. And I suspect all the big moves to Masteron and Blue Sky. Blue sky particularly, I think coming so quickly is, due to the way that Twitter had gone, and the direction with that. And I think, it&#39;s. Perhaps the same. we&#39;ll look to those big players, but rather than being something that the indie web people think, no, I shouldn&#39;t have these algorithms affected me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It really comes down to a sort of breaking point. The politics or really, or the disagree. for, me,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:16] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; the break, that I needed was just realizing that my attention, I was not able to compete against the algorithm. I literally was unable to stop. Using the phone. I&#39;ve, decided to call the phone from now on the rectangle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s what I&#39;m gonna refer to it as. So I, refer to people staring at the rectangle. &#39;cause it gives it that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:43] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; what the heck&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:44] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; I don&#39;t know, like very third party It&#39;s bleak and it&#39;s a bit like something at the obelisk of 2001, a Space Odyssey or something like that. But, I was unable to stop doing it and I would be doing it at all times of the day, which I knew four in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why the heck am I doing this? And I realized that it was because these algorithms had completely captured me and it was not in my interest to be staring at the, rectangle at four in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:20:11] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; And I think something which I certainly became aware of, I lost my Facebook. Access. so it was hacked in some way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somebody managed to do something, there was a security issue there, and, there was no way I could really convince them to put me back. And I had, a group which was growing there, so they, suddenly I couldn&#39;t communicate to this group that. I&#39;ve gone, the person running this group and that, that was the thing that really attracted me to things like Facebook was only the groups and a special collection of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I realized as I think more people do, as we see them come and go, that we know these platforms will eventually die. I. and others will take over. and if it&#39;s important for you to own your content, then you probably need to be looking. If it&#39;s disposable, then that&#39;s fine, isn&#39;t it? But if you, feel there&#39;s some value in keeping it and having an ownership over it, you do need to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:11] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; That&#39;s right. It&#39;s a really, peculiar trade off though, isn&#39;t it? because the platforms like Facebook, for example, have captured all the audience. I, my intuition is that Facebook might be in decline, but that is purely intuition. It&#39;s not based upon any data. but if you have your congregation for want of a better word, over on Facebook and like you, something happens and you lose access, that&#39;s gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it&#39;s completely gone. Growing an audience outside of Facebook, I think is really hard because Yeah. Or or YouTube or TikTok or whatever it may be. Because they do such a great job of if you are producing content, which their algorithm says, look, this is making, waves, therefore it&#39;s making our platform money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They will then push the audience for you. They will make the audience for you. Yes. And so it&#39;s a real trade off. Trying to do it yourself is much harder. But obviously you own it, and if TikTok decides to shut you down, it doesn&#39;t matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:12] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, there&#39;s a point actually later on that we&#39;ll get to that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there&#39;s any other points that we put on, whether it&#39;s growing or that, I put in maybe, state, sorry. the state interventions, the things that we&#39;re seeing with the eu with data protection, accessibility, and certainly with the US getting, having monopoly concerns over the likes of what Apple and Google do as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;is that part of the, in some ways it&#39;s legislating against monopolies, which is what we&#39;re. I, guess everybody&#39;s worried about,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:43] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah, I don&#39;t really know, actually. obviously the things like the GDPR and the concern about where your data is held, if you are, typing on a keyboard in Germany, but the, result of that typing in gets saved to some server in the us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, think, that seems to be a topic of growing concern. It&#39;s so ephemeral though for most people to like, how do you capture that in the minds of most people? How do you get people to care about that? Because all that you care about is that the next time you go in, the pixels come back. I. Onto your screen and so okay, who did what When I wrote to John six months ago, let me just go back to that conversation with Jeff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There it is. There&#39;s the conversation I had with John. I remember what we said. Now it&#39;s like, where was that data? I don&#39;t care. I care, but I don&#39;t think most people care. but that does seem to be a part. And, we&#39;re in a fairly fractured time in terms of inter international diplomacy and politics and things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&#39;d be interesting to see how these lines get drawn and whether. Whether we will be siloing our data inside of our own national boundaries more and more. But I don&#39;t know if it&#39;s a part of it. It feels like it is a part of it. Anybody that&#39;s watching this can tell us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:24:00] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; And I think definitely what seems a part of it to me was, at the same time there was a lot of, confidence chats that I saw with a, a renewed interest and an encouragement by many to get creative again, as we did in the early web with HTML and CSS, and make your own personal sites, have your own ownership there. And, again, I something that you put me on to first. there was a newsletter Own your web. I&#39;m just gonna Oh yeah, that&#39;s right on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. By met, Matt Ott there and yeah, I like this. That&#39;s, yeah, it&#39;s great. it just. It just encourages people that they can just build these websites together, as we did in the early days. And people have forgotten about it now. It&#39;s been taken over by everybody feels the easiest way is a, web builder or something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, it&#39;s a really good series. and that led me on to realizing there were other services I wasn&#39;t aware of. Things like, glitch here, which is a little bit like, GitHub pages or, Netlify, which we use, but it&#39;s really a bit more aimed at free hosting for people who want to do their own basic sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get started with HDML, maybe start with some templates, levity, which we&#39;ve been talking around is, on the remix here for easy blogging with Eleventy is in here. So again, it&#39;s something that&#39;s been around for a while, but. Not hugely taken off though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:25:28] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; It&#39;s interesting how, like how we&#39;ve entered this era I, and you keep calling it the subscription economy where you just pay a little bit and you have access to all this stuff, but you don&#39;t own any of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in the case of music, you might pay Spotify $10 a month or something and once that elapses, the music&#39;s all gone. Whereas when you were a child and I, was a child, you, purchased the music and it was yours forever. And sure enough, you didn&#39;t have access to all the music and you thought long and hard about which CDs you were going to buy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But thinking about it, in my childhood growing up, we, rented nothing. We had a mortgage on the house that we lived in, but everything, all transactions were a case of you pay for the thing and you get the thing and it&#39;s now yours to own. Whereas now we&#39;ve definitely, there&#39;s a shift to, okay, I&#39;ll pay you a small amount on a monthly basis or an annual basis, or what have you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the trade off is that you won&#39;t ever own it, but it&#39;ll be yours during the period in which you are paying me. Of course the problem is when that, when you no longer can pay it, like you either choose not to pay it or you run outta money or you retire and suddenly realize that all these bills that you&#39;ve been able to service for all this time are no longer possible, and suddenly all your access to the music is gone and you probably would&#39;ve been better off building up a record collection all those years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it&#39;s interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:26:56] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, absolutely. I, must, the other thing that I linked to on there, which I think is great &#39;cause it won&#39;t come up in search very Oh yeah. For people, which again, is fairly new and it&#39;s somebody just putting a starter for people who just wanna get back to those early days when you just wanna build something that you own yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I feel there is a big. Encouragement if you like. It&#39;s almost, it almost feels a little bit like the seventies just when punk came in. This idea that people could just get back and make music with three chords themselves with a bit of attitude rather than having to know all the sophisticated stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it feels a little bit like it&#39;s encouraging that, and for people to be a little bit more, as they were the websites. Most of the designs we do them to a formula. We&#39;ve read something like StoryBrand and we know we need to write a certain type of headline and have this in a certain order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;our three benefits need to be listed after our value proposition. And in the early days when people had, geo cities and even MySpace to a certain degree, they were a bit wacky with their designs. so there&#39;s that going on. The idea of, showing your creativity through your own personal site and owning the data and sharing with the world, just any.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interests and thoughts that you have. Yeah, and I think that&#39;s a loss, the idea that people, will go and set up Facebook &#39;cause it&#39;s easier to communicate with their friends. But there are less people now who, without any commercial reason, will set it up just as a way of self-expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:28:25] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. It really is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, the internet is such a power for good, isn&#39;t it? It&#39;s such a, yeah. It&#39;s an amazing resource that humanity has. And it does seem a, shame, honestly. Looking back, I suppose to some extent it was inevitable that money was gonna get involved and take over the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it will be interesting to see if a proportion of the people can, can wrestle that maybe this isn&#39;t a situation where we&#39;re trying to, we&#39;re trying to make it either or. Yeah, it&#39;s more a situation of, okay, those that wanna roll their own and do the indie web thing, they, yes, they can do that. And the corporate stuff that can carry on as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we can have a bit of both. Maybe that&#39;s the, sort of ideal, yeah. Seesaw of it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:10] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; And I think it&#39;s, it is in there. I think it&#39;s with the indie web, an alternative. And I think everybody needs an alternative. We, and that&#39;s it, isn&#39;t there? I think, we always need, I think commercialism has pushed forward the web to being what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We couldn&#39;t imagine it being initially to what it is now, so it&#39;s needed there. But there is this point where it feels like if you&#39;re only on the web to server, a corporate, it&#39;s lost a lot. yeah. So what can we do? Let&#39;s have a, have I covered the points there? Oh, I did want to mention here, I&#39;ll bring it up here to the.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Humane Human Web. Hu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:48] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Humane. Sorry. Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:49] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; apologies. Humane Web&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:50] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yesterday. There you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:51] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, there&#39;s a lot of things like this. So this comes from Michelle Barker Set this up. she writes a lot on CSS and does some talks and that she&#39;s, I love that website by the way. You did. It&#39;s funny, you really like some bold stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see your, you, I laugh that. Yeah. Funny enough, I think you&#39;ve a heart, you this personal expression stuff that you see with the insight. So you, always react to those. yeah. Yeah. yeah, so I, I think there&#39;s an overlap with lots of people doing these kind of various different things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So her point is her point on the top there, what it&#39;s becoming, that the web is becoming hostile to humans, that people have been tracked and that their privacy is routinely violated. that search is just gonna giving you ads and everything. So her kind of take on it, is also from. Not just where the data goes, but also the eco-friendliness of stuff, and I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s one of her big things. To make lighter websites that don&#39;t burn the planet is one of her big things on that, but made for humans again. And similarly, there are other things, let me just bring these up. People are wearing, taking badges and things like the people pledge. I, dunno if this is a good thing or not, whether it&#39;s just helping this particular domain to get a lot of attention or whether it&#39;s this kind of nice idea that you put a badge on your site, which is saying that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You stand for these things, you&#39;re not gonna discriminate it or devalue anyone on the basis of their age, gender, identity, and other things. Like one, which I&#39;m tempted to put on any site that I do, which is not by ai. yeah, exactly. Yeah. So you can have little badges like that. I don&#39;t know if that&#39;s connected with the, in a way it seems the same sort of move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s like positioning against a corporate direction, if you like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:44] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. It&#39;s hard to encapsulate, isn&#39;t it? Because this whole movement isn&#39;t summed up in one trite little sentence. there&#39;s just some feeling in the back of my head about what it is, and. I can&#39;t encapsulate it perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you, showed me a website and, and you asked me, does this align, I&#39;m not sure does it, I&#39;m not entirely sure, but there&#39;s a feeling and it, feels a little bit. philanthropic. It feels a little bit, I don&#39;t know, left-leaning for want of a better word. It seems to be more all embracing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s definitely not about making loads of money. I&#39;m wondering secretly if we got all of the people involved in the indie web on a deep and profound level and, ask them, would you like to live in a commune? I wa I wonder what the answer would be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:34] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; so yeah, so we&#39;ve got, we&#39;re back to some Hi hippie 60 times up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, that&#39;s right. Hugging trees. Yeah. It is a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:41] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; bit, don&#39;t, it is a bit of that though. There is some of that sprinkled over the top of this without a doubt. Yeah. Okay. what can we do? Oh, sorry. Carry on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:50] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, no, it&#39;s the same thing. I, won&#39;t read out. it is. Fascinating Hayden Picker In&#39;s conclusion, but it&#39;s a lot to read out there what he says we should do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I&#39;ll leave that on the site there. there was something which I was introduced to, actually it was by LA Zach Leatherman, the author of 11 two. We&#39;ve been talking about. He did a talk, I think about five years ago or something on this, and he introduced me to this concept of Posse, which stands for Publish on your own site, syndicate elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love that. Which. Yeah, and I think that&#39;s something that you can start to do, can&#39;t you? With these protocols where you can start to say, okay, the, canonical. Link, the URL is yours and then your content goes out to all these other services to attract things. And yeah, he cites an example actually, Jeremy, Keith and his site, he&#39;s very good at being able to set these things up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So almost he talks about it as well a lot. He&#39;s a big, Defender of the indie web. Of course, as you might expect with him, I can&#39;t really show you any examples of it, but basically, no, it&#39;s very much tied up with a band in a pub at the moment, isn&#39;t it? Yeah. Yes. But that&#39;s really how he&#39;s running his site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He, he, it, always stays with him on his domain and it gets sent everywhere else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:34:13] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; there is a. I was just gonna say there&#39;s a lot of moves in WordPress at the moment to make this possible. So the PO protocol, which is built by a chap called Mattias Fle, he, he&#39;s building it. He&#39;s been, he now works for Automatic, but the idea is very much of that, it&#39;s that you publish on your own website and then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It. Your website is the account on an activity pub related platform like Mastodon or Pixel Fed. So you publish it there and it&#39;s not cross posting, so it&#39;s not when you hit publish, it&#39;s not then pushing it out to Mastodon. It is. The Mastodon account. The website? Yes. The account. And that&#39;s hard to get your head around &#39;cause we&#39;re not used to that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then in the future, the, it&#39;s, built or being built. The idea is that if somebody comments on Mastodon or pixeled from that or any other platform on the, activity pod protocol, those comments come back into your WordPress post or page. And then if you reply that all gets sent out and it&#39;s all happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You, you&#39;ve got that conversation on your own. Yes, your own website. It&#39;s fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:26] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I had a little look at that I was interested in. &#39;cause it wasn&#39;t high numbers for the plugin that goes that No, That allows you to do that easy. And I&#39;m also looking at it because we&#39;ve decided to not go the WordPress route and do it with 11 for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. I want to see if we can do this very same thing as well with us to have it. As a kind of comedy system to make sure that, there&#39;s this whole&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:45] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; thing called web mentions, but Exactly, that&#39;s as far as I can take you with that. I don&#39;t really know how that would be implemented or what that really encapsulates, but I know that in this community, in the sort of indie web, community web mentions is, that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes. Yep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:00] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; And then there are methods as well. I saw one for being able to, it doesn&#39;t matter what platform you&#39;re using, as long as you&#39;ve got the control where you can use the at protocol from Blue Sky to use Blue Sky as your kind of commenting system,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:14] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; I guess that would have a very similar endeavor and that&#39;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some, and I know now there&#39;s a ton of, work being done for people bridging those two protocols, so literal bridges, so that one connects perfectly with the other so that the two. Protocols bind together so that you could, I don&#39;t know, have something that links over to Mastodon and Blue Sky and can publish onto them both at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:40] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; just news here, I, it&#39;s very hard when we talk about a lot of these things, so there&#39;s usually a question. It&#39;s a bit like SEO where there&#39;ll be articles saying it&#39;s dead, and no it isn&#39;t. It&#39;s very much alive and stuff, and it&#39;s things like, web rings. We, they were there in the early days of the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web before we had Google and the, we would find those connections. I think some of the bigger corporations run some of these, web rings, but that&#39;s something we can do in blogging communities. They still exist out there and I started to find a bit of a few of those, but. To be honest, I was so used to just going to search to find all my information from the web that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:37:22] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:37:22] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; unless I knew about this, it&#39;s unlikely I&#39;d find it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I think it has been. And something I&#39;m quite keen, I think, to do myself a little bit more with this is to make sure you create genuine links with people so you can use things like web mentions and stuff by. just naturally mentioning, why you are writing about something comes from somebody else&#39;s work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you mentioned them. yep. They become aware of it. You promote them and somebody takes from yours and it&#39;s this nice circle. Of self-promotion, if you like, that doesn&#39;t rely on gaming,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:37:58] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. It&#39;s like robbing one another&#39;s backs in a way, isn&#39;t it? Yes. It feels a little bit more like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Yeah. And you&#39;re not doing it because of, because you&#39;ll get a search result boost out of it. You&#39;re doing it &#39;cause it&#39;s the right thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:38:11] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, exactly. And it, also helped, you, you don&#39;t have to explain from the start again. if you&#39;re working on somebody else&#39;s work, you want to lead them to that so they can see where you started from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I think it just seems a much more. Sensible way to communicate with each other. So anyway, we&#39;ve been going off for some time, so I&#39;ll probably speed up,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:38:30] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; aren&#39;t I? Okay. Yeah. I mean we, yeah, probably we should wrap it up fairly soon, but, just, one quick thing. Apropos of nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. And that is to say that you were talking about search engines just now I have, I&#39;ve I. Ditched Google, as my search engine of choice and I&#39;ve gone over to using, oh, you&#39;ve got it there. yeah, cgi, I dunno if that&#39;s how you pronounce it. I believe that this was started by somebody who used to create a WordPress plugin, and I&#39;ve forgotten which one it was, but it&#39;s probably one that you and I have both heard of and they moved out the WordPress space and, and.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the, trade off here is that I have to pay for it, but the good thing about it is that I&#39;m, not hoping to keep my search engine results for any length of time. So I don&#39;t feel like I want to own, any of the data that I put into this. But the, benefit is that you get a, an unsponsored set of search results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They don&#39;t keep track on what you do, and you can prioritize certain domains. So say for example, I was searching for, oh, I don&#39;t know, like socks or something, I might be able to put in a bunch of local websites to me and say, actually, when you&#39;re giving the search resource, only select those websites to, to search through so you can curate the search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, in that way it inoculates CGI. From, from that bias, which we have no doubt is in the Google search results. you can, definitely get a sense that promoted content, sponsored content comes out at the top, which it always does. You can see that right at the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so I&#39;m gonna try this out for a little bit and we&#39;ll see how we go. I can&#39;t say I can&#39;t endorse it &#39;cause I&#39;ve not used it for long enough. I only been using it for two or three weeks, but I&#39;m gonna give it a go. Yeah, and I think it&#39;s $120 a year. I think they&#39;ve got a 30 day trial or something if you wanna give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I, I think it&#39;s a good thing for me to be doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:40:28] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, no, I think it&#39;s fascinating. I think with Google, as we, realized, obviously they did it with things like encouraging us to use schema and rich snippets, which they don&#39;t need so much now with ai, but in some ways we realize now it&#39;s to keep them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To keep us all on their domain rather than the original deal, which is, we&#39;ll do what you want Google, to make our sites, search friendly. Absolutely. And you send us the traffic, Yeah. Let&#39;s go in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:40:54] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. Yeah. give it a go. cgi.com. See what you think. Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:40:58] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I&#39;ll mention another one, which I put down here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;cause I, in fact, I put it down as a note there, as web users, we can try different search engines. You were already ahead of me, but I saw somebody else mention talking about new web. Marginalia Now, it&#39;s probably not that useful, but it&#39;s, you can search and I can&#39;t because honestly I&#39;ve, I don&#39;t know it very well to be able to demonstrate it and plus we&#39;re on audio, so I won&#39;t, but it basically, it will give you a totally, you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can search, by the sort of topic that you want. And I think I, I&#39;m not quite sure how it works, but it&#39;s, the person who was recommending this as an approach said and they really summed up for me, what I feel about Google these days is often the sort of stuff I&#39;m interested in. I have to work through loads and loads of stuff, so I was trying to find that site I was promoting earlier, which is the HTML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is for people. Couldn&#39;t remember what it was exactly called the domain, tried Google Search, knew it was a fairly recent thing, couldn&#39;t find it. And what everything I was listed really was a good SEO article by a, big corporation. So it would be GoDaddies, article on HDML, or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And pretty much everything was a corporate thing. So I think. Marginality. What was Margin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:42:16] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; or margin? Margin. Marginal margin. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:42:19] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. Marginal. Yeah. Yeah, I&#39;ve got it. I had it up here, didn&#39;t I? A moment ago. There we are. Yeah. It doesn&#39;t look particularly friendly, but I think it just allows you to, I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Search for sites. it&#39;s built really for the indie web type thing. It&#39;s where&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:42:34] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:42:34] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; in the same way. So yeah. I didn&#39;t know it existed, but I just think that&#39;s quite fascinating. yeah, that is. Yeah. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:42:40] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:42:41] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Gosh, the other thing is something I&#39;m. If I&#39;m gonna ask a client, actually I&#39;m gonna speak to a client the day after tomorrow about their new site in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m gonna ask &#39;em if they want me to block ai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:42:53] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Oh, interesting. whether or not you&#39;ll be successful in that endeavor is, up for question because I dunno how honorable the, the robot stop text, is yes, but certainly it&#39;s worth a shot. What&#39;s the, what&#39;s your intuition there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you get the feeling that most people don&#39;t want to contribute their own content into an AI LLM?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:15] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I don&#39;t know. I don&#39;t, it is the first time I&#39;m gonna ask. It&#39;s just crossed my mind. I realize there&#39;s a beautiful list that I found of, various ways of blocking somebody from the WordPress&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:25] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, haven&#39;t done anything about that. my content is just out there and presumably it gets scraped. it&#39;s not gonna be scraped or have a great authority, but I, haven&#39;t really. I&#39;ve drawn a conclusion about that, but it feels to me that certainly if you are a content creator, the voices are getting louder about that not being, especially if you are a creative, you&#39;re a musician or something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does seem like a bit of a shame that. As a species, we&#39;ve decided that, something that you can get, for one us sense, a song created by a website that socked up all the songs that are out there in existence, that doesn&#39;t seem, particularly well aligned with humanity. no, I would be very surprised if the indie web movement is particularly well aligned with the AI movement, but I could be wrong about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:44:18] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. Oh, I think, most will not. Yes. Yes. It will not want a lot of people. I think the people I follow now are not keen. They&#39;re very keen to, to say that we haven&#39;t used AI with this one. Or they&#39;re very keen as well to point out that the cost of an AI search is so much greater than a normal search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which led me to the other point that I thought about what we could do. And I think, when it comes to our site, content site, we hadn&#39;t even talked about it before. And I was reminded by Bob Monor from the 11 two community that you can, on static sites have a fairly good search these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I think this is a topic for us later to see how we could maybe implement some of these kind of indie web techniques. Things like, oh yeah, I&#39;d&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:45:02] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; that, I, would love to know how to implement those. So if, we can do that would be. Wonderful. Yeah. and you never know, the indie web community might, might be able to get something out of that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great. Yeah, I think we&#39;ve come to the end. I think So let me, find my mouse and, put us back on the screen like that. So that&#39;s it. this one&#39;s going out as an audio as well as we&#39;ll stick it on the, is it going on the YouTube as well? Yes it is. Yeah, everything all there isn&#39;t that ironic. I know the irony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re gonna, we&#39;re gonna use YouTube, but we&#39;re gonna slight rain on a wedding day. Slack them off at the same time, so there we go. That&#39;s it. We&#39;ll see you next time. Thanks David. That was really interesting. Yeah, enjoyed that. Bye bye-Bye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt; </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Building with an 11ty starter sites and headless WordPress</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/7/" />
    <updated>2025-02-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/7/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;building-with-an-11ty-starter-sites-and-headless-wordpress&quot;&gt;Building with an 11ty starter sites and headless WordPress&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;starter-sites&quot;&gt;Starter Sites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;11ty has something similar to WordPress themes called starter sites. It also has plugins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some places to look for themes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://11tybundle.dev/starters/&quot;&gt;11ty Bundle&lt;/a&gt;. A fabulous place for all things 11ty by &lt;a href=&quot;https://bobmonsour.com/&quot;&gt;Bob Monsour&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jamstackthemes.dev/#ssg=eleventy&quot;&gt;JamStack Themes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/docs/starter/&quot;&gt;The 11ty site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starter sites are typically plain for us to add our own CSS, but there are &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/CloudCannon/campus-spark-bookshop-template&quot;&gt;exceptions&lt;/a&gt;. Some are created around Tailwind or Bootstrap or include javaScript framework intergration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3 considered suited to the show&#39;s website:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/11ty/eleventy-base-blog&quot;&gt;The 11ty Base Blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/madrilene/eleventy-excellent&quot;&gt;Eleventy Excellent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/scottsweb/elva&quot;&gt;Elva&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eventy Excellent by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lenesaile.com/en/&quot;&gt;Lene Saile&lt;/a&gt; was the closest fit as it used CUBE CSS, Paul Irish&#39;s Lite YouTube Embed and has a strew of great features.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;11ty-as-a-static-frontend-for-wordpress&quot;&gt;11ty as a static frontend for WordPress.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andy Bell has a couple of articles on &lt;a href=&quot;https://bell.bz/i-hooked-up-eleventy-to-wordpress-api/&quot;&gt;hooking 11ty to WordPress&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bell.bz/importing-eleventy-content-into-wordpress/&quot;&gt;importing 11ty content to WordPress&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These talk about using WordPress plugins to tell hosts to rebuild 11ty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mikeaparicio.com/posts/2023-11-07-using-wordpress-as-a-headless-cms-for-eleventy/&quot;&gt;Using Wordpress as a headless CMS for Eleventy by Mike Aparicio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://davedavies.dev/post/how-to-use-11ty-with-headless-wordpress/&quot;&gt;How to use 11ty with Headless WordPress and deploy to Netlify by Dave Davies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;The mentioned WordPress plugins have not been updated in 4 years. We also have to consider the number concurrent builds our static hosting plan allow if letting clients update. Netlify only allows one on the free plan.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;an-alternative&quot;&gt;An alternative&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 11ty &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/docs/migrate/wordpress/#use-@11ty/import&quot;&gt;importer&lt;/a&gt; that can graps WordPress posts from the WordPress REST API. It works out of the box with the 11ty base blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;early-conclusion&quot;&gt;Early conclusion:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A WP notify plugin could be used as a prompt to devs to do a manual update, but imagine someone repeatedly publishing to correct typos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automated updates require WP plugin dependencies and or skills to manage that. For a simple blog setting up Decap&#39;s free CMS seem easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the cost, technical complexity and maintenance overhead of headless along with the growth of static and uncertaintly in WordPress it seem this is likey to be in decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-with-the-11ty-base-blog&quot;&gt;Building with the 11ty base blog&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learning more about 11ty by using the starter site from its author &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zachleat.com/&quot;&gt;Zach Leatherman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-pros&quot;&gt;The Pros&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Preconfigured 11ty plugins: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/docs/plugins/rss/&quot;&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/docs/plugins/image/&quot;&gt;Image Transform&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/docs/plugins/navigation/&quot;&gt;Navigation&lt;/a&gt;,  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/docs/plugins/syntaxhighlight/&quot;&gt;Syntax Highlighting&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/docs/plugins/id-attribute/&quot;&gt;Id Attribute &lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/docs/plugins/html-base/&quot;&gt;HTML &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;base&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple Stylesheet to extend or replace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Updated and well documented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If using AI, tell it you are extending the 11ty base blog and it adjusts it&#39;s solution!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-cons&quot;&gt;The Cons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need time to understand how the plugins work and how it is configured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;missed-last-time&quot;&gt;Missed last time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using slugs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding conditionals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/docs/languages/webc/&quot;&gt;WebC&lt;/a&gt; (web components).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Transcript&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:05] &lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Hello there. This is the second video looking at the 11 static sites generator from the perspective of WordPress users. In the first episode, we built a simple site from scratch, and in this we are looking at 11 starter sites and some of the more advanced features. David has begun rebuilding the show site using the 11ty base blog and can share this experience of it as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we&#39;ll also talk a little bit about using 11ty as a static front. End to WordPress. So I mentioned David. There he is. How are you doing, David? You right? Yeah, I&#39;m&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:40] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; really good. we&#39;ve got a lot to cover with this. We do. I probably, and I&#39;m nervous again because it&#39;s outta my depth with this stuff, and, we&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:49] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; will forgive&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:49] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:50] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; It&#39;s a bit of live&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:51] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; stuff going on again. yeah. So should we bring up our show notes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:55] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, let&#39;s put the bits and pieces on the screen. There we go. So&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:01:00] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; we&#39;re actually using here, what we started working on, which you. The place for our, a new site. So it&#39;s on my local host at the moment, so I&#39;m using that for the notes and it&#39;s coming from the base blog, which we&#39;ve mentioned over here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&#39;ve done a, little bit of styling on it, but not much already. I think probably the first thing, just to note for anybody who is coming from WordPress like us is that, Levi to, does have something similar to WordPress themes in that they call these kind of starter sites, and it also has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;plugins as well. but it&#39;s different. it hasn&#39;t had 20 years of, arguing over what a theme of a plugin should do, but, yeah. but they&#39;re quite different on that. So let&#39;s quickly talk about where you might be able to get one of these teams. &#39;cause that was the first thing I thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll use a starter theme to get us. Go in and effectively I ruled it out and then came back to the idea of using the base blog. So let&#39;s talk about other themes that are around. I wanted to mention this one. I&#39;ll bring this up, which is the 11 bundle, because honestly I wouldn&#39;t have got as far as I have if it wasn&#39;t thanks to, and I&#39;ll bring his site up as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bob Mons, I think, I hope that&#39;s how you say his name. But he does this great job. He&#39;s got great articles. Himself. So he&#39;s definitely somebody to follow if you&#39;re into eleventy. But he does list his own sort of chosen kind of updated list of other things here. And what&#39;s nice about is you can see which version of eleventy it&#39;s using on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but also I just wanted to mention &#39;cause it&#39;s got this fire hose here, which has pretty much all the articles that are coming on about 11 and there&#39;s about one a day on these. So definitely worth taking a look at that. And out of interest, actually, the ones that I considered really suitable for our show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if we were using a starter site, were the ones that are first listed here. So 11ty base blog, 11ty Excellence, and Alva here as well. So that was good. Also, another place which I discovered, which doesn&#39;t add much on it, is this. placed JAMstack themes. So you can look at the 11tywo ones. Here we&#39;ve got Astro, which is more popular, not many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s only 19 listed, but Astro, which is very popular at the moment and has 18. So I&#39;m not sure how updated that is. So you get a, screenshot of this and where to go from GitHub to get it and a demo, whether one&#39;s available. And finally the last place, and probably the first place for most people to look would be the levity site itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where it has the starter projects here, and this has got a nice feature, as you can see over here. It&#39;s. Got, the, oh, it&#39;s like a Google Pay spa scores, right? Yeah. So it&#39;s, they&#39;ve got a wonderful thing on here, the leaderboard, where it&#39;s actually taking the live data of real users using these themes and stuff, so you can actually see who&#39;s doing well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you can put your site on it actually, and have it judged to see how it&#39;s doing. Excellent. Yeah, it&#39;s quite, quite a cool little thing, but there&#39;s something like 90 to a hundred or something of the starter themes, which are available here. One that I was looking at before, I can see this here, but you may notice, that most of them look pretty plain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:04:29] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah, certainly the little thumbnail there does in many cases look quite plain, but not always. It seems te text heavy, if Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:04:36] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes it is. And I think really if you were someone, come in as a non coder, non coders do certainly use starter sites. They don&#39;t need to know HMO very well or CSS, and they can get started if they stick with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But generally, I would think. That it&#39;s mostly the audience that attracts the people who are into HML and CSS and will want to build their own. Of course. So you&#39;ll do your own styling on top of this. So I think, Really, I, that&#39;s what I put as note here is that it&#39;s, I would say they&#39;re typically played, so you can add your own CSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the other thing is, there is an exception here. Let me just, there&#39;s quite a few exceptions, I guess to all of that, as there always is. let me just bring this one up. so you do get, something to contradict that, something which is fully fledged Something Yeah, that looks like a, actually looks like a WordPress site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dare I say it? Yeah, it does. And it&#39;s got all of these kind of cool things on it, but I think that&#39;s the exception to the rule. with these kind of things where they&#39;re heavily styled, they&#39;re usually left to do, whatever you prefer. Some of them though, what might be useful if you are, somebody uses Tailwind or something, some of &#39;em are integrated with that, or Bootstrap or they&#39;re integrated with some of the JavaScript frameworks as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as mentioned, there was three, I think. For us, the base blog, which I ended up deciding to use, and 11 Excellence, which, you&#39;ve seen before. &#39;cause I said I love, this. Yes. Yeah. It could have saved us a lot of time, I thought. I don&#39;t know why I love that. I just do. I think&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:06:20] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; it&#39;s lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:06:21] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; it is really well done. Lena Sael, I think is her name is. German developer who lives in Spain and she does a lot of sort of levity stuff and really a very clever woman and a lot of people, as you can see here, have used this site to build their own. She&#39;s listed them out here. These other people, some of &#39;em are her own projects, but other people have used these and.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, I communicated to her because she was just releasing something new and there was something that came up, which I didn&#39;t understand, and she was quick to get back with me, and there&#39;s a new version of it and why I like this, why I thought this was good for our needs was the fact that, As we know, I&#39;m a big fan of Cube CSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She also is using that and, talks about many of the things I do. She&#39;s got, dark and light mode in this, which is something that I wanted to add. We&#39;re using YouTube, Embeds. Yeah. Using Paul Iris&#39;s light embeds. So you only load the thumbnail image rather than load all the stuff that&#39;s all baked into all of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there&#39;s some really, she&#39;s got pagination, which isn&#39;t in the base blog, which we&#39;re using at the moment. she&#39;s also got, lemme just show you this &#39;cause I think this is quite full. this graph image is built into this. oh, nice. Where, what it does it, basically what it does is it creates your open graph images for, that you need for it because it prints out on a SVG that you put in, turns it into a jpeg, I think, or a ping image, whatever it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and prints out your data and whatever else you put in there. So you have these automatic created. things which we don&#39;t actually need. No. Yeah. So I think I&#39;m gonna use it for my own personal blog because I think it&#39;s fantastic. But anyway, I just wanted spend, but&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:10] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; you decided against it for the no script show option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:14] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes. And there was one other, I think I&#39;ll just quickly show it that, and again,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:18] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; I just love this. There&#39;s just something about the color. I think it&#39;s the color system of this one that I really like,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:24] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; but it&#39;s so simple. This Yeah, it&#39;s so&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:26] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; nice. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:28] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; again, we got light and dark on this. what was really nice, and I won&#39;t open it up, but it actually integrates with front matter CMS, which I Okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Showed in the last episode where it&#39;s an extension Yeah. For. vs. Code and it, so you can get a CMS experience if you like, in your VS code thing. So that&#39;s it. But yeah, and it&#39;s got also, multilanguage. Oh, multi. You can set this up for your, yeah. So you can do that. but anyway, we didn&#39;t do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided to go with the base blog just to learn from all I, I did. &#39;cause I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ve got a skim over, so we can talk about that a little bit more. We did say that we will talk about using, 11ty as a static front end for WordPress, which is, headless WordPress is the kind of, been a popular thing. Certainly. I won&#39;t go into too much detail here. I have put some articles, it&#39;s a Coupled by Andy Bell, on this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at it both ways, hooking 11tywo WordPress and importing 11 content into WordPress. So going the other way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:09:39] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; am I right in saying though that this is like a bit of an endeavor that&#39;s run out of steam a bit?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:09:46] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I, don&#39;t think so. I. there is, let me just bring this all on this by Mike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;aio, I must say that, right? Yeah, we&#39;ll go&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:09:57] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; with that. Cio. I&#39;m gonna say ar reio. Yeah, geo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:10:00] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I dunno. Yeah, I&#39;ve watched some videos. He does, he has some really great content on, design systems and, he&#39;s got a great article here as another one on this where you can set this up using this kind of fetch, node.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that which will fetch all the posts from WordPress and then you bring that into 11 and to make this all work as the client that I had in this particular case that he&#39;s talking about, they wanted that for pages and posts and he brought it in and connected it up and all the code is here. The thing is with both of these articles, and I dunno if it&#39;s down here, where it shows you I won&#39;t find it quickly, is both of &#39;em are using two different WordPress plugins so that when the client updates and publishes, that sends a communication to the hosting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;one of &#39;em is actually just for netlify to say rebuild. 11. So it would update the post there. The snag that I found with these is that these articles, I mean they&#39;re later than when these plugins came in, but the two plugins that are mentioned by Dave Davis, who&#39;s got a very similar, post on this, I looked them up and they&#39;ve both not been updated for four years and one of them has actually closed any contributions to their GitHub repository, right? so I think this is not for somebody like you and I who haven&#39;t got these skills to be able to make sure that this, these people have maybe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:11:27] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; moved on and maybe they just built it for a particular project that they have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe they had to just migrate a massive site or something like that, and this was just the most effective way to do it. I don&#39;t know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:11:37] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, but you could do it and if you&#39;ve got the skills, but I thought it was beyond us. But there is a nice little alternative I think, which will just allow, and I&#39;ll, do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a video by Zach Leatherman, the author of Eleventy who shows this. But I&#39;ll, repeat it again just because it, Allow me to show how you might import a starter site Okay. From scratch as well. So we&#39;ve got the 11ty importer where you can bring in, it&#39;ll grab the WordPress posts from this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we&#39;ll see if this works with this. so what I need to do first, let me get rid of some of this. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:12:12] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; get your, palette clean. Yeah. Is helpful set up. So what, just to be clear, you are gonna use this importer tool. The link is in the no script show, notes, and the endeavor is to import.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posts, I guess pages as well. How does it work?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:12:28] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. posts on this one is what it set up for you. Okay. The 11 importer, which I, just quickly brought up, actually I&#39;ve got a link to it here. Yeah. Actually does other stuff here. So there is a nice little video that is done on this one and I dunno if we can find it quickly here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will do WordPress &#39;cause that&#39;s the most popular thing. It will also bring in things from YouTube, but it will also bring in things from. there&#39;s more migration here. There&#39;s another platform. What&#39;s the popular platform? that&#39;s an alternative to Twitter. Masteron. Oh, Masteron, okay. So it can import stuff on that as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay. That&#39;s interesting. Yeah. So let&#39;s see if we can go back here. And now what I need to do is when you go to any of these starter sites, so if I was to go to. The base blog here, what we&#39;ll find is that you can just use this template and generally what you might want to do is to, then create a new repository for yourself on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve already got that. So if I just go and click on me, go to my repositories. I&#39;ve already brought this in and I&#39;ve got base blog over here. Okay. Got it. Yep. So if I go into that and then, and I mentioned it last time we were talking, that it might be useful to have GitHub desktop. Yes, you did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Like that. Yeah. So if we open that up, then what I can do is take this repository, which I&#39;ve copied and hopefully. Oh, there we are. We&#39;ve come in. So it&#39;s let&#39;s just check that it&#39;s going to where I want it to go. So it&#39;s coming from where I want and it&#39;s going to local path 10th. That&#39;s exactly where I want it to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nice. There is a code. Yeah, there is. Whoa. Okay. And that&#39;s done actually. And I&#39;m gonna open it up in visual. I&#39;ve got two of these open now, so we could have problems. It&#39;s all No problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:30] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; we&#39;ll&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:30] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; work with you. We&#39;ll figure it out. I&#39;ll do away with that. And I should bring this up on this screen &#39;cause you can&#39;t see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I should just also increase the size &#39;cause you can&#39;t see much, can you? Is that Yeah, that&#39;s fine. We,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:42] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah, we&#39;ve got lots now We can definitely read that. That&#39;s lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:46] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; we may, what we&#39;ll need to do first probably go to the read be document because what we&#39;ve already made. A clone of this one, and we&#39;ve already set that up, but actually, because it hasn&#39;t included all the node stuff there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay. We&#39;re gonna have to install all of that ourselves here. So bear with while I just bring up the terminal. Terminal and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:15:09] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; you&#39;re gonna NPM install? Oh no, I&#39;m not gonna do that. Not that one. Oh, this is your short code. Sorry. This is your text expander that you&#39;re using to generate the. Yes it is correct code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, you maybe just copy and paste In this case&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:15:24] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; it&#39;s quite short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:15:25] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; There we are. There you go. And now we&#39;ve got&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:15:27] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; small bit of time. Actually this will allow me, one is just doing that &#39;cause it&#39;s got, loading all the notes. I just wanted to mention something. Let me just bring this up. If you are using some of the starter sites, what might scare somebody new is seeing something like this, which is what I saw, on Elva before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I also saw it on the 11 is. oh gosh. Yeah. That looks terrifying. Yeah, It&#39;s because it&#39;s a node which is no longer supported. And what you can, it gives you the information. You can just run the NPN Audit fix and it will sort things out, and it&#39;s probably okay, and the author will do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I just thought it was worth throwing in that. If you&#39;re coming to this for the first time as I was, something like this is quite a scary thing to see if this is not we&#39;re used to doing press on regardless. Okay. Yes. Okay. So you do get something there. Anyway, we should have copied all of our&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:16:21] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, it says it still watching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A bit more time to kill here, David. What else can we, no,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:16:26] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; It&#39;s done. It&#39;s, the wrong one. I&#39;ve got it open twice, so I see that and now we can run the 11tyail and I&#39;ll do that with my, short. Key and we should have that now. There we go. Yeah. Or 80. 80. 80. There&#39;re So I increase, there we go. I increase the size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now what we can do here just to show so that&#39;s basically installed in it, and then you can work from there. So it&#39;s not. Too bigger job to start from the starter site, get it on your local level. Now, once you&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:17:00] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; know what you&#39;re doing there, which you clearly now do, I think that was a two minute enterprise for you o of without all the talking and everything that you had to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s probably a couple of minutes, isn&#39;t it? Yeah, exactly. Coffee and come back and it&#39;s all good to go. So this is the, which starter site is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:17:17] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; this? What&#39;s, this is the base blog. Except the only thing is I&#39;ve increased the font size on. Now what I wanted to do was just show the importer working. &#39;cause that was it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s quite cool. Yep. so if I just get rid of this again, and we&#39;ll go back here and I&#39;ve got the, what I need to put in already typed out because. Oh, you&#39;re&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:17:41] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; prepared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:17:41] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; You&#39;re a good YouTuber, David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:17:43] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; you&#39;ve got yourself ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:17:45] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; So what I&#39;ve just pasted in here, this is all we need is something telling that we&#39;re going to import WordPress to this particular address that we&#39;ve got in here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what we want to do is to output this content. Sorry, output it into the content and into the blog section. So one thing that we do need to know if we&#39;re using one of the starter themes is where we want that stuff to go. And in this case, with the base blog, it&#39;s in content, and then our posts go in here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay? So we want that to be the same. And then we, could do a drive run. We can decide where we want to locate the assets, but in this case, the assets want to, set to co-locate. So effectively what this should do. It should put them in a folder with the post themselves. Okay. So the images that go with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let me just run this and let&#39;s just see if it works. and we should, oh, it&#39;s asking me now because I. I haven&#39;t got the import package in there, so I&#39;m just going to say yes. Okay. I want that and it&#39;s going to do that as well. The beauty, you probably only needed. Yes, it&#39;s because I&#39;ve opened up a new one and what we&#39;re seeing here is it&#39;s fetching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s fetching the different JSON files, so this is using the WordPress rest, REST API to drag in these posts. And I know there&#39;s one error on this and what we should see over here is. In our blog. Okay. Now we have our posts and we should see that with these, they put the assets co-located them with this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was the co-locate thing. Okay, got it. Yes. And if I can find the right tab. I will,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:26] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; just show you now. Just, there we go. I was just gonna say, we&#39;re looking at a very pink screen there, but we&#39;re, back. We, can now see your brow. That great. We should be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:34] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; back, let&#39;s see if I&#39;m on the right one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fingers crossed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:37] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; It was definitely 80 82, port 80 82. So why is there some caching&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:43] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; going on? Probably. This is the problem when you&#39;re doing this. Browser caching is always, what I&#39;ll do off screen. You can&#39;t see this. I shall just run this again. I. When you say,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:54] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; run this again, are you gonna, I&#39;m just restart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:58] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I&#39;m 11. Let&#39;s just see if that shakes it up. There we are. We&#39;ve got our post. Yeah. so we&#39;ve got, yeah. So all been well, yeah, it&#39;s brought in the assets. Now. Something to just notice. there are a few little things that you get, so if you&#39;ve got, as I have in this case, it was built with a page builder and I&#39;m using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A form of that kind of, all of these had a video on the top there, which was hidden behind this kind of code that I put. So it didn&#39;t manage to pick up on that, but otherwise the images and everything, so Set that up. That would work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:20:32] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; so you did something quirky in WordPress, which 11? The importer there, it just was on, it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:20:40] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; was unable to, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay. Is unable to understand what all the, what complexities were going on there. Otherwise it would, picking the JavaScript that was needed, but it was done in such a convoluted way, so it was missing on that. it does this, I read somebody said they had an 8,000 article blog and it took 11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the importer, two minutes to, to bring all of that data over. So yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:06] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; To to, the human mind. 8,000 sounds like a lot, but to a machine just pausing text, it&#39;s just yeah, bring it on. That&#39;s fine. Yeah, exactly. Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:15] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. That bit&#39;s done. I&#39;m going to get rid of this. okay,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:21] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; that was successful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was a, really nice example of how to do it. So you&#39;ve, managed to import in a matter of moments, an entire WordPress site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:30] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes. Oh, the other thing that you might just be interested in, if I go to the site that was, this is the first thing I thought, is the rest API. So if I actually go to the site, it was important.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s actually blocked off. I&#39;ve got a maintenance mode on it. I&#39;ve got everything set, so&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:48] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; it&#39;s invisible to the human reader. But the rest API just. Very, yeah, exactly. You through all of that. Okay,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:54] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; great. so if I just gave a, client a log into this, it would be fine. And if, because of course it&#39;s taking the post data, it&#39;s turning that into markdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. So if you had a lot of junk code, which I did on that, it cleans it up. Really. It just takes the Oh, that&#39;s nice too. That&#39;s a unexpected benefit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:10] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Excellent. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:11] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. So my, got a lot cleaner. Good for moving that over. okay, let&#39;s go back to our notes, our article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:21] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Where are we now then?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I think so. We&#39;ve done the importer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:25] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; We have, we&#39;ve done how to, download us, start a site and get started with that. I think, we were talking about this earlier, I think we share the same conclusion that maybe because of the technical complexities and maintenance with headless and the growth of, static CMS is going around, I think it&#39;s probably not something you&#39;ll either go one way or the other, won&#39;t you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think with it, I think. There&#39;ll be less headless solutions. Yeah, it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:52] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; feels like 5, 3, 4, 5 years ago, headless was a real buzzword. It was really an interesting thing. I imagine probably an enterprise, it still might be. Yeah. But it doesn&#39;t feel like, your normal freelancer working in the, let&#39;s say WordPress space is gonna be too interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;cause there&#39;s just so many moving parts that could go wrong. And I&#39;m not sure that the, benefits outweigh the. The hassle unless you really are truly an expert and this is all absolute muscle memory. And, I&#39;ve not really heard anybody talking about headless much in the WordPress space of late. No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So maybe it&#39;s run its course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:23:32] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I never got it at the time because I just thought, I don&#39;t, I&#39;ve not had security issues &#39;cause I look after. Okay. And caching gives me a face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:23:39] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. Caching is the sort of the golden bullet there, isn&#39;t it? A little bit, yeah. Okay. Yeah, so&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:23:45] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; there&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:23:45] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; was that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:23:46] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; okay. Should we talk about what we&#39;ve been doing here as we are using this local version where we&#39;re trying to recreate using the 11 blog and the reason why, when you say&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:23:55] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; what we&#39;re doing here, do you mean what we&#39;re looking at on the screen? This, Yes. Yeah. Okay, great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:24:00] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Sorry. So style wise, we&#39;re not there that, we haven&#39;t put the logos in here, but we have taken the Eleventy Bog, which is, and I&#39;ve added in the things that, Might have taken me to another theme to this and taken away some things as well from it. And I did it really because I thought I wanted to know how complex it would be for someone like me, to take a starter site. Would it be the same problem you can have in WordPress where I&#39;ve done it, where you want to reconfigure some parts of a theme that you&#39;ve already got?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep. Yep. And there&#39;s just too much to wade through and there&#39;s an element of that as well. But I found it very useful because I&#39;ve been able to learn by, because the base bog is the one that. Zach Leatherman looks after and created. So probably the best person to learn from if you&#39;re gonna get into starter sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it was perfect to a certain degree for what we needed. the only thing we didn&#39;t have is I wanted the light and dark. Okay. on this. And we also needed, which I was mentioning before, if I go back to, let&#39;s just go into the archive here and go into our last. thing we wanted to have this thing here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&#39;t click on it now, but it&#39;s just loading the image. It looks like it&#39;s the video. It&#39;s not loading the stuff right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:25:17] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; There&#39;s some wizardry going on where it will load the video when you click on that image, that thing that looks like a video. Okay. Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:25:25] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; So we&#39;re using Paul Iris&#39;s light in bed, which will just serve up and hold back YouTube from all of its JavaScript and just serve up the image for quick thing that interestingly enough, there is anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A web component that Zach Lettermans built, which is based on the same thing. But I haven&#39;t used that. I&#39;ve just put it in &#39;cause I know how to do that myself. Okay. and did that, what else did I need to add in here? There was one other thing that doesn&#39;t come with the 11 base blog, which we needed really, I think, and I can just demonstrate it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh yeah. Okay. Yeah. Is the pagination on the archive pages? Get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:26:04] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; So what does it do? Does it just try to load everything all in one go if there&#39;s no pagination?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:26:10] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. So on the original blog that you get, it just, it&#39;s just the text that it gives you to start with it. Yeah, it&#39;s a starter site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it can almost go and on endlessly then, because it, browsers will be able to cope with all of that kind of information. But if you want to section it out like this, seem nice to add this in. So that was quite, an adventure for me. AI helped me though. Interesting. So&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:26:34] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; it wasn&#39;t straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There isn&#39;t like a, I don&#39;t know, something built into the base blog that you can just declare something. You had to go out and find the way to build it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:26:45] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, there is, PA pagination is something that you can easily add with 11ty. Okay. The way that I needed to add it in this particular case with the base blog, which I&#39;ll maybe touch on in a moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, yeah, sure, sure. Maybe a bit more complex. But the beauty is, and this is a real tip if anyone wants to do this, what discovered is that ai certainly clawed and I was trying deep seek at the time, so I was asking them both questions where I got stuck with the base bog and it go. it struggled as well, but when I said I&#39;m using the base bug, it goes, ah, this is what you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s configured this way. Interesting. Okay. So shows the documentation&#39;s really good for the 11th stuff &#39;cause it was able to Okay. Yeah, Tell you exactly what it did. yeah, so it, it sorted me out. So that&#39;s just the basic stuff that I made some changes. Obviously we need some styling, we sorted this sort of stuff out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, shall I bring up, I think I&#39;ll bring up the code editor for this. If I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:27:40] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, it was fairly straightforward for me as a, as somebody watching what you were doing to figure out what you&#39;ve done. But I imagine it was a bit of a bed of worms to, actually do it the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:27:52] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we got a whole bunch of, I. So the, one of the things I think, with a starter site like this for me was the fact that the downside of it all is the fact that you really do need to understand how things have been configured in, something like this. Because there&#39;s a lot of great sort of things that been set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of them I&#39;ve commented out, which is the images, I won&#39;t go into this, but it has a wonderful image plugin where if you upload into an image, it will, you can. If you can set it to do almost anything, but it will, it will turn, if it&#39;s a heavy SVG, it will turn it into, whatever the smallest thing is an A VI or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay? It will add in the sizes. It will create a picture tag if it needs to serve a viv, and then a backup of a web p or a backup of a jpeg, right? For those browsers that don&#39;t support it, it will do this all automatically. I pulled it out only because of the build time with it, because this would be perfect if you are a CMS person and you&#39;ve got a client coming in and dragging in any kind of image, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It will take care of all of that trouble for you, but that&#39;s not us and we&#39;re not using many images. In fact, we&#39;re using what comes from YouTube, our thumbnail. So you just did it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:12] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; expediency. Given your situation where not many images and the ones that you are using, you&#39;ve probably got the right format and optimize them anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exactly. So I thought, okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:23] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, exactly. So I mean I, I ran a test on it earlier. There&#39;s one other, the things that we put in as a little diagram, and you know it on the defaults, it just set me with a different versions in a picture tag. And the smallest was the Avis. That&#39;s something like nine kilobytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I just thought, our audience. If I needed that again, I would just put it in without the picture tag as a na, because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:48] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:48] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; It wouldn&#39;t need different sizes. It&#39;s so small. Anyway, so I thought that&#39;s generally the way we go. So I took that out. Okay. But there are some really cool things and, let me mention first where I got stuck, and AI helped me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if I go into the contents, are we still on&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:30:10] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; the, are we still on pagination? We&#39;re still. On&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:30:13] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; that I was gonna talk about pagination. Yes, exactly. Yeah. it didn&#39;t, it had it on the post. So you&#39;ve got the next post and the before post, that&#39;s automatically in the base blog. But I didn&#39;t have it on the archive pages and I created my own additional pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So with the example of chat here, what you discover is it uses another plugin called the 11 navigation, which allows you to really construct some, if you wanted to. A mega menu or something like this, okay? Allow you to organize things a lot better. &#39;cause you can put &#39;em in the subcategories, but because it does that, and this is something I think I mentioned, gray, gray matter as something that happens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&#39;t gray matter. This is a, an 11tyhing where you can use JavaScript in your front matter area. On this. So suddenly everything I&#39;m doing in my template now, because I&#39;ve got the navigation now has to be turned into something which is in a JavaScript format. If you&#39;ll, gosh, okay. Yeah. Which is where it goes beyond me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But luckily I was able to add the pagination simply by asking one of the ais, I&#39;m using the base blog. I want to do this. And, it just churned this out for me, which is using the standard code, which you&#39;ll see anyway in the documentation, but it just put it in the right syntax or format for the matter area here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&#39;s just&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:37] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; looking at that and not knowing what I&#39;m talking about, it looks like it&#39;s going so reverse. True is newest to oldest, I&#39;m guessing. Yeah, the alias is almost like a custom post out. We&#39;re looking for the posts. The size six is how many to show before the, before you need to click the pagination, so there&#39;s six on a page, and then there&#39;ll be six more on a page and six more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And exactly. Data collections podcast. I don&#39;t even know what that is. Not a clue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:07] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; that&#39;s because that&#39;s what I&#39;ve named this particular collection, so it&#39;s on the, got it. Page, which we&#39;ve now called chat at the moment where, okay, some, this is why it&#39;s not up at all because we, still sort out some of the naming conventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We called it podcast and maybe we&#39;ll call it chats. I&#39;ll reconfigure this. But the beauty of it is, and it&#39;s the same with the tagging system of the base blog, is that it&#39;s automated for you. So when I need a new page, this is automatically going, yeah. It&#39;s not&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:33] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; gonna figure it all out for you. Okay. And it&#39;s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:35] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; going to, because of 11, it&#39;s going to put the.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big previous and the next and everything can create that, then we can change what we call that, over here. So, we&#39;ve got that all built in. and it&#39;s the same with the tagging system as well. This is built into the base bog. If I create a new tag on one of my posts, it&#39;s gonna do it, but that was just one of the little gotchas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That I got into with that. That&#39;s, yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:57] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; in some respects I&#39;m surprised that isn&#39;t built into the base of 11. But then again, you might not want, some sort of archive of anything. You might just want a five page website with just, the navigation in the top right of the desktop version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it makes sense not to have it in, if you&#39;re trying to keep things lean. Makes sense. Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:33:20] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I, think maybe, it&#39;s, pagination does seem like something for the base blog because it is designing for blogs, but also we&#39;ve gone down a different route slightly with this in the sense that you would generally have a blog and then you would have tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I&#39;ve used the tag. Oh, I see. Okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:33:34] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Got it. Yeah. Yeah, because&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:33:36] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; still if, I go back into any of these. it doesn&#39;t matter. which one, you&#39;ll see I&#39;ve got a tagging system, but it&#39;s also running into the tags. It&#39;s automatically creating. So any new tags that I put in my front matter will get a new tag separate to the ones that I&#39;ve created for ourselves and looped here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Got it. If that makes sense. yeah, that does make sense. Okay. So it&#39;s a, it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:33:59] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; is a different taxonomy structure than, what I&#39;m used to in WordPress, which obviously just handles all this out the box. There&#39;s, other ways of doing things in, eleventy with tagging. Okay. All right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:34:10] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. it&#39;s pretty simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s just go into the blog. One nice thing is that it&#39;s set up so contents of the area, so anything in there can get changed and all the posts are in here and I didn&#39;t know I could do this, but it&#39;s set up. Two, recognize anything in here so I could put a folder in without messing things up and organize our posts over here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, a nice thing to do. And if I go over to, let&#39;s just go into the one we&#39;re looking at the moment we&#39;ll do, This is what I&#39;m doing now is I&#39;m able to, it&#39;s something I didn&#39;t mention last time round, so I put a little note, because when I was, if you met, I was creating a simple site and just to give you an introduction to the idea of collections and how you might create posts, I didn&#39;t explain the fact that my post names didn&#39;t match what my URL was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:02] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Okay. So we could,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:03] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; this is how you do it basically. So it&#39;ll sify. Nice five. Yeah. So I&#39;m telling it to go into the permalink. Of build and this, and I&#39;ll just add to it. I&#39;ve created a tag here. I could create many more and it will automatically create those tags for me. So if we decide that there&#39;s some crossover between the things that we&#39;re doing in our categories, or this other ones, I can put them in and they will just tag and create the.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The, pages we need. And the beauty is with the video id, that&#39;s how I&#39;ve connected it up with the Paul Iris&#39;s light YouTube embed and bringing forward those images. I&#39;ve now been able to put that so it goes in the metadata. So if as an open graph image, it could be used on the front page to automatically do it, and it&#39;s outputting as well to the individual posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So nice. Got it right. Yeah. Yeah. And there&#39;s another nice thing as well in there that you can do drafts as well. So if you put this as, I&#39;ve commented it out the moment, but if I set this to draft true. I can still, I can still, do a build to the hosting work on this. It&#39;s not gonna show it until I either remove this or set it to false.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay. So it&#39;s, not going to, yeah. So it&#39;s gonna ignore it. So you can work on that useful, a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:19] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; pending status, but there it is, ready to roll. You just delete that draft. Yeah. I&#39;ll just delete that out&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:24] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; and then the next time I do an update to got it. As I would do to, it&#39;s going to do that. That&#39;s it. Let&#39;s, let me go back to the notes. Actually, I need to come back here. Okay. What, didn&#39;t we cover? Any questions that you&#39;ve got so far? No,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:39] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; all of it seems, straightforward isn&#39;t the word &#39;cause it&#39;s all very new to me and I would probably upend me if I tried to do it myself. But no, that all makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:49] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; there is, the syntax highlighting is quite a nice thing that we wanted to put in, which came in there. If I just go into one of the learns over here and go into. Light and dark toggle here. It&#39;s got this wonderful way of, it&#39;s, used in somebody else&#39;s library, another 11 user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:37:10] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; this what we are looking at there, the code example that you&#39;re looking at. If you would just type that in as marked down, it would just look like. Any old text, you&#39;ve what? There&#39;s a sort of plugin if you like, and that enables you to encapsulate that portion as, show me this as code instead, and then it&#39;ll, with a bit of CSS, it&#39;ll put it in a darker box and it will make the, it will format CSS so that the bits and pieces which you want to be in different colors, are in different colors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:37:38] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, exactly. And in fact, let me just go over here. If I go to one of the learn examples and let&#39;s make sure I&#39;ve got one with a bit of code in it. I&#39;m sure there is somewhere, I&#39;ll probably pick the one. There&#39;s a bit of HML there by the looks of it. There&#39;s a bit of H ml, so we have these three back ticks and then you put the language that you want it to do that with and Put this in. So it&#39;s gonna be there. And that&#39;s the format with this. We&#39;ve got some CSS here. Got it. Feedback ticks. We close &#39;em with BT ticks as well. And then we just put CSS and then it&#39;s gonna display that and what&#39;s happening behind the scenes, which allows me just to talk about snake else. I&#39;m going off tangents, but, the CSS, so last time we did a video, we talked about the CSS and I bundled it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a Nun Jux file and included all of the different CSS style sheets that had into that one. Now I tried to do something similar, but I got into a mess and I just decided to use what&#39;s already set up in the 11 base blog, which I think is pretty cool. If I just go into, let me just open the this up. On the, let&#39;s go into our Includes, into our layout and into the base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay. It does it all in the template here, and you have this kind of, there&#39;s lots of stuff and I&#39;ll probably have to stop &#39;cause it&#39;ll get. Too boring soon, but, there&#39;s a lot of stuff that goes on in here. So there&#39;s another bit of a sort of plugin if you like, which allows you to get a bundle by the URL here, and you can specify at CSS and then you can put this in here, what you want to include.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s gonna send it all to one location, which is set up into another folder called the distribution, the dis. Folder and it puts it all together in that way, which is a slightly different way. But the nice thing about this is that you can also, if you wanted to have that as inline CSS on your page, you can just&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:39:35] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; have Oh, print out within the star sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:39:38] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. And so it also means as is used as well on the base blog. Naturally it is actually printed in line. I&#39;ve changed this now, so it puts it in a style sheet, but it does allow you say the syntax highlighting which we were talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:39:54] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:39:54] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Is one of the things that&#39;s, brought in. And in fact, then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;re just putting that on the post. I think it might be showing here that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:40:03] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; So the, if, there&#39;s no, so for example, on a post, there&#39;s a high probability that you want c syntax highlighting for C-S-S-H-T-M-L, et cetera. and if you&#39;re doing it, if you&#39;re injecting that in line only when it&#39;s needed in this case, in a post, because there&#39;s a high opportunity that a post will have that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you could do it on a. Page by page basis, or a post by post basis. And yet the CSS file is stored in the same place in that little bundle. that&#39;s quite clever actually. I like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:40:35] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. it&#39;s putting the distribution and then, so in this case it&#39;s been automatically set up In fact, it&#39;s pulling in that theme is what&#39;s given me the, coloring for the syntax highlighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, and actually there&#39;s another one in there which I&#39;ve left as it is there, which just is the difference, the changes made to the original, but it&#39;s actually can pull these things in from the node modules themselves, rather than what you&#39;ve got there. quite cool stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:41:03] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, let me, yeah, I was just gonna say, do you wanna just quickly knit back to your show notes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&#39;cause there was a few things on that page. yeah, it was the one before. And then scroll down. What have we looked at? Were, no, where&#39;s it going? Yeah, so we, you&#39;ve mentioned syntax just now, so I&#39;m looking underneath the pros. The first bullet point there, pre-configure 11 plugins. So the base theme Comes with. Something to do with RSS. You mentioned image transformation. So you can throw a, an image in like an SVG and it will turn it into an A VI and you can configure all of that navigation enables you to do more complicated navigation syntax we&#39;ve just seen. Yeah. Highlighting Id attribute an HTML base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, they&#39;re part of it. I dunno what they are, but Do you want to touch those or is it, you can&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:41:51] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; see it here, although I might take it away. What it&#39;s doing is when it&#39;s seeing, because it&#39;s a good thing for accessibility. Yeah. Be able to link to headers. What this is doing automatically with the ID attribute, it&#39;s a kind of, is it a plugin?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not sure quite sure, but it&#39;s included and I can remove it with one line. But basically where we see this, if we go into the source code, it&#39;s giving us an ID against this header as well. So if I look there, we&#39;ve got the, it gives me an ID as well. Got it. Got it. Yeah. Okay, so we&#39;ve got some, so instead of it&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:42:24] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; just being an H three, it&#39;s H three, whatever an idea of whatever the H three.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is, so in this case the comms? Yeah. Oh, that&#39;s nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:42:33] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. So on. I guess the only issue you might have is if you have the same title on the sec, but you shouldn&#39;t really ever have that should you? No. on the same page. That&#39;s the only problem with an ID there. Okay. But yeah, it&#39;s quite a nice thing, a little accessibility thing or way to be able to link to a part of your article if you are linking someone else to it built in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don&#39;t have to do anything. It&#39;s automated. There was a actually, and I needed to use this a lot and it&#39;s even for building a simple site first time round, I didn&#39;t really touch on the conditionals else if all the time. Okay. And that&#39;s a really easy thing to do with the nun ju. And I just have to now quickly think on my feet where there&#39;s an example of where I&#39;ve done this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I&#39;ve done it in the base blog where I wanted to, in the base nex. Let me just have a look here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:22] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; So is this like an inline thing we&#39;re looking for? Are we looking for some line? Yes. I want conditional logic of if this the can&#39;t see anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:31] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes. No you can&#39;t. Can you? &#39;cause I&#39;ve forgotten where I might have put it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me just have a look. Keep looking&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:36] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; on. We&#39;re fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:38] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I don&#39;t know&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:39] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; the, the way it&#39;ll look, but I&#39;m keen something. Hopefully. Okay. Oh, there was an end if there, right at the bottom. What was that end? If that was one of them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:49] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes. Let&#39;s have a look. Where are we starting with? You had an end, you had an if&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:52] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much further up. Oh, no, If collections post. Ah yes. So I think it&#39;s not the one I wanted to further down near the bottom of the screen, right near the bottom is an if collections posts, and then obviously there&#39;s an end. If so, you&#39;ve got an, you&#39;ve got an if within an if here by the look. Oh, no, you don&#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&#39;ve just got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:44:13] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I&#39;m not sure where I&#39;ve got to on this one. because you&#39;ve got, now I can&#39;t remember what I&#39;ve done, but, anyway, with all I wanted to, I, before I get stuck on what I&#39;ve done here, I think there is my example, this is a perfect example. what I wanted to, when I didn&#39;t have, as you could see actually on the, that we&#39;re looking at, I don&#39;t have a video ID for the thumbnail for the YouTube video &#39;cause it hasn&#39;t gone up yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what I&#39;ve done is to say. Only if my front matter gives me an id. Will you print out what you need to blank. Oh, and I noticed that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:44:49] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; was in the, that was in the front matter, that portion of text. at the top of the post you had a, I think it said YouTube ID or something and there was like the 10 characters of the slug Of the URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:45:00] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes. Of the YouTube was, it was. It was commented out as well. So that&#39;s why it&#39;s not, because otherwise it would take up the space of YouTube. Lemme me understand&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:45:10] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; this then if, that wasn&#39;t commented out and it was, so if you&#39;d got a YouTube ID in the post Yes. And it wasn&#39;t commented out, so it did exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That if would say, does it exist? Yes. Okay. Now append it to the end of the YouTube URL and display it. So not only is it doing the job of whether or not to display, but it&#39;s also using the same, yeah, there it is. Video id, it&#39;s using that to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:45:37] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah, declare whether&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:45:38] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; it should display or not, but also appending it to the URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. So if I leave this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:45:42] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; and I leave it below course, and if I take this off so it&#39;s there. we needed a conditional to show &#39;cause what&#39;s gonna happen now if I refresh or be, it&#39;s not, is it? Oh,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:45:55] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; you need, yeah. You might need to clear some caches or rebuild the whole thing. The vague, I think I just need to rebuild it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. But I trust you. I&#39;m sure it&#39;ll work. Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:46:06] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Otherwise without that conditional, it would be showing, it would be trying to show, the, in fact, actually, I&#39;ve hidden the head of one and I use the image to replace it. So generally that&#39;s the case. I get it though. That&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:46:21] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; made sense. the syntax of it and all is new to me and.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I, see what it&#39;s doing. That&#39;s good. Yeah. It&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:46:27] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; was worth mentioning that you could do, &#39;cause it was, you&#39;d want that on simple things. And also something I didn&#39;t mention as well last time was the fact that there is these web components. So in Eleventy and I, skipped over it. There is something called Web C, which is Zack Leatherman&#39;s own language for using, web components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in fact, it&#39;s a web component which is creating, it puts around the main tag, which is creating these IDs combined with. The other Java script that it has there. So that&#39;s another part of 11tywo, which I really haven&#39;t got into. Okay. But it&#39;s another option for how you might put together your sites with, using web components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:47:06] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; What I&#39;m learning though, is depending on, so unlike, so Okay. The intention of WordPress was never really to put functionality in the theme, but that kind of did end up happening. Yeah. But in the theme, usually in the customizer, you can switch things on or off. Like I show the. I don&#39;t know, the author, show the, metadata for when it was published and what have you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what I&#39;m seeing is something akin to that. Here you&#39;ve got these plugins built inside of a theme, in this case, the base theme that you can switch on, switch off, configure how you like, but obviously it&#39;s much more like hands into the code and figuring all that out. But they enable you to add components to your website, your pages, your posts, add if statements around them, so they show or don&#39;t show depending on certain conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so you&#39;ve got this framework for building. Based upon the exact same data, you can have a different array of things happening on the pages with these plugins. okay. I&#39;m, beginning to get it a bit, I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:48:06] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. Yeah. It&#39;s, most of the time, it&#39;s the, that&#39;s the downside of with the starter thing because when you start to remove things, you really need to know how the directories are being set up or what plugins, but I&#39;m probably not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entirely there, but I think I&#39;ve now learned what&#39;s there. you&#39;re calling in, as you see, these are kind of plugins are called in at the top here, import these kind of plugins. Oh, there&#39;s the RSS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:48:30] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; one and navigation. Yeah, Okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:48:33] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; and yeah, it&#39;s wonderful. And then filters have got some other things that&#39;re all built into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there is a bit of doing this, but I was surprised how far I&#39;ve got and how confident I feel. And it&#39;s a little bit, saying about that. There&#39;s a couple of points where I&#39;m really excited. I got excited about WordPress at the time. One of them was when I first started doing my own themes, and that feels a lot like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then the other time was when CSS got really difficult and I&#39;ve discovered page builders. So I&#39;ve got like this kind of, it feels like going back to some old days where I, yeah, made powerful, helped a little bit with ai, but, it does mean we. No JavaScript skills. I&#39;ve been able to do some quite complex stuff already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:49:15] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Nice conditions. Yeah. So it&#39;s not, I enjoyed it. How, are we doing with the show notes there? Have we got through what you wanted to say? I think so. Like we had&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:49:24] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; maybe, yeah, I think so. There was a couple of things I just wanted to cover. I think I thanked who I wanted. There&#39;s more to show you, on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe I&#39;ll just do a short video if there&#39;s something that&#39;s missed out on this. Okay. That I think might be useful. But, otherwise I think we&#39;ve. Probably, we&#39;ve done our best to try and cover what,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:49:41] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah, that, that looks good. So the, endeavor there was to show what a, theme can do, in this case, the base theme inside of 11ty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there were loads of options, dozens and dozens of options. Some more minimal looks like, some less minimal. and David showed you where you can get those. As with everything, the, the bits and pieces, the links that you just saw. Will be available for your dilatation, over on the no script show, 1111 based website at some point in the year 2027.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:50:15] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; But there&#39;ll be a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:50:15] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; link to wherever you can get the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:50:17] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; notes in&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:50:18] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:50:18] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; YouTube. Yeah. Comments? Okay. Oh yeah, of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:50:21] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah, Thank you. so look in the, description of the YouTube video and go from there. Basically. Yeah. Okay. Is that it? Are we wrapping that up? I think so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:50:31] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:50:31] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; think so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it was useful. Yeah, it was really interesting. Honestly, the more you talk about it, the more convinced I&#39;m that I should give it a go if only I had 50 hours available to meet. Yeah, exactly. It does take some time. Yeah. All right. I&#39;ll see you next time, David. Thank you. Bye bye. Thank you. Cheers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, bye-bye. Bye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Long-term WordPress user tries building with 11ty (a Static Site Generator)</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/6/" />
    <updated>2025-01-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/6/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;show-notes&quot;&gt;Show notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As WordPress user we know how to build dynamic sites. We know next to nothing about Static Site Generators and the Jamstack. Here we rebuild a HTML site with 11ty (Eleventy). We also look at adding a CMS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-we-cover&quot;&gt;Things we cover&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What we need to run 11ty (Node, Git and free hosting).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting 11ty from scratch (installing 11ty).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating our first page. Converting Markdown to HTML.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating a header and footer template for our site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introducing Front Matter (like WordPress custom fields).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding CSS and bundling with a Nunjucks template.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bringing in other website assets with the Eleventy config file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making the site&#39;s head dynamic for SEO (doing the job of a WordPress SEO plugin).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making HTML more manageable with partials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adjusting CSS classes with Front Matter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introducing data (like WordPress&#39;s database), but with a dynamic menu.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding events. Similar to working with WordPress&#39;s post loop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding a CMS (Decap and locally the Front Matter CMS extension).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@EleventyVideo/videos&quot;&gt;11ty YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://11tybundle.dev/&quot;&gt;11ty Bundle&lt;/a&gt;. A fabulous place for all the latest by Bob Monsour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are years out of date, but with the help of 11ty docs and Claude AI I could covert to 11ty V3:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://learneleventyfromscratch.com/&quot;&gt;Learn Eleventy From Scratch&lt;/a&gt;. Andy Bell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4wD00RT6d-g&quot;&gt;Turn static HTML/CSS into a blog with CMS using the JAMStack&lt;/a&gt;. Kevin Powell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Static vs dynamic for content heavy websites</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/15/" />
    <updated>2025-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/15/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;Spoiler&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is about what to use for the show&#39;s website as the content grows. We&#39;re going to try &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/&quot;&gt;11ty&lt;/a&gt; partly because Nathan&#39;s show &lt;a href=&quot;https://noscript.show/15/wpbuilds.com/&quot;&gt;WP Builds&lt;/a&gt; is already about WordPress, but also 11ty might be a more logical fit for this particular show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-our-site-needs&quot;&gt;What our site needs:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A quicker way to write posts. A text editor or Markdown?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier way to add SEO metadata, open graph, sitemaps and RSS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way to automate tags and categories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A quicker way to add performant YouTube videos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-dilemma-of-static-v-dynamic&quot;&gt;The dilemma of Static v Dynamic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An old debate. Dynamic provided what we needed in the early 2000&#39;s, but even by 2008 there was &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, a SSG (that inspired 11ty). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/000404&quot;&gt;Bake don&#39;t fry&lt;/a&gt; by Aaron Swartz in 2002 also got some questioning dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;wordpress&quot;&gt;WordPress&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious choice as most successful blogging platform:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quick and easy to set up with no developer skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A massive range of themes and plugins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We know it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Well funded… although topical at the moment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;downsides-for-this-shows-site&quot;&gt;Downsides for this show&#39;s site:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control of the code output. Important to a show focussed on web standards and accessibility *.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using WP would not teach us about alternatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paying for hosting(caching/backup/security) and time on software update and maintenance **.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not so easy offer a CMS version of our site demos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The intented audience. WP is seen as a no code solution. This show is about how lovely and friendly code can be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* A classic theme would allow this, but control over the modern block themes requires JS skills we don&#39;t have or need.&lt;br&gt;
** We could convert WP to static for free hosting but manually that is a faff. Services that convert WP to static hosting are expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;static-site-generators&quot;&gt;Static Site Generators&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gaining popularity at the moment. The 2024 Web Almanac &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloudcannon.com/blog/the-rise-of-static-first-websites-why-major-brands-are-making-the-switch/&quot;&gt;shows 67% growth in static and hybrid website architectures among the top 10,000 most-visited sites&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;general-problems-with-static-site-generators-ssg-s&quot;&gt;General problems with Static Site Generators (SSG&#39;s)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Needs some skills or willingness to use a terminal rather than a UI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many choices. No industry standard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many have retired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are lots to set up with a blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&#39;s cobbled together out of various bits of tech. House of cards?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to add the CMS yourself for a multi author blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No inbuilt commenting system or search.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-11ty&quot;&gt;Why 11ty?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s 360 SSG&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamstack.org/generators/&quot;&gt;listed here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Possibly the simplest way to explore SSGs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unopinionated. There&#39;s no way to know you have used it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexible with a range of templating languages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You add complexity as needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast build times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not VC funded *.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users include: W3C, UK gov, US gov, Google, Cern, NASA, A11Y Project, Web.dev and CSS Tricks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fans include: Miriam Suzanne, Lea Verou, Stephanie Eckles, Heydon Pickering, Andy Bell, Chris Coyier, Michelle Barker, Sara Soueidan and Ben Myers (many people mentioned in this show).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* 11ty has recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/blog/eleventy-font-awesome/&quot;&gt;joined Font Awesome.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt; 
&lt;summary&gt;Transcript&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:06] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Hello and welcome to the No Script Show. After some visual YouTube only content, we’re back with an episode that also works as an audio podcast too. Here we’re looking at a longstanding debate, which seems to get more significant all the time. That is whether or when to go a static or dynamic route when building websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this podcast is focused on catching up with changes in the web platform, we don’t generally talk about third party frameworks and platforms, but as the show’s own website gets larger, we may need help to manage it. This has left us with the static. Dynamic dilemma, and I’m joined as always to have this chat by David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How you doing, David?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:47] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I’m really good. yeah, so should we spoil things and say that we already know what we’re going to try and use? Yeah. for this site we’re gonna try 11, which is a static site generator. the main reason for that, is, Is that you already do a show, which is on WordPress anyway, and that’s our background anyway, so we know that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By taking a look at that, it gives us something new to do. But, I think this conversation came up. We thought, we might as well do this topic. ’cause you asked me the question with you we know each other from WordPress and I’ve been starting to learn 11 I. For the idea of making kind of large content sites with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you said you’re just not swapping one set of complications for another with that. And I thought, yes I am. but I thought there’s a good conversation, but why I might want to do that. So I guess, yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:01:48] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; what this is about. It’s interesting ’cause obviously if, like me, you are heavily embedded in the WordPress ecosystem and continuing to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might add, there’s a learning curve just to make WordPress work. You could really not know anything about html CSS, JavaScript, any of that, I’m sure many people do. And so you spend your time learning how to make WordPress achieve what it is that you want to achieve with code or plugins or whatever it may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I did get the intuition that if the no script show website needed some sort of capability to manage the content as it grows, you’ve gotta have some system in place. It can’t just be writing static HDML files and uploading them. It’d be nice to be able to automate some features or have some CMS in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did wonder what would the learning curve for 11 look like? And if it basically ended up being the same kind of learning curve that you do with WordPress, I was just thinking, what’s the point in that? You’re just swapping one difficulty for a different difficulty. And so that was why I prompted that conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which then in the background led you to create the content for this episode, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:03:02] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. And I. More logically, I think it’s more appropriate for this show because what we tried to do is make it different from what we were doing with WebPress to get back to relearning the web platform. And mostly it was geared around the idea of keeping it as simple as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. So we don’t talk about the other stuff, but obviously we’ve moved to that point here, and this is probably why it’s more logical because. If we go with something like Eleventy in particular, which I’ll discuss later, it allows you to opt in gradually for what you need, rather than start with this kind of monolith system where even with the JAMstack type stuff, you can end up that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should we bring up the website where we’ve got some of the notes to just guide us through our conversation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:03:46] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah. I, would just say at this point, if it’s all right, David, that I, have no experience with Eleventy at all, so really I’m just your. The here today to be a foil. if anything doesn’t make sense to me, I’m going to ask you what’s going on and what have you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I’ve had various conversations with you. You’ve outlined how it works and what have you. But if I end up being incredibly ignorant, apologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:04:09] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; apologies to anybody who’s in the levity community ’cause they really clever people there. And I’m just. just starting to grapple with it to understand it, but not having really any JavaScript background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is a program that runs on JavaScript. I’m really not that knowledgeable. Okay. So I’m probably gonna stuff up with the things that I say. But anyway, let’s, and I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:04:30] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; just say though, at this point it, it’s interesting because it has excited you though. yeah. And obviously in these videos we try not to be that person, you’re just demonstrating how excited you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think it’s fair to say that you are really. Pleased that you’ve come across this and you’ve obviously explored a load of different options and this is the one that you’ve got into. And so in a way, in a sense, I’m happy that you found it. ’cause it, you used to have that same feeling I think about WordPress and now you’ve, you’ve swapped it for this, so that’s nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve got another project to get your teeth into. It’s lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:05:04] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. and particularly with that, it’s quite what’s quite interesting and it’s. It wasn’t known at the time. I didn’t really understand the 11 t. I didn’t know what the options were if you wanted something outside of WordPress, and certainly on that kind of JAMstack side, but it turns out that most of the people I’ve ended up talking about on this show, the people that are getting me back into the web platform and learning CSS, again, are a lot of the people who are big fans of this particular thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So interesting. It’s yeah, it’s like I found the thing that might. Fit my needs best. it’s gonna depend. So let’s start with the site, what this site needs, because it’s becoming, we’ve done 30 sort of bits of content. some of it hasn’t even gone on to the site. We haven’t redesigned it yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so I. We are we getting to the point where doing it manually, as I am just writing out the HT ml and sticking up a new page on it, is getting a bit, tedious, particularly with the SEO stuff, right? That has to go in there. So we need, as I’ve listed there, a quicker way to write a. Posts and obviously WordPress or a dynamic system is likely to give you a text editor where you are more likely to go if you are on the static Versions of that is using markdown, which is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty new to me. Are you familiar with it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:06:25] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; I’m familiar with it, but it’s never been something that, that gelled with me. I’ve always preferred, basically not mark down. I’ve always preferred to write the text and then highlight the bits and then add the correct formatting via some kind of editor, be it tiny MCE or now the block editor in WordPress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That just works with me. I know people who are just huge fans of Mark down. To the point where, you know, any app that doesn’t support markdown, be that like a note taking app or what have you, they just won’t use it. ’cause they, it’s become part of their muscle memory. So for me, no, but I understand its benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:01] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; And it’s a big thing in the WordPress community. A lot of people, there’s plugins, you can add it in if you want to, if you wanna work with that. but yeah, Yeah, so it’s something I’m gonna have to learn to speed up the writing of these posts if I want to do it that way. With markdown, I think you’ll only&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:16] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; need a handful of shortcuts if you like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think you know, headings and links and there won’t be too much. I think that you need to commit to memory. So I think once you’ve got 10 things in your head, that’ll probably be all that you need for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:30] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, it makes it. I think, writing with Mark down is quicker than actually using the text editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you’re right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:36] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:38] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; but I gotta get used to that. But an easy way, and this is really the key thing, I think adding in the SEO stuff that you do when you want a different description on that and it gets a little bit more complex with, Some of that stuff, particularly with the open graph stuff, if you want a particular image to show, which we often do on this one, sitemaps and RSS feeds, all that kind of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A way to automate the tags and categories, which we’ve effectively got two categories. There were the sort of separate learn videos that I did separate to our main podcast and, now we’ve already, because we. We don’t know where this show’s going. We’ve already ended up with a third, which is our kind of YouTube only content, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;yeah. a way to be able to organize that kind of stuff. And also, a way of being able to add the performant YouTube videos, which I’ve had to do manually each time, to, yeah, it’s it’s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:30] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; interesting looking at those bullet points because for my need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:34] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; WordPress&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:35] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; satisfies that in, every one of those bullet points works really well with WordPress. from the perspective of this and the endeavor that we’re doing here, it it’s interesting to see those things are now the bare minimum of what you need. It basically boils down to four or five things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. And if you can find a platform that satisfies those four or five things, then you’ve hit gold. yeah. Okay. Carry on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:58] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; there might be a few other things, like dates and stuff like that. Yeah. Okay. You could write those in if you want modified date to do automatically as soon as you change the post and that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. things that you could do with both systems. So yeah, the dilemma of static or, dynamic and in all honesty, when I thought we’d be doing this show, what I thought we’d probably end up doing is doing a kind of WordPress, version of it first. Because obviously it’s what we know, but I didn’t really realize until recently that this is a bit of an old debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as I understand it, it’s like dynamic obviously came in the early two thousands. Obviously WordPress, not the newest of them came in, what, 2003?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:09:44] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:09:44] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I think so. Yep. And that took care of the fact that, we needed to have. Lots and lots of pages on as such and things like blogs and that take care of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I did, what I didn’t realize is that the whole question of is dynamic all we need or is kin static play a role was already there. There was jackal, which, I’ll bring up the website. I know this is going out as audio, but, It won’t make any difference to this. I’ll just bring up their site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is, a static site generator that’s been running off Ruby since about 2008, I think. Okay. still popular, so it’s not exactly as if, this concept is new. It’s quite new to me. And I guess with that, the popular term, JAMstack coming in. Probably from about 2000, not sure 15, 16 or onwards. it’s probably changed things and what we can do with JavaScript now is changed things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But yeah, the idea of being able to statically, generate these things and. Zach Leatherman, the author behind Eleventy, who I was listening to him and he was pointed to an article, bake Don’t Fry by Aman Schwartz, which, dates back to 2002 where he set off some kind of debate questioning. dynamic, whether we should be doing it on a computer end rather than having to generate the content that the user sees Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a live server, then that’s really what we’re talking about, I think. Yeah. yeah, WordPress, as I said, was the obvious choice, because. As we know, it’s the most successful plugin platform. It’s quick and easy to set up with no developer skills, massive range of themes and plugins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So pretty much any functionality or look that you might want, you could probably get out the box. We know it. It’s well funded, it’s got that background, although it’s a little bit topical at the moment, but we won’t get into that. But for me, the downsides for this site show, was that we’re all about the, the code about, working with the CSS and learning all of that new stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it’s important to have something that could, we could have complete control of the. Source code that we’re outputting, particularly as we’re gonna use our site as well as an example sometimes of the things that we talk about. And I think you can lose that with WordPress. You don’t get such same control over things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:12:17] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. you do, have that control, but the, barrier to that, you have to spend many, hours, years possibly really understanding how WordPress is built and constructed in order to learn how to strip out what you don’t want and put in exact. What you do want, which is why I guess enterprise agencies in the WordPress space can charge enterprise level, fees for their products, which presumably spit out exactly what the client wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in this case, it sounds like 11 is the opposite. You start with kind of nothing and you build in the bits that you want, as opposed to WordPress, which has a ton of stuff out the box that you then have to maybe strip out if it’s not exactly what you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:13:00] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, exactly. It is working from the opposite side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it’s not just the, where the dynamic stuff happens. Which, in our case is on the, our own personal computers rather than on the server. But it’s also about, I think the approach generally, although not necessarily true of all static site generators, they come with their own set of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But certainly with Eleventy, it is the kind of, it’s been purposely made with the idea that. Zach Leatherman, the person behind it is really of the belief that most people should be able to make their websites with just plain old the web platform. Yeah. H ml and CSS. Yep. And then if you do need the dependencies, you can just add ’em in as you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s been the kind of approach to that particular project. the thing is though, why I thought we might not do it, because just before I, got into looking into 11, I really got into the idea of using the classic theme and building on WordPress and building my own setup with that one and coding it from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you’re to move over and go to modern, WordPress with it, you have to get into the block themes really, if you’re to take advantage of going forward that route. So then that requires me skills that I don’t have or I’m not going to need. It’s going to box me into. The kind of WordPress React route or something to learn to have that same control over things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:21] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; So are you meaning particularly JavaScript skills that you might need to have? Okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:26] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:27] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:27] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; So somebody can, they can control their code output on WordPress, but you probably need some extra skills if you’re going to go the new modern. JavaScript first route with WordPress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s, so that kind of, that, that kind of skilled me outta the situation even though I don’t have JavaScript skills and it, I don’t wanna be boxed in so much to one particular, JavaScript, if you like, or one approach with that, Got it. yeah. Yeah. So the other downside is that we would, if we use WordPress, then we wouldn’t be learning an alternative, which is always good to know, different things that you can use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we’d have to pay for our hosting and there might be some other things that we’d have to pay for caching, backup, security, that kind of stuff that I do on the WordPress sites that I manage. It is not so easy to ’cause something I would quite like to do with our shows. For the last three episodes that we did, we made a demo site to Yeah, and made that public for anybody if they wanted to use it just to analyze it or use bits of it in the start of their projects, which I want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I’d like to be able to do is to do some. not necessarily a CMS version of it, but just use, add a, an eleventy version of it. Yeah. And it would be a lot easier to do that by just adding some extra things, like there’s a permanent header and footer template and you just change the content for extra pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’d like to make a version of that. That would be. It would be more difficult to share that with people if I wanted to do a WordPress version of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:15:58] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; So do you mean you might atomize the site? So you, okay, if you like this header here’s the bit for the header and if you like this footer, here’s the bit for the footer, that kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you’d be able to share those components, those&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:16:12] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; jigsaw&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:16:13] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:16:14] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; the risk sharing that what all I was thinking of, say we did the bistro site that we did. Yeah. And that was just an example. If I made a version of that, I could decide, and I think we’ll do this, maybe we’ll do this as the next episode, just show how you could just add 11 two to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So say on that bistro site as say, there’s a lot more pages you want on it, and I think. Okay. That means I have to change the header and the photo on each. Got it. Pages. Got it. I can turn this so I can do a CMS version if you like, one that you can do. there something that makes it easier to manage your content really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay. I’m not talking about, UI or anything like that. Okay. But yeah, also the intended audience. I think it’s the downside for this one is to say, we’re really about getting back to the web platform and learning stuff there. And partly because WordPress is. More popularly seen as a no code solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that’s really not fair when all the people are really serious developers who use WordPress, but generally it’s seen as that where our show is a bit about Pumping up a little bit how lovely and friendly code can be these days. Yeah. so it’s more suiting to that different audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Okay. Great. Yeah, so that’s that. also, let’s talk a bit about the static site generators. So there is, there do seem to be gaining popularity at the moment. So there was the. 2024 Web Almanac, which, was just so in showing that there’s a 67% growth in static and hybrid website. A, architectures amongst the top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is difficult for me to say for some reason, 10,000 most visited sites. Gosh, that’s a lot. Wow. It’s, it is a huge growth. Yeah. I mean there is, there is, talk of it here, obviously Cloud Canyon, because they, do a CMS for static. People are obviously going to promote that. I think there is something, if you actually go to the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Itself, the way of being able to measure that’s quite tricky is particularly with something like Eleventy, because you can’t tell Eleventy is being used ‘&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:26] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; cause&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:27] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Eleventy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:27] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; doesn’t put anything out to identify itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:30] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. anybody interested in that would probably just want to go and look at, the table of contents and probably the jump stack area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;because they’ve had to assess on the basis of speed. I believe how. what sites are statically generated and what’s are being dynamically. Okay. So it might not be entirely accurate, but Right. It does seem that there is a trend towards that. And obviously that’s where the growth has been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s other static site generators like Astro 11 is fairly stable, but it’s still been growing over the years that it’s been around. So there is a general growth in those. So there is that, but there are some general problems. Shall we just quickly cover those? Yeah, problem. Let’s go for it. Yep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. These are problems that WordPress solves for you, for other people, which is you do need some skills and you certainly need a willingness, I think, to use a terminal to do command line rather than a nice friendly ui. So that’s still something which is a bit alien to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:29] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I think, a lot of people, that is already a bridge too far, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you Exactly. really getting the terminal out for. The vast majority of the people online is a, is too much. It’s immediately hostile and weird and too scary. So you’ve probably put 99% of the population out with that one bullet point, but for those 1% who love it and are willing to give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep. Fair enough point taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:55] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, and the interesting thing, having, I’m in that, it’s no, I’m not judging that, don’t do that. But now. because it’s a few simple commands and if it’s set out with instructions, how to do it. Yeah, it’s actually quite simple. it’s actually a lot simpler than dealing with most of the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:20:14] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; ui.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can, are you in effect then memorizing the things that you need as opposed to having an understanding of, ever every single thing that you type? Is it more a set of, okay, this is now part of my muscle memory. I know that at this point I need to type this into the terminal even though I don’t fully understand what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:20:30] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Most of the time, when it’s set up, all I’m ever doing is wanting to just run or serve at 11, which is just basically, I, you just do a run command. It’s that one command, and I’ve put it into a short key anyway, so it just, it’s, I don’t have to think to get it up and running. But of course when you’re installing all these different packages, which is what you do with these things, it’s, it’s all made possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And why it’s popular now I think, is because we have. No js, which allows us to pull in all these packages and work on our local environment. So the idea of installing all these different packages and controlling those is, scary. It was scary to me. It’s still scary to me, but,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:11] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; so far, yeah, you never really see what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you, you, you don’t quite get a visual. you get it in the terminal, you get some sort of. Text-based feedback that things have happened, but okay, where did those packages go? What just happened? Where is it on my computer? How can I get to it? And, of course the answer is you don’t really need to, anyway, sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, okay. Carry on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:35] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; No, that’s, brilliant. It’s exactly my experience. and, but now, it’s starting to go, oh, it’s not that difficult at all actually. Yeah. And it just works anyway, and I know where it’s going. Yes. Yeah. I, it. It’s surprising how quickly you change and how it’s not as difficult as you first think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But anyway, yeah, and the other problem of course, with a static site generators is there are, so many choices out there. No industry standard. You can’t really look at this. If I just go over to the Jam Stack site here, we’ll see now on their filter here, it’s listing 365 different generators. Now, gosh, in all honesty, some of them you wouldn’t really think of as a site generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I just go to this on license, we’ll see this WP two static, which is a, now I think defunct. I tried to use this actually a way of turning, a WordPress site into a static site. it maybe does work. It didn’t work the last time I tried it. You, have a solution to do that, don’t you? That you use?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:38] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. I’m not using that one, but I, have a plugin which enables me to turn static to turn WordPress websites into static, and then it shuffles it over to Netlify or. Bonnie, CDN or whatever, Amazon, whatever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:52] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yep. Yeah. I, it may be listed on there. I don’t think it is, but, no. Yeah, there, there are some big players that everybody knows about because of the popularity of reactors, library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then next JS goes with that as a sort of static site generator for that. Hugh goes very popular because it’s quick, but it’s built on a language like go. And then we have all these other ones, which are perhaps. Declining in the popularity that were heavy, that were very much JavaScript frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gatsby is one of those, popular ones coming forward now are Astro and stuff like this. The big, really what I’m trying to show here is the fact that there is so many choices, not one absolute leader in the area as there is with the dynamic with WordPress. And many of these will now be. Not broken, but they will not be getting the support that they need, Funding these things is, quite a tricky thing. So there, I think there are some downsides that go. if you move towards this static site generator, way many as retired as I’ve put here, but there’s also a lot to go into setting up a blog. Like we’re saying, all these different components that you make up in just your head or alone, we’re saying, oh, I want this image and this description to come in for Facebook, a different one for Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;all of that kind of stuff. you’re gonna have to code all these different lines in, if you want the dates to do this, you have to do this if you are doing it manually. So there’s a lot of elements Yeah. that you have to do. And also, the big thing is that it’s the criticism, of setting site generators is that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this benefit as well, but it’s cobbled together out of various bits of tech. it’s, like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:24:40] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; you said, it’s a house of cards. There’s this whole sort of, exactly that House of Cards, you remove one card halfway up the stack and many, more things collapse as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:24:51] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for our job, of course, the main thing is though, I don’t think it’s that relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we wanted a, a ui, a CMS type UI for. Multi-author where we’re both adding to this, then that’s an extra complexity on top of the stuff that you have to do that. And there are, there is a free option. There’s dcap, which is great, which you could use, as a free CMS to do that. But otherwise they get quite expensive if you want to set them up and make ’em a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and there’s no inbuilt comment, none of the dynamic stuff, of course, that you get on the service or the commenting system or the search. But then. I think that’s a topic. We could do a whole topic on this. What there are other solutions here. ’cause you could argue also on the WordPress side that things like caching make the commenting system difficult anyway and searches, and particularly I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good. Unless you do some work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:25:43] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; no, but it’s interesting ’cause they are all, they’re all parts of the thought process to going in, if you can’t tick all those boxes, it may be dynamic isn’t something that you wanna put on the shelf. Maybe dynamic is something that you want to do, WordPress and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if those things are things that you can cope with, particularly the second to last one, the multi-author bit. Yes. then yeah, go static and and. You’ve been through this process, and here’s the next bullet point, Why 11? That’s where you’ve settled? Yeah. Interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve got 360 plus to choose from. Why that one? How did that make&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:26:21] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; its way to the top? Exactly. I’ll just take one thing actually just on the commenting system. We’ll just go back on that one ’cause it maybe is worth talking about it. ’cause one thing that interests me and maybe the easier route, although it’s in WordPress as well, is to, I’m quite interested in web mentions and all of that indie stuff, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. And how you could employ them on sites. But anyway, sorry. Why 11 two? So why really? Why have I. Move towards that. I guess it’s the people that I’ve been following recently. I’ve talked about that. mainly because let’s just go over to their site ’cause it says it all on there because it’s, pictures itself as the simpler static site generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it’s probably the easiest route in for somebody like me who doesn’t understand JavaScript. so that’s probably the key thing. Lemme just have a look. It’s un opinionated. Is that a proper word? Yeah, I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:27:12] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; think so. Yeah. It does not have an opinion is on opinionated. Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:27:16] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. In the sense that you’re not gonna know if 11 is being used unless declare it in some sort of way where even with the other static site generators, they’re probably likely to output something to help you along your way, which will give away that it is that particular static site generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it’s, I think it’s the only example I can think of that. Yeah, that’s really&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:27:38] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; interesting. ’cause yeah, you would’ve thought even to just promote the project, it would be, it’s a choice that they’ve made deliberately to have the ht ML or whatever is being surfaced on the front end. To deliberately strip out everything, which shows that it has been built with 11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because if you think back to the origins of the project, that could have been a very sensible thing to put in because as the project grew, more people would, right click view source, ah, eleventy. Interesting. I’ll go and explore that. But they’ve made the decision to have none of that in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you know that free marketing has gone away, but, for the benefit of the speed of the website and all of that, it’s a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:28:23] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; And, when we say they, it’s really one man. It’s leatherman. Yeah. Yeah. it’s been his project, which is, yeah, it’s just been that, his journey has been WordPress to jackal, to, creating eleventy as a version of jackal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do static site and he’s got these kind of things, which made me align with it, His approach to the web. okay. but it is very flexible because, lemme just go to their site again because it lists these, I think it does over here. no it doesn’t. let me go over to some of my other points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s used on a lot of well-known sites already,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:02] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; gosh, no kidding. Look at that. Yeah. Nasa,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:06] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; we’ve got the W three C now. It’s used for various different pages. Yeah, it might be a sub domain of something, but still, yeah. WordPress is also used on nasa, so there’s overlap with this, where it’s needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web dev, notify, lots and lots of different Chrome developers, so it’s got good. And it’s got really good people. That’s the main thing here. I’ve listed a few of ’em out, but I can see them here as people who contribute to it. Who, so I can see here, there’s, her name’s just gone now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miriam. Suzanne. There you go. Miriam, Suzanne. Yes. somebody writing that. I see Michelle Barker over here. I’m sure if I stared at this. Oh yes. I can see Stephanie Eccles. Lots of people here that we mention who are big fans of that. Let me go back to the notes here, ’cause I’m. Getting sidetracked again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the other thing is as well, if you are using something like 11 T compared to say, another JAMstack solution, what it’s known for is its quick build times, which is quite important. So you’re building your end and you’re probably rooting it through to GitHub, which is then going on to something like gi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netlify. Yeah. And you, and there’s a cost to the build time on that. So if it takes a very long time, which something like Gatsby can take, 20 if not a hundred times longer than something like 11 t could to do similar number of pages. So it’s quite good on that if you want to stay within your free allowance, I’ve put it down as a benefit, that it’s not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VC funded, venture capital is funded. Okay. But it’s also a negative I think, as well. Yeah, I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:30:48] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; mean you’ve got that whole hit by a boss thing, haven’t you with it. if it’s one person, that means it’s great. You’ve got this one point of contact, but also you’ve got this one point of failure,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:30:59] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:00] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. And&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:01] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; 11, it’s been quite interesting ’cause obviously it’s been this personal project, it’s taken off ’cause it’s met the needs of a lot of people who share his same view about keeping things as simple as possible, and and really taken off. With particularly people who, people like Miriam, Suzanne, people who contribute to, making CSS what it is today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:24] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:26] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; so it’s taken off, but Netlify funded it for some time. cloud Canyon did that because they were CMS. That’s use things like Astra and Eleventy or stuff like that. now I think to, it has been self-funded for some time, which is. Some of these people over here were some of the contributors to, they were paying their own money to use it to help him to put more time into the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, just recently, and I dunno what difference that’s gonna make to things, he’s just joined the font awesome team who are doing another product, which is, it’ll come to me in a minute. Something we can Okay. That’s Webber awesome. Oh,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:08] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; okay. Oh yeah. I’d heard of that. Yeah, that’s gone out of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve forgotten what that is. You saw that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:13] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. Fantastic video. Yes. yeah. Yeah, that’s right. So yeah, so it’s,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:16] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah, it’s a part of that. That video was fantastic. That video was like, it was shot in Hollywood or something. That was incredible. Anyway, sorry, what an aside. Okay, moving on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:28] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; and that’s it really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s probably just covered the. The main things were the things that came up in your mind about this? No,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:35] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; I think the, I’m just curious to see because I, like I said, I haven’t used it. I’m a staunch WordPress fan, and I can, totally see why some of these things have got your, got your intuitions, you just wanna be out there and figuring out how all this works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m just keen to see how it works and in the end. How it works in terms of, being, let’s say a time saver. Now, I, know that there’s all the arguments about, okay, I don’t want a bloated CMSI don’t wanna pay for server time. That’s not being used. I don’t have a need for a commenting system and all that kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I’m, interested to see how it saves time and money over time. I think they’re the two things that I wanna see from this, how quick is it to. Get up and running, how quick is it to create a page? How quick is it to, I don’t know, implement some of the designs like the bento one that you did recently?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How quick is it to inject those into it? and I’m fascinated by the cost implications. ’cause I imagine with this, the cost is for a typical, I don’t know, Brochure website for somebody living in a town, you know where there’s gonna be thousands of views a year, not millions of views a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m interested to see how close to free it is. ’cause I’m imagining it will approximate very close to free at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:33:55] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, you, that’s what we’re doing at the moment, while we just do it with the basic web platform and no. Third party platform at all for this site. we check it out, we get our free hosting and I’m sure there’ll always be some free hosting for the sort of visits Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That we get. The amount of traffic that we get. Yep. So really all this is building on the Y 11 to fits. It is because we can add in something to take, to remove some of the chore of having to update things that would. Come with WordPress out of the box. Yeah. there’s no doubt about it. If I was, taken on a job that, had a big, large content site and it needed multi authors and it was at my skill level, there’s no doubt it would be WordPress That would be the choice for this sort of thing if I had to do this job, because there’s no way that I would be linking all of this stuff up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:34:45] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; To give them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:34:46] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; the UI that they needed. Yeah. yeah. so that would be the obvious choice. But when it comes to this, where. Effectively, it’s only you or I might have to update the content here. obviously the benefits of static is once you stick it up there, unless you mess with it, it’s gonna live on forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where you put, like on a dynamic platform, someone else can mess up your website for You and you have to update, don’t you? Because you know you have to. Yeah. security&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:16] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; patches, things like that. Yeah. It’s interesting. I’ll tell you what, it’s gonna be fascinating. I, you are gonna, you’re gonna ring WordPress out of my cold, dead hands, but, but nevertheless, it’s a fascinating ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, I’m here to watch it all happen,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:32] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:32] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Shall we, shall we do next time,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:35] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; shall we?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:36] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, you could highlight what you think is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:38] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; gonna happen next time. Yeah. Okay. I think maybe we will try and we’ll take one of those, old sites. I’m not sure which ones. One of the, and I’ll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try and put some eleventy in it with my basic skills of what I know about it so far, so you can see it in action. I think we can probably do that as an audio as well, because Oh yeah, if I just explain Yeah. The process, I think it will make sense, but, we’ll definitely need YouTube so you can see what I’m doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So perhaps we’ll give that a bash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:05] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, that sounds good to me. you’ll be able to check this out, at the No Script Show website. It’s no script show slash 15 ’cause that is the episode that we’re on. You’ll be able to find the show notes that we’re showing on the screen, but if you’re listening to it, on the audio, then there are some show notes there that you can click links on if any of the bits and pieces have raised your.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levels of curiosity, about 11 or indeed WordPress. So shall we call it a day? Is that a wrap? Yeah, I think so. Alright. See you. I’ll see you next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:37] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:37] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; thanks. Bye bye. Bye-bye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt; &lt;/details&gt;&lt;/details&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Easier web design and coding with Bento Grids</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/5/" />
    <updated>2024-11-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/5/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Redesigning a Bistro/café site. Part 2. Coding with HTML and CSS</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/4/" />
    <updated>2024-10-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/4/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Redesigning a Bistro site. Part 1. The Design.</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/3/" />
    <updated>2024-10-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/3/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Redesigning a vets site. Part 2. Coding with CSS and Testing</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/2/" />
    <updated>2024-10-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/2/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Redesigning a vets site. Part 1. UX Design and Planning</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/1/" />
    <updated>2024-10-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/1/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Frontend Divide:- UX Designers vs JavaScript Specialists</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/14/" />
    <updated>2024-07-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/14/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are revisiting a 5 year old debate summed up in Chris Coyier&#39;s 2019 CSS Tricks article called &lt;a href=&quot;https://css-tricks.com/the-great-divide/&quot;&gt;the Great Divide&lt;/a&gt; and looking at what has changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-behind-the-great-divide&quot;&gt;What&#39;s behind the &amp;quot;Great Divide&amp;quot;?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A worry:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over &amp;quot;gatekeeping&amp;quot; and gender bias. If you have to be a programmer &lt;a href=&quot;https://rachelandrew.co.uk/archives/2019/01/30/html-css-and-our-vanishing-industry-entry-points/&quot;&gt;accessible routes to web development narrow.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That web standards will fall?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That code complexity is a cost to the environment and users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-does-the-divide-exist&quot;&gt;Why does the divide exist?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTML and CSS not meeting the (perceived) component based design needs of the time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSS not seen as easy to scope for large scale team project work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Browsers not being trusted. Better to use JS to tell them what to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marketing (although Meta and Google seem to have lost interest in their React and Angular offerings).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The amazing real time user interaction JavaScript brought.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CSS frustrates many. Mostly through not learning it, understanding its declarative nature and impatience. &lt;strong&gt;Rachel Andrew wrote:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;CSS is simultaneously too easy to bother with, yet so hard it needs to be wrapped up in a ball of JavaScript in case it scares the horses&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-it-getting-smaller&quot;&gt;Is it getting smaller?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSS is being rapidly refactored - removing common dependencies on JS (including &lt;a href=&quot;https://astro-zerojs-transitions.vercel.app/&quot;&gt;interactive ones&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Browsers working together to speed up progress.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web components offering a standards based interoperable alternative to 3rd party JS components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JS fatigue. Maintaining a complex set of dependencies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Cascade is back with &lt;code&gt;@layer. @scope and :where()&lt;/code&gt; A move to doing more with less code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WebAssembly (WASM) - a new web standard with more power than JS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User demands:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For web content on their terms. Increasingly removing our visual designs and expecting content on any type of device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frustration with CSS often came from mimicking print.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The need to deliver fast, green, valid and accessible HTML content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://noscript.show/img/divided.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-wordpress-divide&quot;&gt;The WordPress divide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those who use a WYSIWYG builder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More recently, those who develop themes as WordPress moves from PHP themes to JS block themes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rachelandrew.co.uk/archives/2019/01/30/html-css-and-our-vanishing-industry-entry-points/&quot;&gt;Rachel Andrew: HTML, CSS and our vanishing industry entry points&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://heydonworks.com/article/reluctant-gatekeeping:-the-problem-with-full-stack/&quot;&gt;Heydon Pickering: Reluctant Gatekeeping: The Problem With Full Stack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chriscoyier.net/2023/02/16/noodling-on-wordpress-in-2023/&quot;&gt;Chris Coyier: Noodling on WordPress in 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>