<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-gb">
  <title>No Script Show</title>
  <subtitle>Building solid websites simply.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://noscript.show/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://noscript.show/" />
  <updated>2025-01-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://noscript.show/</id>
  <author>
    <name>No Script Show</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Long-term WordPress user tries building with 11ty (a Static Site Generator)</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/6/" />
    <updated>2025-01-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/6/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As WordPress user we know how to build dynamic sites. We know next to nothing about Static Site Generators and the Jamstack. Here we rebuild a HTML site with 11ty (Eleventy). We also look at adding a CMS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-we-cover&quot;&gt;Things we cover&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What we need to run 11ty (Node, Git and free hosting).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting 11ty from scratch (installing 11ty).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating our first page. Converting Markdown to HTML.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating a header and footer template for our site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introducing Front Matter (like WordPress custom fields).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding CSS and bundling with a Nunjucks template.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bringing in other website assets with the Eleventy config file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making the site&#39;s head dynamic for SEO (doing the job of a WordPress SEO plugin).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making HTML more manageable with partials.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adjusting CSS classes with Front Matter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introducing data (like WordPress&#39;s database), but with a dynamic menu.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding events. Similar to working with WordPress&#39;s post loop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adding a CMS (Decap and locally the Front Matter CMS extension).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/@EleventyVideo/videos&quot;&gt;11ty YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://11tybundle.dev/&quot;&gt;11ty Bundle&lt;/a&gt;. A fabulous place for all the latest by Bob Monsour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are years out of date, but with the help of 11ty docs and Claude AI I could covert to 11ty V3:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://learneleventyfromscratch.com/&quot;&gt;Learn Eleventy From Scratch&lt;/a&gt;. Andy Bell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4wD00RT6d-g&quot;&gt;Turn static HTML/CSS into a blog with CMS using the JAMStack&lt;/a&gt;. Kevin Powell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Static vs dynamic for content heavy websites</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/15/" />
    <updated>2025-01-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/15/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;spoiler&quot;&gt;Spoiler&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is about what to use for the show&#39;s website as the content grows. We&#39;re going to try &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/&quot;&gt;11ty&lt;/a&gt; partly because Nathan&#39;s show &lt;a href=&quot;https://noscript.show/15/wpbuilds.com/&quot;&gt;WP Builds&lt;/a&gt; is already about WordPress, but also 11ty might be a more logical fit for this particular show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-our-site-needs&quot;&gt;What our site needs:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A quicker way to write posts. A text editor or Markdown?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easier way to add SEO metadata, open graph, sitemaps and RSS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A way to automate tags and categories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A quicker way to add performant YouTube videos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-dilemma-of-static-v-dynamic&quot;&gt;The dilemma of Static v Dynamic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An old debate. Dynamic provided what we needed in the early 2000&#39;s, but even by 2008 there was &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;, a SSG (that inspired 11ty). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aaronsw.com/weblog/000404&quot;&gt;Bake don&#39;t fry&lt;/a&gt; by Aaron Swartz in 2002 also got some questioning dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;wordpress&quot;&gt;WordPress&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious choice as most successful blogging platform:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quick and easy to set up with no developer skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A massive range of themes and plugins.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We know it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Well funded… although topical at the moment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;downsides-for-this-shows-site&quot;&gt;Downsides for this show&#39;s site:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Control of the code output. Important to a show focussed on web standards and accessibility *.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using WP would not teach us about alternatives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paying for hosting(caching/backup/security) and time on software update and maintenance **.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not so easy offer a CMS version of our site demos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The intented audience. WP is seen as a no code solution. This show is about how lovely and friendly code can be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* A classic theme would allow this, but control over the modern block themes requires JS skills we don&#39;t have or need.&lt;br&gt;
** We could convert WP to static for free hosting but manually that is a faff. Services that convert WP to static hosting are expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;static-site-generators&quot;&gt;Static Site Generators&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gaining popularity at the moment. The 2024 Web Almanac &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloudcannon.com/blog/the-rise-of-static-first-websites-why-major-brands-are-making-the-switch/&quot;&gt;shows 67% growth in static and hybrid website architectures among the top 10,000 most-visited sites&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;general-problems-with-static-site-generators-ssg-s&quot;&gt;General problems with Static Site Generators (SSG&#39;s)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Needs some skills or willingness to use a terminal rather than a UI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many choices. No industry standard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many have retired.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are lots to set up with a blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&#39;s cobbled together out of various bits of tech. House of cards?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to add the CMS yourself for a multi author blog.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No inbuilt commenting system or search.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-11ty&quot;&gt;Why 11ty?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s 360 SSG&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamstack.org/generators/&quot;&gt;listed here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Possibly the simplest way to explore SSGs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unopinionated. There&#39;s no way to know you have used it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flexible with a range of templating languages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You add complexity as needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fast build times.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not VC funded *.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Users include: W3C, UK gov, US gov, Google, Cern, NASA, A11Y Project, Web.dev and CSS Tricks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fans include: Miriam Suzanne, Lea Verou, Stephanie Eckles, Heydon Pickering, Andy Bell, Chris Coyier, Michelle Barker, Sara Soueidan and Ben Myers (many people mentioned in this show).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* 11ty has recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.11ty.dev/blog/eleventy-font-awesome/&quot;&gt;joined Font Awesome.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt; 
&lt;summary&gt;Transcript&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:06] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Hello and welcome to the No Script Show. After some visual YouTube only content, we’re back with an episode that also works as an audio podcast too. Here we’re looking at a longstanding debate, which seems to get more significant all the time. That is whether or when to go a static or dynamic route when building websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As this podcast is focused on catching up with changes in the web platform, we don’t generally talk about third party frameworks and platforms, but as the show’s own website gets larger, we may need help to manage it. This has left us with the static. Dynamic dilemma, and I’m joined as always to have this chat by David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How you doing, David?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:47] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I’m really good. yeah, so should we spoil things and say that we already know what we’re going to try and use? Yeah. for this site we’re gonna try 11, which is a static site generator. the main reason for that, is, Is that you already do a show, which is on WordPress anyway, and that’s our background anyway, so we know that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By taking a look at that, it gives us something new to do. But, I think this conversation came up. We thought, we might as well do this topic. ’cause you asked me the question with you we know each other from WordPress and I’ve been starting to learn 11 I. For the idea of making kind of large content sites with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you said you’re just not swapping one set of complications for another with that. And I thought, yes I am. but I thought there’s a good conversation, but why I might want to do that. So I guess, yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:01:48] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; what this is about. It’s interesting ’cause obviously if, like me, you are heavily embedded in the WordPress ecosystem and continuing to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I might add, there’s a learning curve just to make WordPress work. You could really not know anything about html CSS, JavaScript, any of that, I’m sure many people do. And so you spend your time learning how to make WordPress achieve what it is that you want to achieve with code or plugins or whatever it may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I did get the intuition that if the no script show website needed some sort of capability to manage the content as it grows, you’ve gotta have some system in place. It can’t just be writing static HDML files and uploading them. It’d be nice to be able to automate some features or have some CMS in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did wonder what would the learning curve for 11 look like? And if it basically ended up being the same kind of learning curve that you do with WordPress, I was just thinking, what’s the point in that? You’re just swapping one difficulty for a different difficulty. And so that was why I prompted that conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which then in the background led you to create the content for this episode, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:03:02] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. And I. More logically, I think it’s more appropriate for this show because what we tried to do is make it different from what we were doing with WebPress to get back to relearning the web platform. And mostly it was geared around the idea of keeping it as simple as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. So we don’t talk about the other stuff, but obviously we’ve moved to that point here, and this is probably why it’s more logical because. If we go with something like Eleventy in particular, which I’ll discuss later, it allows you to opt in gradually for what you need, rather than start with this kind of monolith system where even with the JAMstack type stuff, you can end up that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should we bring up the website where we’ve got some of the notes to just guide us through our conversation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:03:46] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah. I, would just say at this point, if it’s all right, David, that I, have no experience with Eleventy at all, so really I’m just your. The here today to be a foil. if anything doesn’t make sense to me, I’m going to ask you what’s going on and what have you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I’ve had various conversations with you. You’ve outlined how it works and what have you. But if I end up being incredibly ignorant, apologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:04:09] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; apologies to anybody who’s in the levity community ’cause they really clever people there. And I’m just. just starting to grapple with it to understand it, but not having really any JavaScript background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that is a program that runs on JavaScript. I’m really not that knowledgeable. Okay. So I’m probably gonna stuff up with the things that I say. But anyway, let’s, and I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:04:30] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; just say though, at this point it, it’s interesting because it has excited you though. yeah. And obviously in these videos we try not to be that person, you’re just demonstrating how excited you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think it’s fair to say that you are really. Pleased that you’ve come across this and you’ve obviously explored a load of different options and this is the one that you’ve got into. And so in a way, in a sense, I’m happy that you found it. ’cause it, you used to have that same feeling I think about WordPress and now you’ve, you’ve swapped it for this, so that’s nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve got another project to get your teeth into. It’s lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:05:04] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. and particularly with that, it’s quite what’s quite interesting and it’s. It wasn’t known at the time. I didn’t really understand the 11 t. I didn’t know what the options were if you wanted something outside of WordPress, and certainly on that kind of JAMstack side, but it turns out that most of the people I’ve ended up talking about on this show, the people that are getting me back into the web platform and learning CSS, again, are a lot of the people who are big fans of this particular thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So interesting. It’s yeah, it’s like I found the thing that might. Fit my needs best. it’s gonna depend. So let’s start with the site, what this site needs, because it’s becoming, we’ve done 30 sort of bits of content. some of it hasn’t even gone on to the site. We haven’t redesigned it yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so I. We are we getting to the point where doing it manually, as I am just writing out the HT ml and sticking up a new page on it, is getting a bit, tedious, particularly with the SEO stuff, right? That has to go in there. So we need, as I’ve listed there, a quicker way to write a. Posts and obviously WordPress or a dynamic system is likely to give you a text editor where you are more likely to go if you are on the static Versions of that is using markdown, which is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty new to me. Are you familiar with it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:06:25] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; I’m familiar with it, but it’s never been something that, that gelled with me. I’ve always preferred, basically not mark down. I’ve always preferred to write the text and then highlight the bits and then add the correct formatting via some kind of editor, be it tiny MCE or now the block editor in WordPress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That just works with me. I know people who are just huge fans of Mark down. To the point where, you know, any app that doesn’t support markdown, be that like a note taking app or what have you, they just won’t use it. ’cause they, it’s become part of their muscle memory. So for me, no, but I understand its benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:01] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; And it’s a big thing in the WordPress community. A lot of people, there’s plugins, you can add it in if you want to, if you wanna work with that. but yeah, Yeah, so it’s something I’m gonna have to learn to speed up the writing of these posts if I want to do it that way. With markdown, I think you’ll only&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:16] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; need a handful of shortcuts if you like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think you know, headings and links and there won’t be too much. I think that you need to commit to memory. So I think once you’ve got 10 things in your head, that’ll probably be all that you need for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:30] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, it makes it. I think, writing with Mark down is quicker than actually using the text editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m sure you’re right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:36] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:38] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; but I gotta get used to that. But an easy way, and this is really the key thing, I think adding in the SEO stuff that you do when you want a different description on that and it gets a little bit more complex with, Some of that stuff, particularly with the open graph stuff, if you want a particular image to show, which we often do on this one, sitemaps and RSS feeds, all that kind of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A way to automate the tags and categories, which we’ve effectively got two categories. There were the sort of separate learn videos that I did separate to our main podcast and, now we’ve already, because we. We don’t know where this show’s going. We’ve already ended up with a third, which is our kind of YouTube only content, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;yeah. a way to be able to organize that kind of stuff. And also, a way of being able to add the performant YouTube videos, which I’ve had to do manually each time, to, yeah, it’s it’s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:30] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; interesting looking at those bullet points because for my need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:34] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; WordPress&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:35] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; satisfies that in, every one of those bullet points works really well with WordPress. from the perspective of this and the endeavor that we’re doing here, it it’s interesting to see those things are now the bare minimum of what you need. It basically boils down to four or five things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. And if you can find a platform that satisfies those four or five things, then you’ve hit gold. yeah. Okay. Carry on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:58] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; there might be a few other things, like dates and stuff like that. Yeah. Okay. You could write those in if you want modified date to do automatically as soon as you change the post and that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. things that you could do with both systems. So yeah, the dilemma of static or, dynamic and in all honesty, when I thought we’d be doing this show, what I thought we’d probably end up doing is doing a kind of WordPress, version of it first. Because obviously it’s what we know, but I didn’t really realize until recently that this is a bit of an old debate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as I understand it, it’s like dynamic obviously came in the early two thousands. Obviously WordPress, not the newest of them came in, what, 2003?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:09:44] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:09:44] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I think so. Yep. And that took care of the fact that, we needed to have. Lots and lots of pages on as such and things like blogs and that take care of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I did, what I didn’t realize is that the whole question of is dynamic all we need or is kin static play a role was already there. There was jackal, which, I’ll bring up the website. I know this is going out as audio, but, It won’t make any difference to this. I’ll just bring up their site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is, a static site generator that’s been running off Ruby since about 2008, I think. Okay. still popular, so it’s not exactly as if, this concept is new. It’s quite new to me. And I guess with that, the popular term, JAMstack coming in. Probably from about 2000, not sure 15, 16 or onwards. it’s probably changed things and what we can do with JavaScript now is changed things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But yeah, the idea of being able to statically, generate these things and. Zach Leatherman, the author behind Eleventy, who I was listening to him and he was pointed to an article, bake Don’t Fry by Aman Schwartz, which, dates back to 2002 where he set off some kind of debate questioning. dynamic, whether we should be doing it on a computer end rather than having to generate the content that the user sees Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a live server, then that’s really what we’re talking about, I think. Yeah. yeah, WordPress, as I said, was the obvious choice, because. As we know, it’s the most successful plugin platform. It’s quick and easy to set up with no developer skills, massive range of themes and plugins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So pretty much any functionality or look that you might want, you could probably get out the box. We know it. It’s well funded, it’s got that background, although it’s a little bit topical at the moment, but we won’t get into that. But for me, the downsides for this site show, was that we’re all about the, the code about, working with the CSS and learning all of that new stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it’s important to have something that could, we could have complete control of the. Source code that we’re outputting, particularly as we’re gonna use our site as well as an example sometimes of the things that we talk about. And I think you can lose that with WordPress. You don’t get such same control over things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:12:17] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. you do, have that control, but the, barrier to that, you have to spend many, hours, years possibly really understanding how WordPress is built and constructed in order to learn how to strip out what you don’t want and put in exact. What you do want, which is why I guess enterprise agencies in the WordPress space can charge enterprise level, fees for their products, which presumably spit out exactly what the client wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in this case, it sounds like 11 is the opposite. You start with kind of nothing and you build in the bits that you want, as opposed to WordPress, which has a ton of stuff out the box that you then have to maybe strip out if it’s not exactly what you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:13:00] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, exactly. It is working from the opposite side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it’s not just the, where the dynamic stuff happens. Which, in our case is on the, our own personal computers rather than on the server. But it’s also about, I think the approach generally, although not necessarily true of all static site generators, they come with their own set of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But certainly with Eleventy, it is the kind of, it’s been purposely made with the idea that. Zach Leatherman, the person behind it is really of the belief that most people should be able to make their websites with just plain old the web platform. Yeah. H ml and CSS. Yep. And then if you do need the dependencies, you can just add ’em in as you need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s been the kind of approach to that particular project. the thing is though, why I thought we might not do it, because just before I, got into looking into 11, I really got into the idea of using the classic theme and building on WordPress and building my own setup with that one and coding it from the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you’re to move over and go to modern, WordPress with it, you have to get into the block themes really, if you’re to take advantage of going forward that route. So then that requires me skills that I don’t have or I’m not going to need. It’s going to box me into. The kind of WordPress React route or something to learn to have that same control over things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:21] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; So are you meaning particularly JavaScript skills that you might need to have? Okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:26] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:27] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:27] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; So somebody can, they can control their code output on WordPress, but you probably need some extra skills if you’re going to go the new modern. JavaScript first route with WordPress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s, so that kind of, that, that kind of skilled me outta the situation even though I don’t have JavaScript skills and it, I don’t wanna be boxed in so much to one particular, JavaScript, if you like, or one approach with that, Got it. yeah. Yeah. So the other downside is that we would, if we use WordPress, then we wouldn’t be learning an alternative, which is always good to know, different things that you can use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we’d have to pay for our hosting and there might be some other things that we’d have to pay for caching, backup, security, that kind of stuff that I do on the WordPress sites that I manage. It is not so easy to ’cause something I would quite like to do with our shows. For the last three episodes that we did, we made a demo site to Yeah, and made that public for anybody if they wanted to use it just to analyze it or use bits of it in the start of their projects, which I want to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I’d like to be able to do is to do some. not necessarily a CMS version of it, but just use, add a, an eleventy version of it. Yeah. And it would be a lot easier to do that by just adding some extra things, like there’s a permanent header and footer template and you just change the content for extra pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’d like to make a version of that. That would be. It would be more difficult to share that with people if I wanted to do a WordPress version of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:15:58] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; So do you mean you might atomize the site? So you, okay, if you like this header here’s the bit for the header and if you like this footer, here’s the bit for the footer, that kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you’d be able to share those components, those&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:16:12] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; jigsaw&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:16:13] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; pieces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:16:14] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; the risk sharing that what all I was thinking of, say we did the bistro site that we did. Yeah. And that was just an example. If I made a version of that, I could decide, and I think we’ll do this, maybe we’ll do this as the next episode, just show how you could just add 11 two to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So say on that bistro site as say, there’s a lot more pages you want on it, and I think. Okay. That means I have to change the header and the photo on each. Got it. Pages. Got it. I can turn this so I can do a CMS version if you like, one that you can do. there something that makes it easier to manage your content really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay. I’m not talking about, UI or anything like that. Okay. But yeah, also the intended audience. I think it’s the downside for this one is to say, we’re really about getting back to the web platform and learning stuff there. And partly because WordPress is. More popularly seen as a no code solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that’s really not fair when all the people are really serious developers who use WordPress, but generally it’s seen as that where our show is a bit about Pumping up a little bit how lovely and friendly code can be these days. Yeah. so it’s more suiting to that different audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Okay. Great. Yeah, so that’s that. also, let’s talk a bit about the static site generators. So there is, there do seem to be gaining popularity at the moment. So there was the. 2024 Web Almanac, which, was just so in showing that there’s a 67% growth in static and hybrid website. A, architectures amongst the top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is difficult for me to say for some reason, 10,000 most visited sites. Gosh, that’s a lot. Wow. It’s, it is a huge growth. Yeah. I mean there is, there is, talk of it here, obviously Cloud Canyon, because they, do a CMS for static. People are obviously going to promote that. I think there is something, if you actually go to the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Itself, the way of being able to measure that’s quite tricky is particularly with something like Eleventy, because you can’t tell Eleventy is being used ‘&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:26] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; cause&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:27] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Eleventy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:27] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; doesn’t put anything out to identify itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:30] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. anybody interested in that would probably just want to go and look at, the table of contents and probably the jump stack area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;because they’ve had to assess on the basis of speed. I believe how. what sites are statically generated and what’s are being dynamically. Okay. So it might not be entirely accurate, but Right. It does seem that there is a trend towards that. And obviously that’s where the growth has been.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s other static site generators like Astro 11 is fairly stable, but it’s still been growing over the years that it’s been around. So there is a general growth in those. So there is that, but there are some general problems. Shall we just quickly cover those? Yeah, problem. Let’s go for it. Yep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. These are problems that WordPress solves for you, for other people, which is you do need some skills and you certainly need a willingness, I think, to use a terminal to do command line rather than a nice friendly ui. So that’s still something which is a bit alien to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:29] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, I think, a lot of people, that is already a bridge too far, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you Exactly. really getting the terminal out for. The vast majority of the people online is a, is too much. It’s immediately hostile and weird and too scary. So you’ve probably put 99% of the population out with that one bullet point, but for those 1% who love it and are willing to give it a go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep. Fair enough point taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:55] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, and the interesting thing, having, I’m in that, it’s no, I’m not judging that, don’t do that. But now. because it’s a few simple commands and if it’s set out with instructions, how to do it. Yeah, it’s actually quite simple. it’s actually a lot simpler than dealing with most of the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:20:14] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; ui.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can, are you in effect then memorizing the things that you need as opposed to having an understanding of, ever every single thing that you type? Is it more a set of, okay, this is now part of my muscle memory. I know that at this point I need to type this into the terminal even though I don’t fully understand what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:20:30] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Most of the time, when it’s set up, all I’m ever doing is wanting to just run or serve at 11, which is just basically, I, you just do a run command. It’s that one command, and I’ve put it into a short key anyway, so it just, it’s, I don’t have to think to get it up and running. But of course when you’re installing all these different packages, which is what you do with these things, it’s, it’s all made possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And why it’s popular now I think, is because we have. No js, which allows us to pull in all these packages and work on our local environment. So the idea of installing all these different packages and controlling those is, scary. It was scary to me. It’s still scary to me, but,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:11] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; so far, yeah, you never really see what’s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do you, you, you don’t quite get a visual. you get it in the terminal, you get some sort of. Text-based feedback that things have happened, but okay, where did those packages go? What just happened? Where is it on my computer? How can I get to it? And, of course the answer is you don’t really need to, anyway, sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, okay. Carry on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:35] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; No, that’s, brilliant. It’s exactly my experience. and, but now, it’s starting to go, oh, it’s not that difficult at all actually. Yeah. And it just works anyway, and I know where it’s going. Yes. Yeah. I, it. It’s surprising how quickly you change and how it’s not as difficult as you first think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But anyway, yeah, and the other problem of course, with a static site generators is there are, so many choices out there. No industry standard. You can’t really look at this. If I just go over to the Jam Stack site here, we’ll see now on their filter here, it’s listing 365 different generators. Now, gosh, in all honesty, some of them you wouldn’t really think of as a site generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I just go to this on license, we’ll see this WP two static, which is a, now I think defunct. I tried to use this actually a way of turning, a WordPress site into a static site. it maybe does work. It didn’t work the last time I tried it. You, have a solution to do that, don’t you? That you use?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:38] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. I’m not using that one, but I, have a plugin which enables me to turn static to turn WordPress websites into static, and then it shuffles it over to Netlify or. Bonnie, CDN or whatever, Amazon, whatever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:52] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yep. Yeah. I, it may be listed on there. I don’t think it is, but, no. Yeah, there, there are some big players that everybody knows about because of the popularity of reactors, library.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then next JS goes with that as a sort of static site generator for that. Hugh goes very popular because it’s quick, but it’s built on a language like go. And then we have all these other ones, which are perhaps. Declining in the popularity that were heavy, that were very much JavaScript frameworks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gatsby is one of those, popular ones coming forward now are Astro and stuff like this. The big, really what I’m trying to show here is the fact that there is so many choices, not one absolute leader in the area as there is with the dynamic with WordPress. And many of these will now be. Not broken, but they will not be getting the support that they need, Funding these things is, quite a tricky thing. So there, I think there are some downsides that go. if you move towards this static site generator, way many as retired as I’ve put here, but there’s also a lot to go into setting up a blog. Like we’re saying, all these different components that you make up in just your head or alone, we’re saying, oh, I want this image and this description to come in for Facebook, a different one for Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;all of that kind of stuff. you’re gonna have to code all these different lines in, if you want the dates to do this, you have to do this if you are doing it manually. So there’s a lot of elements Yeah. that you have to do. And also, the big thing is that it’s the criticism, of setting site generators is that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this benefit as well, but it’s cobbled together out of various bits of tech. it’s, like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:24:40] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; you said, it’s a house of cards. There’s this whole sort of, exactly that House of Cards, you remove one card halfway up the stack and many, more things collapse as a result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:24:51] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for our job, of course, the main thing is though, I don’t think it’s that relevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we wanted a, a ui, a CMS type UI for. Multi-author where we’re both adding to this, then that’s an extra complexity on top of the stuff that you have to do that. And there are, there is a free option. There’s dcap, which is great, which you could use, as a free CMS to do that. But otherwise they get quite expensive if you want to set them up and make ’em a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and there’s no inbuilt comment, none of the dynamic stuff, of course, that you get on the service or the commenting system or the search. But then. I think that’s a topic. We could do a whole topic on this. What there are other solutions here. ’cause you could argue also on the WordPress side that things like caching make the commenting system difficult anyway and searches, and particularly I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good. Unless you do some work on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:25:43] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; no, but it’s interesting ’cause they are all, they’re all parts of the thought process to going in, if you can’t tick all those boxes, it may be dynamic isn’t something that you wanna put on the shelf. Maybe dynamic is something that you want to do, WordPress and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if those things are things that you can cope with, particularly the second to last one, the multi-author bit. Yes. then yeah, go static and and. You’ve been through this process, and here’s the next bullet point, Why 11? That’s where you’ve settled? Yeah. Interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve got 360 plus to choose from. Why that one? How did that make&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:26:21] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; its way to the top? Exactly. I’ll just take one thing actually just on the commenting system. We’ll just go back on that one ’cause it maybe is worth talking about it. ’cause one thing that interests me and maybe the easier route, although it’s in WordPress as well, is to, I’m quite interested in web mentions and all of that indie stuff, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. And how you could employ them on sites. But anyway, sorry. Why 11 two? So why really? Why have I. Move towards that. I guess it’s the people that I’ve been following recently. I’ve talked about that. mainly because let’s just go over to their site ’cause it says it all on there because it’s, pictures itself as the simpler static site generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it’s probably the easiest route in for somebody like me who doesn’t understand JavaScript. so that’s probably the key thing. Lemme just have a look. It’s un opinionated. Is that a proper word? Yeah, I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:27:12] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; think so. Yeah. It does not have an opinion is on opinionated. Yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:27:16] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. In the sense that you’re not gonna know if 11 is being used unless declare it in some sort of way where even with the other static site generators, they’re probably likely to output something to help you along your way, which will give away that it is that particular static site generator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it’s, I think it’s the only example I can think of that. Yeah, that’s really&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:27:38] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; interesting. ’cause yeah, you would’ve thought even to just promote the project, it would be, it’s a choice that they’ve made deliberately to have the ht ML or whatever is being surfaced on the front end. To deliberately strip out everything, which shows that it has been built with 11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because if you think back to the origins of the project, that could have been a very sensible thing to put in because as the project grew, more people would, right click view source, ah, eleventy. Interesting. I’ll go and explore that. But they’ve made the decision to have none of that in there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you know that free marketing has gone away, but, for the benefit of the speed of the website and all of that, it’s a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:28:23] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; And, when we say they, it’s really one man. It’s leatherman. Yeah. Yeah. it’s been his project, which is, yeah, it’s just been that, his journey has been WordPress to jackal, to, creating eleventy as a version of jackal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do static site and he’s got these kind of things, which made me align with it, His approach to the web. okay. but it is very flexible because, lemme just go to their site again because it lists these, I think it does over here. no it doesn’t. let me go over to some of my other points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s used on a lot of well-known sites already,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:02] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; gosh, no kidding. Look at that. Yeah. Nasa,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:06] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; we’ve got the W three C now. It’s used for various different pages. Yeah, it might be a sub domain of something, but still, yeah. WordPress is also used on nasa, so there’s overlap with this, where it’s needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Web dev, notify, lots and lots of different Chrome developers, so it’s got good. And it’s got really good people. That’s the main thing here. I’ve listed a few of ’em out, but I can see them here as people who contribute to it. Who, so I can see here, there’s, her name’s just gone now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Miriam. Suzanne. There you go. Miriam, Suzanne. Yes. somebody writing that. I see Michelle Barker over here. I’m sure if I stared at this. Oh yes. I can see Stephanie Eccles. Lots of people here that we mention who are big fans of that. Let me go back to the notes here, ’cause I’m. Getting sidetracked again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and the other thing is as well, if you are using something like 11 T compared to say, another JAMstack solution, what it’s known for is its quick build times, which is quite important. So you’re building your end and you’re probably rooting it through to GitHub, which is then going on to something like gi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netlify. Yeah. And you, and there’s a cost to the build time on that. So if it takes a very long time, which something like Gatsby can take, 20 if not a hundred times longer than something like 11 t could to do similar number of pages. So it’s quite good on that if you want to stay within your free allowance, I’ve put it down as a benefit, that it’s not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VC funded, venture capital is funded. Okay. But it’s also a negative I think, as well. Yeah, I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:30:48] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; mean you’ve got that whole hit by a boss thing, haven’t you with it. if it’s one person, that means it’s great. You’ve got this one point of contact, but also you’ve got this one point of failure,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:30:59] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:00] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. And&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:01] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; 11, it’s been quite interesting ’cause obviously it’s been this personal project, it’s taken off ’cause it’s met the needs of a lot of people who share his same view about keeping things as simple as possible, and and really taken off. With particularly people who, people like Miriam, Suzanne, people who contribute to, making CSS what it is today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:24] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:26] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; so it’s taken off, but Netlify funded it for some time. cloud Canyon did that because they were CMS. That’s use things like Astra and Eleventy or stuff like that. now I think to, it has been self-funded for some time, which is. Some of these people over here were some of the contributors to, they were paying their own money to use it to help him to put more time into the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, just recently, and I dunno what difference that’s gonna make to things, he’s just joined the font awesome team who are doing another product, which is, it’ll come to me in a minute. Something we can Okay. That’s Webber awesome. Oh,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:08] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; okay. Oh yeah. I’d heard of that. Yeah, that’s gone out of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve forgotten what that is. You saw that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:13] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. Fantastic video. Yes. yeah. Yeah, that’s right. So yeah, so it’s,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:16] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah, it’s a part of that. That video was fantastic. That video was like, it was shot in Hollywood or something. That was incredible. Anyway, sorry, what an aside. Okay, moving on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:28] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; and that’s it really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s probably just covered the. The main things were the things that came up in your mind about this? No,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:35] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; I think the, I’m just curious to see because I, like I said, I haven’t used it. I’m a staunch WordPress fan, and I can, totally see why some of these things have got your, got your intuitions, you just wanna be out there and figuring out how all this works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m just keen to see how it works and in the end. How it works in terms of, being, let’s say a time saver. Now, I, know that there’s all the arguments about, okay, I don’t want a bloated CMSI don’t wanna pay for server time. That’s not being used. I don’t have a need for a commenting system and all that kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I’m, interested to see how it saves time and money over time. I think they’re the two things that I wanna see from this, how quick is it to. Get up and running, how quick is it to create a page? How quick is it to, I don’t know, implement some of the designs like the bento one that you did recently?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How quick is it to inject those into it? and I’m fascinated by the cost implications. ’cause I imagine with this, the cost is for a typical, I don’t know, Brochure website for somebody living in a town, you know where there’s gonna be thousands of views a year, not millions of views a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m interested to see how close to free it is. ’cause I’m imagining it will approximate very close to free at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:33:55] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, you, that’s what we’re doing at the moment, while we just do it with the basic web platform and no. Third party platform at all for this site. we check it out, we get our free hosting and I’m sure there’ll always be some free hosting for the sort of visits Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That we get. The amount of traffic that we get. Yep. So really all this is building on the Y 11 to fits. It is because we can add in something to take, to remove some of the chore of having to update things that would. Come with WordPress out of the box. Yeah. there’s no doubt about it. If I was, taken on a job that, had a big, large content site and it needed multi authors and it was at my skill level, there’s no doubt it would be WordPress That would be the choice for this sort of thing if I had to do this job, because there’s no way that I would be linking all of this stuff up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:34:45] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; To give them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:34:46] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; the UI that they needed. Yeah. yeah. so that would be the obvious choice. But when it comes to this, where. Effectively, it’s only you or I might have to update the content here. obviously the benefits of static is once you stick it up there, unless you mess with it, it’s gonna live on forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where you put, like on a dynamic platform, someone else can mess up your website for You and you have to update, don’t you? Because you know you have to. Yeah. security&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:16] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; patches, things like that. Yeah. It’s interesting. I’ll tell you what, it’s gonna be fascinating. I, you are gonna, you’re gonna ring WordPress out of my cold, dead hands, but, but nevertheless, it’s a fascinating ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, I’m here to watch it all happen,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:32] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:32] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Shall we, shall we do next time,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:35] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; shall we?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:36] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, you could highlight what you think is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:38] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; gonna happen next time. Yeah. Okay. I think maybe we will try and we’ll take one of those, old sites. I’m not sure which ones. One of the, and I’ll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try and put some eleventy in it with my basic skills of what I know about it so far, so you can see it in action. I think we can probably do that as an audio as well, because Oh yeah, if I just explain Yeah. The process, I think it will make sense, but, we’ll definitely need YouTube so you can see what I’m doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So perhaps we’ll give that a bash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:05] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, that sounds good to me. you’ll be able to check this out, at the No Script Show website. It’s no script show slash 15 ’cause that is the episode that we’re on. You’ll be able to find the show notes that we’re showing on the screen, but if you’re listening to it, on the audio, then there are some show notes there that you can click links on if any of the bits and pieces have raised your.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Levels of curiosity, about 11 or indeed WordPress. So shall we call it a day? Is that a wrap? Yeah, I think so. Alright. See you. I’ll see you next time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:37] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:37] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; thanks. Bye bye. Bye-bye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt; &lt;/details&gt;&lt;/details&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Easier web design and coding with Bento Grids</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/5/" />
    <updated>2024-11-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/5/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Redesigning a Bistro/café site. Part 2. Coding with HTML and CSS</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/4/" />
    <updated>2024-10-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/4/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Redesigning a Bistro site. Part 1. The Design.</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/3/" />
    <updated>2024-10-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/3/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Redesigning a vets site. Part 2. Coding with CSS and Testing</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/2/" />
    <updated>2024-10-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/2/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Redesigning a vets site. Part 1. UX Design and Planning</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/build/1/" />
    <updated>2024-10-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/build/1/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Coming.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Frontend Divide:- UX Designers vs JavaScript Specialists</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/14/" />
    <updated>2024-07-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/14/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are revisiting a 5 year old debate summed up in Chris Coyier&#39;s 2019 CSS Tricks article called &lt;a href=&quot;https://css-tricks.com/the-great-divide/&quot;&gt;the Great Divide&lt;/a&gt; and looking at what has changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-behind-the-great-divide&quot;&gt;What&#39;s behind the &amp;quot;Great Divide&amp;quot;?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A worry:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Over &amp;quot;gatekeeping&amp;quot; and gender bias. If you have to be a programmer &lt;a href=&quot;https://rachelandrew.co.uk/archives/2019/01/30/html-css-and-our-vanishing-industry-entry-points/&quot;&gt;accessible routes to web development narrow.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That web standards will fall?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That code complexity is a cost to the environment and users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-does-the-divide-exist&quot;&gt;Why does the divide exist?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;HTML and CSS not meeting the (perceived) component based design needs of the time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSS not seen as easy to scope for large scale team project work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Browsers not being trusted. Better to use JS to tell them what to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Marketing (although Meta and Google seem to have lost interest in their React and Angular offerings).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The amazing real time user interaction JavaScript brought.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CSS frustrates many. Mostly through not learning it, understanding its declarative nature and impatience. &lt;strong&gt;Rachel Andrew wrote:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;CSS is simultaneously too easy to bother with, yet so hard it needs to be wrapped up in a ball of JavaScript in case it scares the horses&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-it-getting-smaller&quot;&gt;Is it getting smaller?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CSS is being rapidly refactored - removing common dependencies on JS (including &lt;a href=&quot;https://astro-zerojs-transitions.vercel.app/&quot;&gt;interactive ones&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Browsers working together to speed up progress.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web components offering a standards based interoperable alternative to 3rd party JS components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;JS fatigue. Maintaining a complex set of dependencies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Cascade is back with &lt;code&gt;@layer. @scope and :where()&lt;/code&gt; A move to doing more with less code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;WebAssembly (WASM) - a new web standard with more power than JS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User demands:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For web content on their terms. Increasingly removing our visual designs and expecting content on any type of device.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frustration with CSS often came from mimicking print.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The need to deliver fast, green, valid and accessible HTML content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://noscript.show/img/divided.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-wordpress-divide&quot;&gt;The WordPress divide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For those who use a WYSIWYG builder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More recently, those who develop themes as WordPress moves from PHP themes to JS block themes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://rachelandrew.co.uk/archives/2019/01/30/html-css-and-our-vanishing-industry-entry-points/&quot;&gt;Rachel Andrew: HTML, CSS and our vanishing industry entry points&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://heydonworks.com/article/reluctant-gatekeeping:-the-problem-with-full-stack/&quot;&gt;Heydon Pickering: Reluctant Gatekeeping: The Problem With Full Stack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://chriscoyier.net/2023/02/16/noodling-on-wordpress-in-2023/&quot;&gt;Chris Coyier: Noodling on WordPress in 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What is the W3C doing about AI?</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/13/" />
    <updated>2024-06-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/13/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-w3c-report&quot;&gt;The W3C Report&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s written as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/reports/ai-web-impact/&quot;&gt;academic paper&lt;/a&gt; and there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OwLRtquaLOk&quot;&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt; on the W3C&#39;s YouTube channel. It&#39;s an open document that is first seeking community feedback via Github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may lead to in-depth stakeholder interviews, W3C workshops and developing a standardisation roadmap. It&#39;s looking at:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ethical-and-societal-impacts&quot;&gt;Ethical and Societal Impacts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transparency (data usage).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privacy (protecting personal data).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security (impersonation concerns).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sustainability (the environmental impact).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Balancing interests (fairness to content creators and consumers).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;technical-impacts-and-standardization-proposals&quot;&gt;Technical Impacts and Standardization Proposals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Consent mechanisms for Web content in AI training.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Development of personal data stores for data control.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Labelling AI-generated content to combat misinformation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exposing model-backed Web APIs while maintaining interoperability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Evaluating the environmental impact of AI systems on the Web.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some interesting contributions on Github already. Some are questioning the threat AI poses to the Web. It does not link in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accessibility is another. Jacob Nielsen The &amp;quot;king of usability&amp;quot; thinks usability has failed and &lt;a href=&quot;https://jakobnielsenphd.substack.com/p/accessibility-generative-ui&quot;&gt;Generative AI could do the job.&lt;/a&gt; Do we need alt tags and aria labels? Or language translation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tim-bernards-lee-ai-predictions&quot;&gt;Tim Bernards-Lee AI predictions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He think it will transform the way we interact with the web&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One day we&#39;ll have AI assistants that work for us — similar to our doctors, lawyers, and bankers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The breakup of big tech.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;His passion is for a web where users own their own data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;links&quot;&gt;Links&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2024/03/12/world-wide-web-turns-35-tim-berners-lee-gives-predictions-for-future.html&quot;&gt;Tim Berners-Lee&#39;s AI predictions on CNBC.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@timberners_lee/marking-the-webs-35th-birthday-an-open-letter-ebb410cc7d42&quot;&gt;Tim Berners-Lee&#39;s the Web&#39;s 35th Birthday: An Open Letter.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Transcript&lt;/summary&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:05] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Welcome to the No Script show about modern web design, where we look at what we can build today with minimal software and skills. Today we’re talking about AI from the perspective of the W three C or the Worldwide Web Consortium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Helping us with this is a new report from the W three C team called AI and the Web, understanding and Managing the impact of Machine Learning Models on the Web. Additionally, we have Tim Burners Lee AI predictions thanks to some recent comments when celebrating 35 years on the web. So David, this is a topic we both enjoy debating, so it’ll be interesting to see how our positions on AI have advanced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that, over to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:47] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, well have, we’ve been talking for about two hours before this. yes. We just couldn’t, yeah. Yeah. So we caught up on that. So we’ll try and stick, I think, as best as we can to what the W three C are saying because we can go off on so many tangents. And I think there’ll be other subjects here, won’t they?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll give you my quick summary and I am in the position where I think I was excited about it and I still am. But I’ve never really bought into the fact that it’s something creative, going to threaten any creative job that I might do. I quite like how the large language machines are helping me to do some really tedious tasks these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I do think it’s quite interesting ’cause it feels a little bit like we’ve moved away from that and initial hype where we are more panicked about it and we’re seeing more. Of the kind of news where companies are feeling forced a little bit to exaggerate what you can do. We’re seeing more about how it might be so much more costly to make it advance in the way that we expect it to advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yeah, so it’s quite interesting since the last time we spoke about there was more sort of panic over it, where it feels a bit more relaxed now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:01:57] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; I, flip flop on this subject. I go from a deep admiration of AI and the things that it can do to blind panic, like chicken little, the sky is falling in. And I, really do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, I think, the reason is because in some areas where I honestly thought, computers, let’s call it that computers could never encroach. So the creation of artwork or the creation of songs, that kind of thing. I really did think five years ago that wouldn’t be an impossibility. There was something about the human brain, which was unique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then more recently when things. Which you could call art and things, which we could call music came along. It really did start to make me think, gosh, okay, this is, this is a worry. And I think the worry for me is that we’re gonna gouge out the bottom rung of the ladder. If you imagine a ladder, a career ladder if you like, and, you need people to get on the first step of the ladder in order to then progress to other things as their career goes on and what have you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it feels like AI has the potential to just knock out the first. Bottom two steps of the ladder because it can approximate, a, decent song, it can approximate a decent logo or whatever it might be. And so I worry that the people who might have had those jobs and therefore gained experience, they’re gonna somehow have to get above what the AI can do to be useful in a career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so that worries me. But then equally, I think over the last year, I’m feeling this sense of plateau in what the ais can do. it doesn’t really seem like what it could do a year ago. Is that different from what it can do now? And I expected that would be logarithmic. It would just improve at a greater rate, whereas it seems to have plateaued.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the other thing is with technology since let’s say the turn of the millennium, so 2000, you didn’t really know what the intention was. You didn’t really have a roadmap in your head of what the internet ought to be like. It just evolved. Where whereas with ai, you can perceive what that is and that is a replacement of humans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you can get an ai, AI to create a perfect film, a perfect song. you know what that is already. Whereas the internet, I don’t know what that is. I never knew what it was gonna be. So anyway, so I think on balance, I’m more sanguine about it. and certainly every time I’ve used AI for the tiny little corner of the, the AI possibilities that I use it for, I’ve been profoundly impressed by what it can do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and I have this notion in my head, which is probably self-deception in a way, because I would’ve been doing all of that work myself, and I’m not therefore doing somebody out of work. I’m just saving myself some time. I. I feel that’s a decent trade off, but obviously if that were played out across the whole world, that might not be quite such a, good endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, sorry that was a complete rant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:05:07] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, no, it’s fine. actually there’s just, you made me think of something we didn’t even talk about before, but I think, when it might cut out that bottom layer, the fundamentals. That funny enough is where I think it fails because I think, where it’s pretty rubbish at doing stuff is like things like marking out some HML, which might be appropriate to the context it needs to be, or it’s terrible with CSS I’ve found, and I think, sometimes when it might take some of the chore out things that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;absolutely known, I used it for WordPress. Really impressive because if you like the PHP commands that you might use, the old ones for traditional WordPress are so set that there’s not much variation. So ask it to do something which I couldn’t do. It could do the code, which I couldn’t do, but I know it’s going to be correct, because there’s only so many outputs where I think, sometimes the fundamental structuring of a website or.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it just doesn’t do it. And it’s same because it’s always looking backwards on its stuff. CSS has evolved particularly so it doesn’t know the new stuff and it looks back to the majority of the old stuff, which is not the best way to do it. So, I find actually in some ways it’s, I’m going back to the basics of the very early web and trying to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get to understand things, which I thought I knew, but don’t. HDML and CSS particularly as it’s changing and I think it’s so bad at those things that, yeah, it, you know, I have to guide it on the fundamentals. So I, that is my worry actually with AI is that sometimes it can be used to fill in what you think is a good example for me is AI with, I was talking about this, I did a short video AI with, ALT tags for images seems to be a new thing to do that. And you think, yeah, that’s great. But if you think about it for one second, the last thing a blind person wants is, all this wonderful prose on what this image looks like. They want to know what a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:04] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; game changing, whatever. Yeah, just over superlative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:09] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, but you remind me the whole No, what I’m saying is that, if you really describe a full image as a I Oh, I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:16] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; see. Yes. It won’t know when how to truncate itself or, yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:20] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; exactly. Actually what that image is doing, it wants to know what that image is doing, what parts of that image are. Are meaningful to the context in which it’s set right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the rest is all superfluous. Yeah. So do you see what I mean? I can see where, it’s these lower level things, some of these other jobs where I think you actually have to be a human being because you’re providing for other human beings anyway. Yeah. We’ve, no,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:42] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; no, but that’s interesting. And I, do wonder, I wonder particularly in the, with the example of CSS, because the CSS isn’t the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is what the CSS. Does, which is visual. Yes. I wonder if, that, if the, AI at the moment, these large language models, I wonder if they can make the connection, okay, here’s some code. But what does that actually end up looking is the point, and it might not be able to make bridge that gap, if Yeah. So maybe it’s, maybe that’s, I don’t know. I’m entirely ignorant of whether that’s even a thing,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:15] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; but Yeah. And for speed, I want it to be fast and in the context of the whole site, and it just can’t do it, and I just avoid it because, it just starts hallucinating as. AI does when I start, it doesn’t know stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It thinks it does, and, it, I love sending it off for down its hallucinations where it believes it’s right and it’s completely wrong, and then like to enjoy watching. But, other stuff, it’s great when, when I think when you are making the creative decisions, treating it as a. A dumb assistant I think is wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should we bring up the notes? Because honestly we’ll just go on. Yeah, I will do that completely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:51] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; One moment. Here we go. This is the note. if you are listening to this. Let me get the number right. ’cause in the past I’ve got the numbers of the episodes wrong. So we’re on episode number 13 1 3. And so if you go to no script show slash 13 1 3, you’ll be able to find these show notes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have, I’ve got the episode right for a start. Yes. You have lucky for everyone. Yeah. Okay, great. So here we are. What, where should we launch first? Yeah, this W three C report.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:09:20] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I just thought this was a good chance ’cause it’s, recently out and it’s, obviously it, the title doesn’t really beg it to be read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s an academic paper. And, there is a presentation. I’ve got a link on the show notes, which goes to the YouTube, channel there. But the guy behind that, it’s maybe not, he’s, French, so if, if you can tune into his accent, you might find it quite interesting as a quick sort of summary of what they’re trying to do with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But my understanding is. it comes from the W three. See team, is that what they call themselves? Yeah. Yeah. And it’s, that’s really the, they’ve got about, I think 46 employees in that team. And, this is really just a first document out there, which might later form standards. So the idea is that they put this out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment it’s public, so it welcomes feedback. So it’s out on GitHub, so you can, if you think this report is missing something they should be looking into, you can add to it. And we’ll talk about that, but, We’ve got a summary. Do you wanna just run through these, Nathan? We’ve got, I’ve tried to divide it up what the report is saying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:10:32] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Okay. just to read what’s on the screen, really, ethical and societal. Societal is hard to say. Impacts, are transparency, data usage. These, some of them have got little parentheses at the end, privacy, which is protecting personal data security, impersonation concerns. Sustainability, the environmental side of sustainability, balancing interests, and that really refers to the fairness to the content creators and the consumers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’m sure that if you ponder each of those for just a moment, you can see in a real world example of where AI might be able to abuse. Any of those individual bits, obviously sustainability. If we all rely on AI for everything, we’re gonna be burning through carbon at an incredibly quick rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Balancing interests do content creators, who, owns what if the LLMs are allowed to sock up all of the data without giving credit back, and, they appear to be the origin. Of that particular piece of content, whereas in fact it was written by somebody, I don’t know, 10 years ago or what have you, and each of them, just ponder it for a moment and you’ll be able to figure out how that might be of concern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:11:47] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. And then I think the next, because it’s sectioned up and the next thing is really addressing those ’cause it’s the technical impact and standardization proposal. So obviously what the W three C as a standards organization for the web, it likes to ultimately come up with some standards, which we all agree to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it’s really addressing all of the next ones with, a sort of consent mechanism for AI content. In AI training development of personal data stores for data control, labeling of AI generated content to combat misinformation exposure, sorry, exposing model. Backed web IPAs while maintaining interoperability and evaluating the environmental impact of AI systems on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:12:34] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Can I just say the, I do like the idea of a web, IPA, which is what you’ve actually said. A, web-based Indian pale ale. That would be, really nice. I think you meant to say API, but I prefer I did. I prefer what you said. Can I just say though, just getting back before you put this document together?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. I didn’t really know anything about this at all, and I honestly didn’t think this was any concern. I. Of the W three CI, I couldn’t in my head, have imagine, why do they, wanna get involved with this? and then of course when you put this together and I started thinking about it, really, somebody’s got to be thinking about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s really where it comes down because it has to be some sort of more global approach, an approach where big business doesn’t get its tendrils where government doesn’t necessarily get its tendrils. And All of a sudden the penny dropped. And I thought, actually, yeah, this is brilliant. We do need people who are detached from it all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;they have no economic motive, no political motive, whatever it may be. it’s brilliant that they’re thinking about this and, they seem like fairly sensible defaults starting positions. Yeah. yeah. Anyway, sorry. You carry on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:13:50] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; No, I, had the same thought as well. It’s trying to understand what the W three C has, and I think it does have a unique power when we’ve talked about before with, the working groups, particularly with CSS, how, within those working groups, it’s bringing to the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big tech. It’s bringing Microsoft, apple, Google, Adobe to agree what they think the web should look like, these standards. So it’s obviously the best body given that AI pretty much appears through the web. What other organization could get everybody around the table? And you can see we were talking about this a little bit earlier about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How there might be a benefit to say Google because its main business is through its advertising, through its search. particularly that’s its main business. One of its biggest worries and one of the things they’re tackling here is how do we mark up on the web stuff so people know it’s AI generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, Google want that more than anything for their own business, as well as being on the side of. Supplying AI as well. They also want to control that for that aspect of their business. So there’s a good reason for everybody to try and agree things, I think, to some standards. So where is expected?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;VER developers, who when we’re putting sites together that we declare our. AI content, you know?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:15:11] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. I think it’s gonna be really difficult for the W three C to have teeth in this, in that it’ll be easier for them to just create some recommendations, which we, we would hope people would follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But maybe this will be one of those situations. So for example, at the moment. It does appear that accessibility. So nothing to do with AI for a moment, just accessibility is gaining teeth because politicians around the world are, putting laws together, which say, look, unless you do this, you are gonna feel the, strong arm of the law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if your website is not accessible in these certain ways. And here’s the guide, here’s the guidance for how that should look. but now we’re gonna give it teeth. And that’s coming around in next year in the eu. Maybe this sort of stuff over time will need that approach as well, because you can imagine it’ll be easy to just ignore any of those points and just say, yeah, nice idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But my country, the jurisdiction that I live in, doesn’t compel me to do it, so I’m not gonna do it. Yeah, I’m gonna steal that content and claim it as my own. Who cares? so we’ll see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:16:18] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, the idea of this report is that it does, it is the first stage in it, so right at the moment it’s out there as a, partly written document where people can add in their views and things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That should be, and there’s a couple of ’em will come onto that minute, so this, but then they’ll move on to stakeholder interviews, which I guess we’ll be talking to the likes of Google. Yeah. Microsoft and what they’re doing on that, and then it’ll move into the. W three C workshops in the way that they might go about standardizing anything like CSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Yeah. But I think, surely it should be welcomed by, when you think that you might have Microsoft competing with Google over, I’m sure everybody wants this to be a success in, The end. So if everybody can agree some standards of which they will work to on the web, then it’s to the benefit of everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I think that’s where they are unique. But yeah, it does seem a little odd to me. when, ’cause most of our news about AI is not really, you think of it as a separate endeavor and one which potentially. And that’s another argument of it could remove the need for the web entirely,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:17:28] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. You’re imagining a scenario where you’ve just got this little pocket assistant or something, and a lot of the things that you’re doing on the web, you’ve now consigned to this ai, which is sitting in a device in your pocket or something like that. And you don’t need to browse webpages because I don’t know, you just.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask it a question and it provides you with an answer. Yeah. It undermines what the internet has become. Yeah. This is, honestly, this is so interesting. I with those ethical and societal impacts, I’m, I can’t think of anything that they’ve missed, but I’m sure that you’re right. As the days, weeks, and months go on, I’m sure there’ll be other things thrown in there, but at the moment we do seem to be in a cycle of hype, and I’m seeing it more like that as a cycle a.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fulfilling prophecy, if you like, where one AI company promises a thing. And so the other AI companies have to over promise because of that promise. And then, the original one then has to over promise. And we do seem to be in an ear at the moment and you only have to watch the tech conferences, Google’s io and things like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And they portray AI being this entirely benign. Perfect force where you, are, you show it a thing and it tells you what it is, and you ask it a question and it gives you the right answer. And, it does really seem the hype cycle that we might have had for things like crypto or NFTs a little while ago, and, maybe give it a year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That cycle will just, people will realize. You know what? It can’t do everything for me, but&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:01] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; yeah, I mean there’s certainly, that’s cynical. We’ve been watching some videos that have come out, by, business people who will just say this whole AI thing is exactly like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s another thing. It was big data before that. It’s been, wearables, it’s been Bitcoin, it’s been, and this is just another, Raising funds. Silicon Valley hype hoax if you like. and certainly I think people have been caught into, as we know with Google, it cheated, and got found out for showing some of its demonstrations of what its AI can do where, it’s supposed to be able to identify certain shapes and tell you exactly where it was, where it needed human intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we had a big thing with Amazon as well, where they claim it was a success, but it needed all of these. operatives in India creating the, it was a checkout for their store where they didn’t need to go and purchase anything but cameras with, real people were doing it. And now they claim the a l was a success, but they still closed it down and they still removed a lot of their documentation before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I think there’s a certain element where I’m sure none of these companies wanting to get into this kind of, almost having to get into lives if you like to compete. Yeah. Somebody starts it with an exaggeration, somebody else has to beat it because we’re in competition and they get stuck in it, really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:20:22] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; I think one could, one could gently call it overpromising,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:20:26] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; overpromising is probably a better thing. Yeah. But I don’t think it’s, it’s probably not where any of these companies want to be. It’s just the way, that’s just the way I. Capitalism works, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So everybody, you have to try and get the best competitive advantage. So I would imagine, the WCC has that ability in the past to agree, and I think we’ve only just seen that with a web where everybody agrees. Yes, the web, we want a standard set of code and we all want to agree what that one is, and we all want to make the web work on everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I, I can see how it can be a good place. For AI to be there. Yeah. But there is an argument, sorry, I wanted to just say something on that is I think it’s alluded to in somebody’s GitHub, addition to this, and I think it was that you could say it’s a threat to the web itself in the sense that, and I’ve seen other people talk about this, so if you say, for example, PDFs, they’re very difficult because they’re not web right to make accessible and you have to put all this embedded stuff in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What they’re saying these days is that. large language machines can read that stuff and work out how the content is. So that work might not need to be done in a way. And we see that a little bit, I think with a lot of SEOs saying about Google, how when we were in the age of the big data mark, everything up with schema.org or rich snippets that they called, it was the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s break it up. But a lot of SEOs are saying, and it’s true of Google. They seem to be dropping the support for a lot of these things. Partly because it might be over abused, but I think it’s partly because they don’t need it so much because the machines can work out the content areas of sites based on Oh, I see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their knowledge. Okay. So, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some, yeah, some, things which, so you can get into that argument where you’re saying, a lot of the fundamentals of the webs, which we agreed to, do we need them in the same way? Do we need, old tags any longer? if they’re being read in a different way with AI and.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;do we need aria labels and stuff? If screen readers can detect themselves, with new technology, what a page markup is, yeah, it’s quite interesting. There is a, potential for some of the web to be undermined. with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:22:45] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; I was gonna say something there, but I’ll wait because it is what we’re gonna come onto, but it was about the capacity of AI to actually.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get all of that stuff right. the dom and what have you. So shall I just scroll up a little bit more and, We’ll go onto the next little bit. okay. So we’re onto Jacob Nielsen, did you wanna mention him?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:23:09] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, was just somebody else made the point that, in that report isn’t talking about accessibility and Jacob Nielsen, the king of usability is called Think he wrote an article, and I’ve linked to it there, that usability has failed. People don’t use their RRE labels correctly, don’t mark their HTML up in the way that screen readers can easily read them. And that generative AI could start to do that job, which is really the point I’m making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:23:36] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. Yeah, that was the point I was gonna make as well. And, I think, that kind of makes sense. Wouldn’t this be an area where AI would be. Very good because it’s got a very defined outcome, Ha. Has it been marked up correctly for a screen reader, ignoring the fact that in the future screen readers might operate in a different way for the screen readers that we’ve got today?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Would AI be potentially quite good at this? Because it could see, I don’t know. This is a paragraph, this is a heading that is as heading, nested within another heading. Let’s give that an H two and that an H three and whatever else we might add to the HTML, the markup. It feels like that would be an area where you could just maybe click a button and it would do a.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better job than you not doing it at all, if&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:24:22] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, and I think that’s, I, see Jacob Nielson’s point and I see he’s had some pushback by a lot of people, disabled people actually. and I understand that pushback, and I think this is where, I don’t think that’s the right thinking because I think you do need people to markup because you need another human.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marking this up to make sense to human. admittedly, it’s better than nothing, but I don’t think it’ll get rid of the idea that marking up. documents with HTML properly, with a concentration on accessibility. And I think in some ways it’s, skipping the point as you raised the fact that next year we’ve got a European law, which is requiring many of us to do our websites in a more accessible way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yes, it’s right in the fact that it’s failed, but then there’s been nobody policing this. And I think we’re seeing more policing of it. And I think human beings marking up documents rather than letting. AI do it is better because they will mark it up with the context of how it’s expected to be explained in the same way that I said about alt text as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;there’s no point in describing the whole flipping thing. It’s really how that image relates. does it relate at all? If not, it needs a blank and don’t read it out to people who don’t need to know it. Yeah. it’s just decorative and I don’t think AI can then distinguish that kind of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In situ,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:25:43] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; so it, the AI might be better than doing nothing at all. But it’s probably not gonna be as good as doing something with humans, if I think that’s a sensible default position. Yeah. if your organization is gonna do something, it would appear that just clicking a button and praying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That the AI didn’t hallucinate its way into just nonsense is probably not gonna get you out of legal woes in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Okay. Okay. And then we’ve got Tim burners Lee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:26:15] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. So he’s been, because he’s been the 35th anniversary of the web. Yeah. Gosh. I know it’s getting old. yeah. so yeah, he’s made a, it’s, there’s a couple of things and I’ve linked to them on the bottom of this and maybe I’ll add some more links in ’cause we referenced some things as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, yeah, so he’s done an open letter. About the web, which talks about that. But also there’s another article which is, by CNBC, where they’re going to some of his predictions and included in that is, is AI or as I’m seeing on my notes, it says A one. Yeah, A road in the uk there’s gonna be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;yeah. So the big takeaways from this I’ve added to that was the fact that he thinks it’s gonna transform the way we interact with the web. And Google interestingly have been like that as well recently saying, let you know, let Google do the Googling for you. I. This is new take on what we expect the deal to be with Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But yeah, he’s saying that’ll transform how we inter interact and he sees I’m not so optimistic as him that we’ll all have AI assistance do work for, similar to how our doctors, lawyers, or bankers do. So. he’s very optimistic, isn’t he? About AI more so than me and you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:27:38] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; What, do, you know what, that almost to me sounds like a bit of a dystopia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;there’s a film that I watch and it’s got nothing to do with this, but there was a film that I watched recently where, and it was a dystopian future film, but there was a bit where, the, protagonist, the character in the film went up and talked to a robot to get his prescription. And, there was an actual robot, which, it had a flat lights flashing on the mouth, but no other moving parts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, it was just this, horrific conversation of, I’m owed this thing, can I have it? we don’t seem to have this for, really robotic voice. Anyway, back and forth, and just nothing but frustration. And I, that concerns me, that piece because that seems to undermine the humanity of a lot of things and that bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That be okay. Maybe that’s where we’ll go. But it, I fear that’s where we’re gonna go. It, that doesn’t seem like a, good incentive for humanity particularly, but&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:28:39] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; No, a lot of, services we have is because of that personal connection with people, it. Almost acting like counseling as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a lot of people grieve over the loss of that human connection, their trans actions. So yeah, I think he’s a little bit more optimistic, than I would be. He does also, and it’s related, it’s not under his AI predictions, but he is, predicting as he wrote in his open ledger as well about breakup of big tech as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He sees that happening and I. this is the problem, isn’t it? We are in an advanced capitalist world and we are seeing that, money is going to, concentrated in certain areas. We have big tech, they have an awful lot of power, and we are seeing, To getting to the point where we have to see the US government will be taking a lawsuit out against Apple to make sure this competition there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve got something new that’s just passed, doesn’t it, for the EU as well, which gives more control over big tech so it doesn’t abuse its position. So I do think there may be a need to Yeah, you, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:44] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; And also interestingly, it is largely. Big tech. Which is pushing this agenda of what AI can do. there, there’s no like tin pot, little cottage industry mom and pop AI out there, which is, a good rival to something like open AI or Gemini or whatever it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big tech who are, and we mentioned it a moment ago, this self-fulfilling prophecy where they’ve got to overpromise because the other one’s overpromising and it’s the big tech doing it, and they’ve got a really big stage. And honestly, they could fill those, they could fill those presentations with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Utter lies. And I think at the moment we just lap it all up because, oh, look, it can do that. That’s exciting. yeah, so I, yeah, I, think you’re right. It does appear like the legislators around the world are, have got the, sword of Damocles definitely above the heads of these big tech companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we’ll see how that plays out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:30:36] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yes. Governments having to take a part in this just to see that. Yeah. They don’t have too much power. And, we were talking about, how interesting it is with. Gen Z seeing things very different. Being a kind of first generation that doesn’t have job security and housing insecurity, that they are slightly cynical where, big companies where money’s going on that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So they change their behavior with big tech. They see in a way what’s going on, where, who has all the power with that. So I think that’s changing things on the ground. I do think, with Tim Burnley and he always sticks to this ’cause it’s partly as well, I think a business that is running is big on everything where this has to be set in the context of the fact that is ideal Web is one where the users own their own data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:22] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. Yeah. I’m a. A big proponent of that. But it’d be interesting because it would appear that some of the big tech companies, particularly Apple, it would appear that they’re moving in that direction. In that they’re it feels that although they have just. Been in chat with open AI apparently, so we’ll see if this breaks out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, is that the, AI will be done on your device, these M four chips that are coming down the pipe will be really good at doing everything on your own device. So as whereas at the moment you’re used to going to open AI or Gemini, and that’s an online. Portal, you type your things in and whether you’re using the API or the web interface, you get a result through the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It, feels like the future is gonna be doing that on your own device. So you own it and it never goes anywhere else. So maybe, Apple will justify not being broken up on that ground. I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:17] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, you mentioned something about there’s no, mom and pop, AI business there. It, we both watched a video, which we liked in a way, but, it was, it was on YouTube and it’s guy called Mike Pound and it’s on, it’s channel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll put the link in ’cause I haven’t got it there. Okay. computer file. And this was the one, if you remember, Nathan, where he was looking at some of the scientific report. And we’re, always talking about the massive advance. Yeah. In AI and what it can do within a whole year, but all their reports or what he was looking at, we have to trust him that his reports are there, but he seemed to be sound man talking, saying that progress will slow down because the costs of getting the quality, because it’s so easy to gather a load of data and that not to be that great, which it means everything’s always looking back, but like I say, it’s rubbish with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CSS because there’s so little data about modern CSS and everything’s old. So to correct it you need so much more data to keep throwing at it, that the costs become too much, in terms of the businesses too advance, it becomes too much. To invest in it, to be able to get the improvements back. And then that’s the other debate, which we’ve heard a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. I, you mentioned it on, your new show, about the environmental cost of AI with all of that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:33:36] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Oh boy, that’s just terrific. Yeah, I think, if you think. Googling things is bad if you, AI things, if you request an answer from an ai, you really are burning through the carbon much more quickly than just going onto a variety of websites and finding it out for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, it’s a lot quicker, but every time you create an AI image or an AI song, or do an AI search. My understanding is that, from journalists that I think have credibility that it’s, burning through CO2, a really alarming rate and something which really shouldn’t be sustainable. so yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. That’s interesting. I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:34:18] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, it does seem like there’s a little bit of a or a weariness now that this will actually pan out. like all the things, as mentioned before, the kind of Silicon Valley stuff, that’s the big thing that’s gonna make money. there’s a lot of other people as well saying, this potentially could be another.com.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bust,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:34:34] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. if it doesn’t continue to get better at an exponential rate, we’ll quickly grow tired of it. ’cause that’s the human condition, isn’t it? Yeah. And the YouTube video, which you are gonna link to but isn’t on the screen at the moment, it ha I think you did a really credible job of explaining that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, rather than the graph going upwards, it, went up for a long time because the LLM suddenly enabled things, which were not possible. And so it looked like. It was being creative and it looked like it was human almost, and it looked like it was passing the Turing test, but his, argument was that, okay, you had to consume all the data to get to that point, and then to make it twice as good as it is now is not just about putting double the amount of data in you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’re like a thousand times the amount of data. To get a teeny tiny improvement. So you put another billion point data points in and you get N point, N 0.1 of a percent improvement. You gotta add another 10 billion. And where does it all come from? yeah, and if we end up filling it in with AI data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, we’re in trouble. But it, made me more sanguine about it, it’s leveling off and potentially it won’t get any better. Obviously, we’re recording this in June, 2024 when the robots have taken over in August, 2025. we’ll have to revise this podcast,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:54] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I do think, but it takes us full circle with all the things we’re talking, which, I think when we look at the ethical and societal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impact and, the things that they’re trying to standardize. It touches on all of these things, the sort of data usage, what data you are using over this. if everybody’s agreed to certain things, we’ll have proper competition rather than, do you know what I mean? Yeah. There’ll be more honesty with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, I think also, something that’s not being resolved yet is the. the content creators, it’s stealing all of their work and, I think some people have done some experiments with, because it’s such a small data set, if you get into something very niche and you ask ai, it, it will almost duplicate what sort of Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:37] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; More or less you are robbing quite literally the exact Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:41] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah. Yeah, and some people have done some experiments where they’ve done it on something so niche or E even tested it by putting up wrong information on the web so the AI comes back with the wrong information that is on the web because it’s the only source, but it almost entirely rips off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole article that serves it back. So I think, when it comes to standardizing some of this stuff, when it starts to look into, the fairness of to content creators in some standards, and it looks to, I. the kind of data usage and it looks to what’s sustainable as well. I really hope that AI do get round the table around this, kind of things to create standards because I, it’s not in their interest, I don’t think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think AI’s promising. I think it can help us to do a lot of jobs and we both use it and love. Some of the things it can do for us,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:37:32] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; but it’s interesting though, but it, okay. So all of these organizations are made up of humans and Yeah, it is in their interest to not do this in the short term because there, there’s gonna be billionaires made there next year, and then they can just swan off and do whatever else they want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for the long term interest, if open AI and Google want to have an a, an AI future. That spans decades then, there is an interest. But I think one of the things that I’m concerned about at the moment is the self-interest. Yeah. Of a few people at the top of these companies who are, making money, like they’re printing it and it is in their interest to just do the nefarious stuff, to over promise to all of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, we, don’t seem to have a way of. Reigning those people in at the moment. That could be a very naive position. Maybe they’re full of, good intentions and I’m probably, I’m labeling them incorrectly, but it feels a bit like that sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:38:36] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; No, of course. And it’s gonna happen. And I, for me, I think why I think this is good organization and I hope it does succeeded with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;’cause I think, yeah. We talked about another success before when you think the web could have been lost to flash. Proprietary technology, Yeah. That could have easily, and a lot of people believed in it. It would be in the self-interest, but somehow it managed to preserve, and I think there’s never been a time where.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest giants in tech I’ve got behind something like the W three C. So we see the security of this web project, and I don’t, I was saying about before, could it replace the web? I don’t think it will because it takes so long anyway for people to adopt new technology and it’s more effective the one that we’ve got and everybody is behind that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;yeah. They’re setting up of these. So I think it would be a good thing. And even if there is a lone wolf out there who, perhaps wants to exaggerate for their personal quick gain or something. ’cause that’s the danger, isn’t it? With everything. Somebody tells a lie to exaggerate something, they do really well out of that lie because people believe it and they get lots of money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the next, the only way you can compete it is with another lie and on it goes and everybody goes. Please. I wish we’d stop with this lying, and I think that’s right. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:39:46] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Oh, dear. I mean we’ve definitely, we’ve definitely solved that problem for everybody, haven’t we? Yeah, They’ve solved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everybody. I,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:39:55] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; I think it’s interesting anyway, and, just hardly going to get any attention, the fact that there is this document out there and I think, I think it’d be interesting to see how that develops and whether we get, yeah. AI standards coming from the W three C, I think that would be a fabulous thing if it could be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:40:13] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley:&lt;/strong&gt; Perfect. I’ve taken the show notes away. so that was episode 13. That was our thoughts on, AI and the W three C’s approach to it. the show notes as always, no script show slash the episode number in this case. 13. Go and check ’em out there and, you two will be able to see Tim Burn’s Lee’s predictions as to what will happen to the A one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I doubt it. I’m sure David will go and change that in a hurry, but that was lovely. Thank you David. Thanks. I’ll speak to you soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:40:44] &lt;strong&gt;David Waumsley:&lt;/strong&gt; Yeah, cheers. Bye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How web typography has evolved</title>
    <link href="https://noscript.show/12/" />
    <updated>2024-06-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://noscript.show/12/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;style&gt;

       
        .text-effect  {   
            margin-top: 0;     
            margin-bottom: 1rem;       
            font-size: 7rem;               
            display: block;
            font-weight: 900;
            background:url(&quot;/img/typography-title.webp&quot;) center;
            background-size:cover;
            background-clip:text;
            -webkit-background-clip: text;   
            color: transparent;
            filter: drop-shadow(0.2rem 0.2rem  black) ;
        }
        
    h1 small{
    
      font-size: var(--step-1);
      font-weight: 400;
      font-style: italic;
    }
    .columns{
    columns: 18rem auto;
    column-gap: var(--size-l)
    }
    
    .columns::first-letter{
      font-family: Georgia, &#39;Times New Roman&#39;, Times, serif;
      border: .2rem solid var(--brand);
      padding: .5rem;
      margin: 0 .6rem 0 0;
      initial-letter: 1.7;
    }
    
    
    :root {
      --color:hsl(240, 9%, 14%);
      --c1: hsl(355, 81%, 62%);
      --c2: hsl(293, 93%, 73%);
      --c3: hsl(240, 100%, 81%);
      --gradient: linear-gradient(
        60deg,
        var(--c3),
        var(--c2),
        var(--c1),
        var(--c2),
        var(--c3)
      );
      --scale-start: 0.1;
      --scale-end: 1.0;
      /* 
        linear easing generator
        https://linear-easing-generator.netlify.app/
      */
       --ease-elastic: linear(
        0, 0.186 2.1%, 0.778 7.2%, 1.027 9.7%, 1.133, 1.212, 1.264, 1.292 15.4%,
        1.296, 1.294, 1.285, 1.269 18.9%, 1.219 20.9%, 1.062 25.8%, 0.995 28.3%,
        0.944 31.1%, 0.93, 0.921, 0.92 35.7%, 0.926, 0.94 39.7%, 1.001 47%, 1.014,
        1.021 52.4%, 1.02 56.4%, 1 65.5%, 0.994 70.7%, 1.001 88.4%, 1
      );
      --ease-bounce-out: cubic-bezier(0.34, 1.56, 0.64, 1);
    }
    
    @media (prefers-reduced-motion) {
      :root {
        --scale-start: var(--scale-end);
        --ease-elastic: ease-out;
        --ease-bounce-out: ease-out;
      }
    }
    
    .text {
      font-family:Georgia, serif;
      background-image: var(--gradient);
      font-size: 5rem;
      background-clip: text;
      -webkit-background-clip: text;
      color: transparent;
    }
    
    @supports (animation-timeline: view()) {
      .box {
        animation: trigger steps(1) both, fade linear both;
        animation-timeline: view();
        animation-range: entry 40% contain 40%;
      }
    
      .text {
        animation: pop-back 1s var(--ease-bounce-out) forwards;
      }
    
      @container style(--animate: true) {
        .text {
          animation: pop 1s var(--ease-elastic) forwards,
            text-gradient 500Ms cubic-bezier(0, 0.55, 0.45, 1) forwards;
        }
      }
    }
    
    @keyframes fade {
      from {
        opacity: 0;
      }
      to {
        opacity: 1;
      }
    }
    
    @keyframes trigger {
      to {
        --animate: true;
      }
    }
    
    @keyframes pop {
      from {
        scale: var(--scale-start);
      }
      to {
        scale: var(--scale-end);
      }
    }
    
    @keyframes text-gradient {
      100% {
        background-position: 10% center;
      }
    }
    
    @keyframes pop-back {
      from {
        scale: var(--scale-end);
      }
      to {
        color: var(--color);
        scale: var(--scale-start);
      }
    }
    
    
    .w-mode{
       writing-mode: vertical-lr;
       font-size: 2rem; 
       transform: rotate(180deg);
       margin:0 1rem 0 0 ; 
       filter: drop-shadow( -3rem 0 rgba(25, 25, 25, 0.339))  brightness(200%);
    }
    
    .box {
    display: grid; 
    grid-template-columns: 6rem auto;
    align-items: end;
    background-color:black;
    }
    
    .box h2{
      margin-inline-start:-1rem;      
    }
    
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;text-effect&quot;&gt;Typo&lt;wbr&gt;graphy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;responsive-typography&quot;&gt;Responsive typography&lt;/h2&gt;  
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ve gone from one screen resolution to accommodating standard mobile and tablet sizes to no assumptions about viewport size or pixel density.  We&#39;ve seen various shifts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;px to rems.&lt;/strong&gt;  Once hotly debated. The 62.5% trick of converting 1 rem to 10 px is still quite popular.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Media queries to fluid typography&lt;/strong&gt; (with viewport units and calc). Recommended: The &lt;a href=&quot;https://utopia.fyi/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Utopia CSS generator&lt;/a&gt; and Trys Mudford&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xd6wSHqGreQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;video presentation&lt;/a&gt; about Utopia and fluid design. Utopia also helps us with type scale.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;individually spaced elements to systems for flow (vertical stacking)&lt;/strong&gt;. Recommended: &lt;a href=&quot;https://every-layout.dev/layouts/stack/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;The stack on Every Layout&lt;/a&gt;  and this &lt;a href=&quot;https://someantics.dev/great-typography-with-modern-css/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;typography demo&lt;/a&gt; by Mike Mai on Ben Myer&#39;s someantics.dev.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New units:&lt;/strong&gt; ch, ex, vw, vh, vmin and vmax. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;accessibility&quot;&gt;Accessibility &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have seem an increased awareness that the web should be readable to all:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From a western bias to writing modes and internationalisation.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://noscript.show/3&quot;&gt;We talk about this&lt;/a&gt; when discussing a talk by Rachel Andrew on modern CSS layout.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web safe fonts to an abundance of open source options and back to quality and system fonts.&lt;/strong&gt; We did a &lt;a href=&quot;https://noscript.show/learn/3&quot;&gt;short video &lt;/a&gt;on system fonts which looked at &lt;a href=&quot;https://modernfontstacks.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;modernfontstacks.com.&lt;/a&gt;  Familiarity help users the most, but designers like new trends. We have to find a balance.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From the browser styles to setting line height and proximity according to the font used&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;abbr title=&quot;The Web Content Accessibility Guidelines&quot;&gt;WCAG&lt;/abbr&gt; can give us some guidelines (ie. 1.5 for paragraph line heights). Experts set this according to the font&#39;s &quot;X&quot; size. They know also to reduce the line height on headings and make the space above a heading wider the the space to the next paragraph for better proximity. &lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;From seeing link underlining as &quot;visual clutter&quot; to respecting it as essential UI&lt;/strong&gt;. We now have &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/text-underline-offset&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;text underlining offset &lt;/a&gt;, text-decoration thickness and style giving designers more control.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;variable-fonts&quot;&gt;Variable Fonts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Multiple font formats (TTF, OFT, EOT, WOFF) to WOFF2 (unless supporting IE).&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Individually loading weights and italics to fine control via CSS.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Color (chromatic) fonts. It is probably too soon to see the value particularly as this has not started with one format.
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section class=&quot;wide&quot;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesser-used-specifications&quot;&gt;Lesser used specifications&lt;/h2&gt;   
&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
There&#39;s lots in HTML and CSS that is probably under-used in typography.  Here we are using &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/columns&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;CSS columns&lt;/a&gt; to force two columns within the space available. We could set it to &lt;code&gt;columns: 2;&lt;/code&gt; but we would need a media query for smaller devices. Instead this set to &lt;code&gt;columns: 18rem auto;&lt;/code&gt; so when there is not 18rem of space it colapses to one column.    
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the above section we are using &lt;code&gt;:first-letter&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;initial-letter: 1.5&lt;/code&gt; to create a drop cap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; On this site the &lt;code&gt; &amp;lt;kbd&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/kbd&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag saves us needing images to explain keyboard commands &lt;kbd&gt;Ctrl&lt;/kbd&gt;  &lt;kbd&gt;⇧ Shift&lt;/kbd&gt; and &lt;kbd&gt;Enter ↵ &lt;/kbd&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&#39;s many other useful tags in HTML. In this article we have used: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;abbr title=&amp;quot;Web Content Accessibility Guidelines&amp;quot;&amp;gt;WCAG&amp;lt;/abbr&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and used &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;wbr&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to force the Typograpy title to break as &quot;typo&quot; and &quot;graphy&quot; when ther is not enough space. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;new-specifications&quot;&gt;New specifications &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/hanging-punctuation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;Hanging-punctuation&lt;/a&gt; It gives us the ability to have stop quotation marks indenting the text. Safari only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/font-size-adjust&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;font-size-adjust&lt;/a&gt;Most useful for ajusting fallback fonts to match custom fonts. Preventing a jump. Limited availability &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/font-kerning&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;font-kerning &lt;/a&gt; sets the use of the kerning information stored in a font. Auto lets the browser decide. Normal let the font decide. Fully supported.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/CSS/background-clip&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot;&gt;background-clip &lt;/a&gt; sets whether an element&#39;s background extends underneath its border box, padding box, or content box. Used on the title of this post. Widely Available.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;box&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w-mode&quot;&gt;Typography&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;h2 class=&quot;text pop&quot; id=&quot;branding-and-storytelling&quot;&gt;Branding &amp; Storytelling&lt;/h2&gt;    
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Designers have got ever more creative with text and the &lt;abbr title=&quot;Worldwide Web Consoritum&quot;&gt;W3C&lt;/abbr&gt; is making it easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scroll animation coming to CSS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing modes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better positioning with CSS grid and subgrid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Blending, filtering, masking and overlapping with other elements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Transcript&lt;/summary&gt;                 
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:05] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Welcome to the No Script show about modern web design, where we look at what we can build today with minimal software and skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we&amp;#8217;re talking about how web typography has evolved to meet new technological and social demands. We can&amp;#8217;t cover all the new CSS properties and units or fully explore what is possible with variable fonts, but we might be able to understand modern web typography through its changing history. David.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How comfortable are you with the topic of typography? Now there&amp;#8217;s a leading question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:00:37] David Waumsley: Yeah. not very, I always feel intimidated. We were talking about this earlier. I think we both feel that when people really know their stuff, when they&amp;#8217;ve got design training, they know stuff and it&amp;#8217;s almost a secret language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that&amp;#8217;s a club. Yep. I dunno the secret handshake to get in, but I&amp;#8217;m learning stuff and it&amp;#8217;s becoming more important to me all the time and&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:01:02] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;think it never felt at the beginning when I was doing websites, it never felt like an important thing. And then I&amp;#8217;d open up a book. So when books were the way that you learn about the internet, I&amp;#8217;d open up a book and I&amp;#8217;d see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;somebody getting into typography and my eyes would just glaze over. there&amp;#8217;d be charts pointing to the corners of letters and the kerning and all of that kind of thing. And I think I don&amp;#8217;t need to know any of this. it&amp;#8217;s hard enough getting the pixels on the page, just I&amp;#8217;ll use whatever font comes my way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but you&amp;#8217;re right. And I, feel like a lot of people who have been, very good, capable, thoughtful about typography, I. Maybe they have some background in graphic design, a history of working in graphic design, or maybe they went to some art college or something like that. So there has been a feeling that it&amp;#8217;s in a domain that I don&amp;#8217;t, usually circulate in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:01:53] David Waumsley: I know. And you were showing me some of the books that were on your shelf there. Yeah. You&amp;#8217;ve got things by Elliot J Stock and, what was it? Mark Bolton. Mark Bolton.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:02:00] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;The, the Designing for the Web, it&amp;#8217;s an old book now, but open it up and it&amp;#8217;s full of this typography stuff and, actually interestingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think that information in that book has probably aged. If you were to look at screenshots of websites, that will be terribly outta date. &amp;#8217;cause that book&amp;#8217;s probably about 12, maybe older, maybe as much as 15 years old, I&amp;#8217;m not sure. the, layouts and the capabilities and the screenshots of the websites, they&amp;#8217;re really out of date now and you almost smirk looking at them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the typography information. It looks as fresh today as it ever did. So that&amp;#8217;s curious. It&amp;#8217;s this stuff is old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:02:40] David Waumsley: Yeah. And I think what we&amp;#8217;re talking about is how we&amp;#8217;ve translated some of that historically onto the web here. We&amp;#8217;ve not worried about it &amp;#8217;cause we&amp;#8217;ve been limited in what we could do When we started with the web, when we started, we.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You had those website fonts anyway, but, but I, and I think there&amp;#8217;s also errors that we&amp;#8217;ve never even thought of that you and I both been exposed to you particularly &amp;#8217;cause you&amp;#8217;ve interviewed a lot of people who are knowledgeable about this. So there&amp;#8217;s a lot of things like knowing a readable character length, across the page, something that&amp;#8217;s comfortable to read with, something generally under about 70 characters or something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underline in text, which we&amp;#8217;ll talk about links as we&amp;#8217;ll talk about. And, Just generally. also we tended to center things, didn&amp;#8217;t we? Yeah. Blocks of paragraphs, which were hard to read. So I think there&amp;#8217;s a lot of things that you and I would&amp;#8217;ve picked up because it&amp;#8217;s coming even to, those communities in WordPress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, pick up from a lot of people knowledgeable in that, about that kind of stuff. But&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:03:40] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;yeah. Yeah, whenever I&amp;#8217;ve spoken to somebody who is deeply embedded in this kind of thing, I am profoundly. Interested in the level of detail that you can get to with typography? Yeah, we&amp;#8217;re, obviously, in this episode, we&amp;#8217;re gonna scratch almost none of the surface even.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re just, we&amp;#8217;re just touching the merest bit of it. But when you get into it, all of the different bits and pieces that make up a letter, there&amp;#8217;s so many words that are, ligatures and kerning and all of these different things, and I don&amp;#8217;t know what most of them are. Having a conversation though with these people always leaves me feeling, wow, there&amp;#8217;s a, that literally is a career just in that, just in learning typography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I think it&amp;#8217;s, I think it&amp;#8217;s not, I think the ship has sailed for me. David. No, I think&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:04:33] David Waumsley: we can start to, we can implement a lot of stuff that sat there. I think what makes me interested in it is. Following on from my last chat, we were talking about how difficult it is with images that I know even from the early web when I could look at somebody who knows typography, they can lay out a beautiful site with text only and I just think I wanna be able to do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Anyway, shall we bring up the show notes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:04:56] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Yeah, indeed. Indeed. Here we go. Okay, I&amp;#8217;ll just quick plug about this website, So you are looking at, if you are looking at this and not listening to it, but if you are listening to it and want to look at it, go to no script show. So that&amp;#8217;s the url, no script show, and then forward slash whatever episode we&amp;#8217;re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is episode 11. no script show slash 11. We&amp;#8217;ll get you to this page. And what a, fantastic start you&amp;#8217;ve made at the top there, David. That looks like an image. Surely it&amp;#8217;s an image. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:05:32] David Waumsley: it&amp;#8217;s type, it&amp;#8217;s just using, I think, a fairly new property where we can, and I always forget what the name of it, I mention it later in the notes, so we&amp;#8217;ll come to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;#8217;s a, basically a clipping two type. And then we can put an image showing through, so the, type is transparent and the image underneath it is clipped in it. So yeah, I thought I needed to do something a little bit fancy for this episode, yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:05:54] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;But that is really, lovely, isn&amp;#8217;t it? Because just, the evolution of that in the day when we began, that was possible, but only as an image without a doubt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and it&amp;#8217;s not. it, I, don&amp;#8217;t know how many people deploy this kind of typography, but that looks profoundly nice. it may not to be ev everybody&amp;#8217;s palette, the colors or what have you, but look at what&amp;#8217;s possible. Yeah. It&amp;#8217;s copy pastable. It is the word typography on a screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you&amp;#8217;ve got all these lovely flowing colors in the background and it really sets it off. It&amp;#8217;s really alive at the very beginning, so Bravo. Lovely job. Yeah, thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:06:34] David Waumsley: okay. Should we start with, we&amp;#8217;re looking at changes, so we&amp;#8217;ll start with the biggest change probably is the, responsive web and how typography had to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we&amp;#8217;ll start talking, I think about responsive typography because we&amp;#8217;ve gone from that single screen resolution that we could all work to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;#8217;s similar to print. Then we&amp;#8217;ve gone to. Responsive when we first got our sort of standard sizes for our most mobiles and tablets to now when we can make no assumptions about the viewport size of that our users have, or the pixel density as well that comes with those devices. So we, that&amp;#8217;s meant that we&amp;#8217;ve had quite a few shifts really, that the first one is from pixels to Rems as our unit for working with type.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I think with that I&amp;#8217;ve put down that it was once hotly debated. and it was up till quite recently, I think, with a lot of people still preferring pixels, still backwards looking on this, but I. And we were talking about this earlier, it&amp;#8217;s, been a recommendation for s from the W three C since we&amp;#8217;ve had CSS three, which is going back to 1999.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So 20,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:07:52] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;25 years that everybody&amp;#8217;s ignored it. Yeah, but that&amp;#8217;s because that&amp;#8217;s, largely because. They weren&amp;#8217;t able to use it. The browsers didn&amp;#8217;t keep up. Exactly right. Exactly. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:05] David Waumsley: And I think it still continued on because, It&amp;#8217;s, not just that, that the technology wasn&amp;#8217;t there to allow us with rems, it&amp;#8217;s just that we&amp;#8217;re so used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;people have to convert often from a pixel perfect design onto the web, and they&amp;#8217;re used to working with pixels rather than, having something which is just non-static at all with rems. But I think the argument&amp;#8217;s over, and I don&amp;#8217;t think you&amp;#8217;ll find any experts that will. For pixels now because of the accessibility, because of the fact that it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you&amp;#8217;re unable a user&amp;#8217;s unable then to change their browser settings if they want something large and have that honored and have everything, proportionately changed. So I think REMS is definitely it because it&amp;#8217;s more manageable, it&amp;#8217;s more scalable. You, can change your mind about the overall size quite easily by changing the root percentage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:08:59] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;But, I guess a reason for. This not becoming the default also is because it&amp;#8217;s so much less intuitive to understand. It&amp;#8217;s there&amp;#8217;s, some weird number that you put in there which isn&amp;#8217;t necessarily an integer. And because of that it&amp;#8217;s hard to ga gauge what that means. And based upon what you&amp;#8217;ve got as the root font size them, it might look different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas with a pixel you put in 30 and assuming you&amp;#8217;re using the same font throughout the website, you know what that&amp;#8217;s gonna look like. And. 15 will be smaller by this exact amount, and 50 will be bigger by this exact amount. But, but it doesn&amp;#8217;t allow for the capacity to change it. I guess a trick in the page builders that we&amp;#8217;ve used is to use media queries and then change the font size within the mobile view and all of this kind of thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, better to just set it up once and get it right with, leading onto the next point, media queries and fluid typography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:09:59] David Waumsley: Yeah, exactly. REMS on their own. I, suppose they weren&amp;#8217;t as convincing us pixels and why the debate went on until we really got, viewport units and calc allowing us to move from media queries where we&amp;#8217;re saying, okay, it&amp;#8217;s gonna be this pixels at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This view port width and there&amp;#8217;s gonna be, now we&amp;#8217;ve moved to fluid tire topography where we can use Cal and let the browser calculate it first. So I guess why the, why we&amp;#8217;ve everybody&amp;#8217;s accepted REMS now is because of the fact we could use fluid typography and we&amp;#8217;ve got these generators that takes all of the chore outta the maths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And my recommended one is the utopia. One, and there&amp;#8217;s a presentation I&amp;#8217;ve linked to it on the show notes there, which is worth watching by Tris Midford, who talks about not only their tool and what they&amp;#8217;re doing with it, but just generally fluid design. And it&amp;#8217;s made it so much easier because now, if I want to do anything now, I just go over to their tool and I say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it starts with pixels. You put in what you want, right at the smallest size, your base layer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:11:04] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;going. Yeah. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:11:05] David Waumsley: You say, what do you imagine the pixels to be there? What do you imagine its largest size that you are accommodating. Put the pixel value expected and it does the calculation between those two points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it also allows you to change the typography scale, which is. Another thing again, which makes typography so much better. It&amp;#8217;s like musical notes. There are set types of scales that you do, so the spacing, and it will do all that for you. So as it&amp;#8217;s condensing down to a mobile, the type of scale that you might have at a large size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There needs to be less space between, the lettering and stuff. the text itself,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:11:39] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;I, confess I&amp;#8217;ve not used that tool, but it sounds like a really valuable thing. So just in case you&amp;#8217;re listening to this on the audio, Google Utopia, CSS generator, and if you are able to get to our show notes, there&amp;#8217;s a link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Directly there, so I should probably check that out. I confess I didn&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:11:58] David Waumsley: No, there&amp;#8217;s a num I, I&amp;#8217;ve done a small video where I&amp;#8217;ve mentioned it as well and using it, and I, it&amp;#8217;s my favorite one. There&amp;#8217;s a lot of ones out there. Why I like it is because they&amp;#8217;re, they use it all the time. There&amp;#8217;s a few good designers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andy Bell is one of them who uses it. All the time. and they&amp;#8217;re using it in Clear Left, which is, Jeremy Keith&amp;#8217;s agency as well. So they&amp;#8217;re supporting it. So they&amp;#8217;re really keeping up to date on things that are changing with typography as well. So that&amp;#8217;s why I like theirs above all others, but Okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Yeah. and it&amp;#8217;s got other things that go with it. Spacing as well, which I used. yeah, so I think, yeah, I never connected the dots until we started talking about the whole REM thing, but I think it&amp;#8217;s, everybody&amp;#8217;s jumped to rems when you can see, you can use the fluid typography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that seems to be the way I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:12:47] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;We should probably say at this point what the fluid ty, what fluid typography is, and if you&amp;#8217;ve never en encountered it, and you are using, I don&amp;#8217;t know, media queries to change bluntly, you&amp;#8217;ve got a, I don&amp;#8217;t know, a, font sizing pixels for desktop, a font sizing pixels for tablet, and a font sizing pixels for anything less than tablet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Call it mobile, then. This is different. This is where the, this is the allowance with fluid typography. That the, width, it&amp;#8217;s, it is a complete linear scale. If you, enlarge the, view port, given the constraints or what, what CSS you use, the typography will just grow proportionately and then reach some sort of maximum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you&amp;#8217;re on, like a giant eight K monitor, it&amp;#8217;s not, gonna be truly enormous. It&amp;#8217;ll max out at some point that you set. But, it&amp;#8217;s beautiful watching it when you actually just grab the handles of your browser and reduce, enlarge, reduce enlarge, and you see the font size growing and shrinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And actually if, you think about that&amp;#8217;s what we should always have had. I. I wish we had that, but we didn&amp;#8217;t, tech technology didn&amp;#8217;t allow for it, but that&amp;#8217;s exactly what you want, right? I&amp;#8217;m on this size device and it&amp;#8217;s halfway between this and this. So the font is there and it&amp;#8217;s perfectly aligned for the viewport that I&amp;#8217;ve got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. it&amp;#8217;s a shame that it&amp;#8217;s now a new thing rather than this has been around forever and ever since the dawn of the internet. And it&amp;#8217;s a kind&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:14:13] David Waumsley: of compromise with it. &amp;#8217;cause I think when it first came out with the fluid typography, it was just saying, oh, we could use viewport width now to do everything right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then you realize that you have to anchor that a little bit with a REM in there to make sure that, because if you do that, then users can&amp;#8217;t zoom out on their browser. So you there&amp;#8217;s a strange anchor and the mass of it become very difficult. So you are not absolutely fully assure, unless you, move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your browser to see how it&amp;#8217;s responding. But it does get over that big hiccup in the fact that once where we have used the responsive to set them to our known mobiles and tablet sizes, we found that many are just before the break point that you might be reaching and then suddenly their text is out proportion to the size of their device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. And you get this horrible jump in, so it gets rid of that. Yeah. And it&amp;#8217;s, it is lovely, isn&amp;#8217;t it? yeah. I think another thing that&amp;#8217;s changed, at least for me, this might be my ignorance, but there&amp;#8217;s a sort of move away, I think from our browsers would generally sort out the spacing on an element by element.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basis, or we would style elements. we would put the margins of the paddings that we wanted on our individual elements. Now, I think there&amp;#8217;s more of an interest in looking at flow because we want to control uniformly the. The space that we&amp;#8217;ve got between our paragraphs and stuff. So there are a couple of, again, a couple of things that I would recommend for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One is the stack, which is on every layout, which is, again, Andy Bell, who I&amp;#8217;ve mentioned, and probably a key person behind this is Hayden Pickering, because 10 years ago now, he came up with something called. atomic, which you called the No, it was the Lobotomized Owl. Oh, this little selector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;yeah. Yeah. it&amp;#8217;s, he always had this problem, so if you put pad in padding on the bottom of your paragraphs, then the last paragraph would always have that padding that you didn&amp;#8217;t want. So he&amp;#8217;s used this little technique to be able to. Effectively set it on the top of your paragraph, but by using these Lobotomized owl, it&amp;#8217;s a child so that, so he doesn&amp;#8217;t select the first one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so there&amp;#8217;s something that you can uniform the spaces. And there&amp;#8217;s also a wonderful demo as well. Definitely recommended. I wanna watch it again by, Mike. May who&amp;#8217;s a really good person on typography and he is got lots of tools as well, that you can use, but is on a show by Ben Meyers called some antics Do dev.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, that&amp;#8217;s clever Semantic. I love what a clever name. Yeah, And you&amp;#8217;ve gotta watch that. if you&amp;#8217;re really into typography, I&amp;#8217;ve gotta watch it again. &amp;#8217;cause I didn&amp;#8217;t, it went over my head. But it really discusses that whole idea of flow and he sets it more manually. But, yeah, and I think that&amp;#8217;s a kind of fairly new thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:17:07] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Again, links in the show notes, both of those things. The stack and the typography demo by Mike May, my, I&amp;#8217;m not sure, is in the show notes. And then we&amp;#8217;ve got these new units, which honestly I don&amp;#8217;t know anywhere near enough about, so I&amp;#8217;m hoping that you are actually gonna school me here. This&amp;#8217;ll be interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:17:27] David Waumsley: I&amp;#8217;m pretty poor on them. One that I do use. So we&amp;#8217;ve got ch which is for character, so we can set our. Width of things by the character length, which is really, useful for that problem that I mentioned earlier about the fact that we tend to, or I did, tend to put too many words. I. On a full view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so it&amp;#8217;s not very readable. You can set with your character length, and that&amp;#8217;s what I&amp;#8217;m doing actually on the site that you&amp;#8217;re looking at. So what&amp;#8217;s setting the length of the inner container here is the characters. I think it&amp;#8217;s set at 70. So effectively the text within that can expand beyond that. So a lot of people are using that in part of the responsive design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you set that maximum on all of your paragraphs, then wherever you&amp;#8217;re gonna place &amp;#8217;em in your design, you know it&amp;#8217;s going to be. Fairly readable, you said?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:15] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Yeah. That&amp;#8217;s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:15] David Waumsley: interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:16] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Okay. That&amp;#8217;s fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:17] David Waumsley: Yeah, and something I don&amp;#8217;t think I&amp;#8217;ve ever used yet, which is X, the Ex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is ex Yeah. I&amp;#8217;ve never used this. No, it&amp;#8217;s based, it&amp;#8217;s a little bit like M&amp;#8217;S are based on the, the font, M size, and we get REMS from that because we get root elements. X is the same. It&amp;#8217;s something in typography, which again, I don&amp;#8217;t understand, which is set in the, height of the X basically is something measuring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when you get clever people like Mike May, who knows how to use these, they will actually use that value for setting the heights. They will use that for. Knowing what is the correct line height to put according to the font that you&amp;#8217;re using? Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:18:59] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;this rings a bell. it&amp;#8217;s got, it has got some characteristic of the letter X, hasn&amp;#8217;t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I can&amp;#8217;t remember why that letter in particular. Maybe it&amp;#8217;s just got certain height or width ratio. Yeah. Can&amp;#8217;t remember, but yeah. Okay. That&amp;#8217;s fascinating. So not the letter X, but EX in this case. Yeah,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:19:18] David Waumsley: EX in this case. I&amp;#8217;ve never used it yet, but it&amp;#8217;s really for, if you do understand that you might be setting certain things against the, X value of the font if you really understand the font you are using.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you are styling into that. Yeah, it goes a bit above me. And then of course we got the. We&amp;#8217;ve already talked about them. We&amp;#8217;ve got the sort of a viewport width of Viewport height. We can start using an viewport minimum of Viewport Max. And someone like Mike May, again, I really don&amp;#8217;t use V Max yet, but he might use it to section the sort of space he will put on sections of his site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So his header, his footer, his main, The leftover space at the bottom, he&amp;#8217;ll be setting this to percentage. So depending on the browser itself, it will allow a little bit more space or less as needed. So again, it&amp;#8217;s, it&amp;#8217;s one way of doing it. But again, I use other things in Utopia for spacing to, set spacing so it changes according to the size of the viewport.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there&amp;#8217;s lots of different ways to skin this particular cat, I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:20:19] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Yeah. And no doubt a Google around each of these will give you, yeah, a lot more information. But yeah, some of those a mystery to me. Some of them I&amp;#8217;ve definitely used. Okay. Shall we move on? Yeah. Yeah. Accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:20:33] David Waumsley: again, that&amp;#8217;s a big.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;awareness boost that we&amp;#8217;ve had recently over accessibility, maybe because it&amp;#8217;s becoming law for us. So if we do it professionally, I guess we should be aware of these things. So there&amp;#8217;s a lot of changes there. we&amp;#8217;ve talked about this before. There&amp;#8217;s, we&amp;#8217;ve really gone from this western bias on the web to now having writing modes and internationalization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. So we, I think we talked, Rachel Andrews talked about that when we were talking. I think it was in episode three when we talked about how we need to know this concept to know our CSS layouts. But there are lots of other things coming along with that. I noticed, I was just listening to the latest release, on Chrome where they have started to put in place something so you can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deal with, Chinese, Japanese, and Korean characters and stuff, and kind of space those out, Oh, interesting. That&amp;#8217;s a big shift. Interesting. Yeah. Okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:21:34] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Yeah. So we were saying before the call began, weren&amp;#8217;t we before we hit record, at least that, at least I don&amp;#8217;t, really even think about the, web as, a Chinese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Character thing. Yes. if I ever see something like that, I, I&amp;#8217;ve clearly strayed into an area of the web that I can&amp;#8217;t access &amp;#8217;cause I can&amp;#8217;t read Chinese. But just think of the population and the fact that all of these browsers in the past, at least anyway, were really configured for, left to top to bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. and the character set being, a Latin alphabet. And of course most of the world don&amp;#8217;t, use any of that. But, but we&amp;#8217;re educated to think about that. and even, the things that we&amp;#8217;ve been talking about, the ex is based upon the, Latin character X and so on. And I don&amp;#8217;t even know where to begin with typography with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t know, a Chinese character set. I, no idea what the concerns are there. I do know that there&amp;#8217;s a history of, calligraphy and making those characters look beautiful. I would say even more so than we have in the West with our typography, that there seems to be a real heritage in, I. when they paint the Chinese characters, making them look beautiful and adding weight to certain strokes so that they enlarge in one part and diminish in another, and then, tail off into sort of, almost nothingness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I. Yeah. And, yeah. Fascinating. I&amp;#8217;d, love to get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:23:10] David Waumsley: into that. It&amp;#8217;s interesting &amp;#8217;cause I think the new things that you brought out for them is, a word break and auto phase for them. And also trimming because how, how their text is getting aligned in the sort of spacing isn&amp;#8217;t. Always perfect on the web and kind of, this is all still new stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems incredible that you should have such a large population of people Yeah. Who have not been accommodated so far on the web. But that&amp;#8217;s definitely a change and it knocks onto us. &amp;#8217;cause even if we never deal with those, we&amp;#8217;ve had to understand things like Flexbox and grid layouts in terms of writing modes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ve needed to have that concept to be able to align things properly. So yeah, that&amp;#8217;s a massive change. Shall I move to the next thing? sure. That is our shift away from what we had when we started, which was only web, say fonts or system fonts to this abundance of open source options. Google fonts particularly, and then back to, I think I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;#8217;s not, this is, this keeps going backwards and forwards I&amp;#8217;m sure to a few quality fonts that you use that have all the character sets that are, flexible or a trend a bit back to considering system fonts again, I. So I did a little video on that one before, which was &lt;a href=&quot;https://noscript.show/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection&quot; class=&quot;__cf_email__&quot; data-cfemail=&quot;d3bfbcbcb8babdb493bebcb7b6a1bdb5bcbda7a0a7b2b0b8fdb0bcbe&quot;&gt;[email&amp;#160;protected]&lt;/a&gt;, which allows you to see what, what fonts are available on different systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And you get a little screenshot of it as well, so you can see how they might pan out if you do want to use them. But there&amp;#8217;s a real, I. I think from a accessibility point of view is the fact that probably what helps people with dyslexia above anything else or other things is familiarity. So if it&amp;#8217;s your system font that you&amp;#8217;re using for your body text, if that&amp;#8217;s an apple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we should be seeing there, I think should be San Francisco on your screen. this is a variable font. It&amp;#8217;s a, font that we couldn&amp;#8217;t license and, for many people that&amp;#8217;s just gonna be familiar. So it&amp;#8217;s a good font to use perhaps, rather than bringing in a custom one where we don&amp;#8217;t need to, where it doesn&amp;#8217;t add any extra value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:25:19] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Yeah, I think we all got a bit carried away when Google fonts came around, didn&amp;#8217;t we? Dumping, just dumping every kind of imaginable font that we could because it looked quirky and interesting. And I, think you&amp;#8217;re right. I think there&amp;#8217;s definitely a move away from that, in the WordPress space and CMS space and, webspace, localizing those fonts, I guess is a, recent endeavor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, GDPR and all that kind of thing. But, but I, think you&amp;#8217;re right. I think going back to system fonts and something which is familiar. for functional text. Text, like we&amp;#8217;re seeing on the screen now where we&amp;#8217;re just trying to get information from us to you where the flare and the novelty of it is really not the point then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. But obviously if I was to go to, I don&amp;#8217;t know, the latest band&amp;#8217;s website, the latest pop stars website, where that sort of creativity is trying to be emphasized. Maybe the bit about how tickets, how much tickets cost, and where the venue is. Maybe that&amp;#8217;d be a web safe font. the bit about, what the artist does and who they are, especially the headings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You you, still feel you&amp;#8217;ve gotta go a bit knots with that because, &amp;#8217;cause it, that&amp;#8217;s part of the whole typography thing is allowing you to be creative. But I&amp;#8217;m like you, but maybe it&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8217;cause I&amp;#8217;m old and my eyes are starting to fail a bit more. I&amp;#8217;ve got glasses on and things I want, I would just want clarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just want everything to be, the contrast between the background and the font. To be clear, I need it to be readable. I need it to be spaced out and I, I honestly don&amp;#8217;t care too much for the, for the snazzy fonts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:26:55] David Waumsley: Yeah, and I, just think, obviously with the other pressures, the kind of green pressures and the speed pressures as well, that, if there&amp;#8217;s not a good reason to argue for a custom font, we don&amp;#8217;t necessarily stick it in and, but that&amp;#8217;s not been my thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last 10 years, it&amp;#8217;s been like, woo. Which, of all these fonts that, Exactly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:27:14] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Which one might Crow are in? But don&amp;#8217;t you have, I can&amp;#8217;t remember the last time this happened to me, but when you stumble across a website where they&amp;#8217;ve just got text, so imagery is out the window, it&amp;#8217;s just, plain background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. Beautiful typography, something clear, readable. They&amp;#8217;ve obviously thought about the layout a lot. Yeah, it really does. It compels you. It just sucks you in, Yeah. it, it&amp;#8217;s, really profound what fonts can do. In fact, we said this before we began the show. The. A website where clearly somebody&amp;#8217;s put a lot of effort into fonts and making their typography look amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It it really knocks it out the park. It takes something ordinary and makes it into extraordinary, but it, I don&amp;#8217;t end up looking at the font particularly. I just get this profound sense. Oh, that&amp;#8217;s clever. That&amp;#8217;s really beautiful. Yeah. I&amp;#8217;m now gonna go and explore what font that is and what the wits that they&amp;#8217;re using and all of these kind of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, yeah, sorry, digression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:28:14] David Waumsley: Yeah, no, that&amp;#8217;s fine. the next point in some ways I think I&amp;#8217;ve made it already, but, perhaps a trend in that from moving to browser setting the line heights and stuff, or as individually doing it to, and proximity according to fonts use. So in some ways we have some guidance about line height is usually the biggest problem for people not being able to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;#8217;ve got your paragraphs and you&amp;#8217;ve not got the right amount, and you can go to something like war gag. the, actually there&amp;#8217;s another little thing on there. If you hover over the wagg, you&amp;#8217;ll see I&amp;#8217;m using, oh, it&amp;#8217;s under lined with a, I&amp;#8217;m using the abbreviation here. Another bit of typography.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the web content accessibility guidelines. Oh, sadly,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:28:56] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;our video platform doesn&amp;#8217;t pick that up. That&amp;#8217;s interesting. Ah, that&amp;#8217;s, but, I am hovering over something and on my screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:03] David Waumsley: Ah, interesting. Oh, I can&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:04] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;see it. And, it, there, there&amp;#8217;s a little, like a, tool tip if you like, that&amp;#8217;s the browser has provided, which pops up to, to give me the context of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on, on the video, it&amp;#8217;s not come through. There&amp;#8217;s, there must be some reason for that. But anyway, there we go. And I think,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:29:19] David Waumsley: there&amp;#8217;s more awareness of lots of things about giving line height and, the experts will know how to do that against the, fonts. The waggle will give us guidelines, like it should be roughly about 1.5.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it&amp;#8217;s a unitless height, so it takes the value of the. The unit for the font that you&amp;#8217;ve said. and there were other things that I wasn&amp;#8217;t aware of until recently is the, and it&amp;#8217;s probably failing on this site. the idea of proximity, the idea that we need to leave a little bit more on a header when there&amp;#8217;s some paragraph text underneath it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The, on the header itself, the space above it needs to be more than the space before you get to the paragraph. So the proximity of the header two. The paragraph underneath is grouped together, and that makes for better reading. So these, yeah, it&amp;#8217;s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:30:05] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;interesting. I&amp;#8217;ve always found that to be strange when you look at that, when you see it on somebody else&amp;#8217;s website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I. It looks correct, but when you are in the weeds and you are looking at, let&amp;#8217;s say, I don&amp;#8217;t know the, padding above a heading, I always want to get rid of it. I want it to go away. But, then when I look at it on the front end, oh yeah, no, that, that looks right because it, you do need to give that little bit of breathing space, don&amp;#8217;t you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That bit&amp;#8217;s finished. We&amp;#8217;re now onto a new heading. There needs to be a, proportionate gap to show, okay, this is an H four. There&amp;#8217;s a. There&amp;#8217;s something going on there. This is an H three something and this is an H two something else. but I, always, have this intuition. I want to erase it, but I generally don&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:30:51] David Waumsley: Yeah. It&amp;#8217;s just that, it&amp;#8217;s just so you can see what content belongs with what which kind of belongs with the content below. Just proximity is one of those things which I&amp;#8217;m becoming more aware of all the time. as you listen to more people who know UX design and have that. Formal training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m just looking&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:05] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;for it on this page. And we, you don&amp;#8217;t really have too much use of that, do you? You&amp;#8217;ve got these great big, I&amp;#8217;m guessing these are H twos or something like that, but, it should be, if&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:14] David Waumsley: I&amp;#8217;ve done it I probably haven&amp;#8217;t, it should have a little bit more space above. Oh, it definitely does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:20] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;it looks like it, there&amp;#8217;s a little, you probably can&amp;#8217;t see on the screen. There&amp;#8217;s a little gray box here and the distance between the v and the box. Oh, no, it definitely is. There&amp;#8217;s definitely a little bit more. Okay. Alright, Rob.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:31:34] David Waumsley: the, next point under accessibility was just a, move, that we&amp;#8217;ve seen, I think recently about earlier we tended to see underlining as visual clutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;something that you, on your links I&amp;#8217;m talking about here, to now respecting it as a essential. UI and I think we&amp;#8217;ve been given some new tools that go along with that one that I most and I&amp;#8217;m using it all the time. If you see that, yeah, you are where the links are there, there&amp;#8217;s a, bit of a space between it, and that&amp;#8217;s because of the new property, which is the textline, underlining offset where you can actually offset that line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we, none of the descendants are touching on it. and also you can set the. Thickness of that line as well. You can make it a little bit thinner and obviously you can color it. So we&amp;#8217;ve got a lot more control over our links. Now&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:32:23] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;I really like what you&amp;#8217;ve done here. So obviously the descender, the G here in, in whatever font this is not particularly, it&amp;#8217;s not particularly long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The G doesn&amp;#8217;t descend that far. Yeah, but still. The, little gap that you&amp;#8217;ve got here, which is bigger than I would expect normally is nice. it really does make that kind of feel like it&amp;#8217;s, I don&amp;#8217;t know, it&amp;#8217;s not breaking up the, flow when my eyes going from left to right and reading through it, that line is out the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah. So I&amp;#8217;m able to read it as normal text and keep going. and I do the fact that the line isn&amp;#8217;t broken up. and, sorry, one last thing. And I do think that this has to become the default, doesn&amp;#8217;t it? I think we all just need to settle on underlining is the way to do it? Yeah, just let&amp;#8217;s all go back to underlining please.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:33:10] David Waumsley: It&amp;#8217;s become a, I think, setting also this offset, is quite nice. And I think some people have put it in their CSS resets if there&amp;#8217;s no other style against it or class against it that will be there. Stephanie Eccles does that and and I think that&amp;#8217;s. A really, it&amp;#8217;s only recent this, that we were able to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I can see why people are wanting to remove stuff, even though you do break up the line by default of browsers. If there is a descender, it can be a little bit uncomfortable to read. But yes, I think the argument now is that we should, and, to be honest, we&amp;#8217;re just going back to arguments that we&amp;#8217;re there from the nineties, so we,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:33:47] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:33:47] David Waumsley: Jacob Nielsen, who was always saying, you must underline your links. You must underline your links. And somehow we got designers got into the idea that it was just a bit clutter and we&amp;#8217;ll remove it, it&amp;#8217;s fine and it really isn&amp;#8217;t fine. And the way to know that is just imagine I. That you can&amp;#8217;t see color, and then you&amp;#8217;ll know it&amp;#8217;s not fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And imagine that. Yeah, that&amp;#8217;s a nice&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:34:06] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;way. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:34:07] David Waumsley: Simple. Or, imagine that your device is a black and white device, a monochrome device. Yeah. And suddenly you&amp;#8217;ve removed what the web basically is. It&amp;#8217;s,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:34:17] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;yeah. That&amp;#8217;s really a good point. Yeah. That&amp;#8217;s a perfect encapsulation of why. It needs to be that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are, if you cannot see color, just imagine it in black and white. And here it&amp;#8217;s pretty clear. Also, I guess your, the, line height, the gap between the, this, row of text and this row of text is enough to allow that. To breathe, if Yeah. So the, under, let&amp;#8217;s, yeah, this is a better example &amp;#8217;cause you can see more of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underline here, you&amp;#8217;ve got the offset, which is quite generous, but still not too much. But it&amp;#8217;s still not interfering with the road. Be below the, the line below it. This is still not being interfered with by this. And you can actually see that in the. The way it&amp;#8217;s being highlighted. So that&amp;#8217;s nice. nicely Don David,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:03] David Waumsley: basically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, we&amp;#8217;re using system fonts here, so I&amp;#8217;m not actually sure whether, the line height is right on yours as it is on the one that I see on the Interesting. So, it&amp;#8217;s a bit of a guesswork on that, I think. Anyway. Yeah, so I think that&amp;#8217;s definitely a move. And it was, it&amp;#8217;s down to the fact that we had frameworks like Bootstrap, which were hugely popular, that didn&amp;#8217;t underline their links by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s changed now. Bootstrap. Yeah. But anyway. Okay. Should we move on to the&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:29] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;next&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:29] David Waumsley: bit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:30] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;of technology? Yeah, we&amp;#8217;d better race, actually. We&amp;#8217;re on. Yeah, we&amp;#8217;re on. not, I&amp;#8217;m not sure exactly how long, but we&amp;#8217;ve added up quite a few minutes. So let&amp;#8217;s just put the, put the pedal to the metal. Is that what they say?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something like that. There&amp;#8217;s a lot to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:35:42] David Waumsley: cover here. Yeah. Variable fonts. We can cover them. Fairly quickly. there&amp;#8217;s a big, change in the fact that we used to have to support multiple font formats. &amp;#8217;cause there&amp;#8217;s a whole history with them. So we had the TTF, the OFT. I can&amp;#8217;t remember the what they stand for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But no, there were a whole history, I think you know, the true type form. There&amp;#8217;s the first one that was Microsoft and Apple getting together back in the eighties. And then you get. Variations that have come on those to make them fit better with the web. Things like, I think the OFT added ligatures and things like that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then we&amp;#8217;ve got the embedded ot, which was the one to work very well with IE. And then finally the world, worldwide web consortium got together and had a body for, fonts. And then that&amp;#8217;s when we got Wolff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:35] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Honestly, if you, if you get me to transcribe this with AI software, the last paragraph you just said will be so interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:36:45] David Waumsley: So, we get the web open font format, which is what we&amp;#8217;ve got. And from 2010, so this is really the recommendation from the Ws. Three C from 2010, and then they further optimize it. So we get WF two now support is there for WF two. So we&amp;#8217;ve basically gone from having to support all these, this history of formats to really being able to pretty much, unless we need to support IE, to get away with WF two, which is wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yay. Yay. What do, yeah. And the, great thing about this, which leads us really to the variable fonts is the fact that, the. That&amp;#8217;s the format for variable fonts, and I think that&amp;#8217;s the big trend now is the fact that instead of having to load individually the weights or the italic versions of the font that we&amp;#8217;re using, is that we can have this all within the one WF two format and use CSS to fine control the weights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if we want some. Bizarre weight. So we want it, instead of it going from 300 to 400 and we want 3, 2, 5, or something as the exact weight, we can do it with the variable fonts. And if we want our italics to slightly slant in a different way, we can do it with the CSS. So I think that&amp;#8217;s really exciting, at the moment that we can do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Downside, of course, is that you. if you&amp;#8217;re only using a couple of weights or something and you&amp;#8217;re not using all this extra, then they are a bit heavier than loading those individually. And finally, yeah, we put down, which I think we&amp;#8217;ll just skip &amp;#8217;cause I think we&amp;#8217;ll need to come back to it &amp;#8217;cause I don&amp;#8217;t understand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Color or chromatic fonts. Chromatic is the correct&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:38:25] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;word. no. I have no understanding of this. Anyway. It&amp;#8217;s a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:38:29] David Waumsley: It&amp;#8217;s a thing. Yeah. And actually it brings in a new format. I think it&amp;#8217;s taking one of the old formats with SVGs and I think there&amp;#8217;s not clarity over what that is. There are some, Google fonts out there, which are chromatic fonts that you can play around with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, don&amp;#8217;t quite get the value yet because I&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:38:45] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;don&amp;#8217;t, yeah, I&amp;#8217;m on trying to understand what the purpose is, if you, we can set the color of a font fairly straightforwardly in CSS I&amp;#8217;m interested to see what the benefit is. What, are we getting out of it? Is it that fonts can be, I don&amp;#8217;t know, can there be gradients in font colors, or.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I, yes,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:39:04] David Waumsley: exactly. I think it&amp;#8217;s exactly that and I think, you can do a lot of the tilting and rotating and stuff of your fonts, which can create some lovely effects. But in the ones that I&amp;#8217;ve seen around, the only thing where I could see I&amp;#8217;d use it and, effectively it&amp;#8217;s no dissimilar from what I&amp;#8217;m doing on the top header of this post where I&amp;#8217;m got an image coming through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where I&amp;#8217;ve seen a color font being used, say it&amp;#8217;s saying the word pizza and the background, the images of pizza and. Think, I&amp;#8217;m not going to load this quite heavy color font to do that when I can do it with a, kind of simple. Clip masking like this for myself, so yeah. Yeah. The value&amp;#8217;s not there yet for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay. We&amp;#8217;ll have to see. Perhaps I don&amp;#8217;t understand it. yeah. Alright. That&amp;#8217;s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:39:45] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;variable. Fonts. Now we&amp;#8217;re onto some lesser used specs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:39:49] David Waumsley: Yeah, I just wanted to mention a couple of things on typography &amp;#8217;cause they were relatively new to me, so I put an example up on there. So something which is really when we&amp;#8217;re talking about responsive again, it&amp;#8217;s not used and that&amp;#8217;s CSS columns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And actually this is so cool. This is so great. Yeah, it&amp;#8217;s, it is just simply that you can set. Columns for any of the things that you want, and you can make it responsive. It&amp;#8217;s not by default. So if we have a column count of two, it wouldn&amp;#8217;t be responsive. We&amp;#8217;d, we would need a media query. But what I&amp;#8217;ve done on here, because there is a, limited space anyway, I&amp;#8217;ve put it so it&amp;#8217;s just magic numbers with this, but I&amp;#8217;ve put it at 18 res here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;#8217;s created two columns while there&amp;#8217;s more than the 18 res to it. But if you. If you zoom in on this one, it will just automatically,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:40:36] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;see what we get. Oh, collapse. Probably make that in the center. Zoom. Let&amp;#8217;s put that right in the middle there. So I&amp;#8217;m gonna collapse the screen. We&amp;#8217;ve still got two columns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there look, there we go. There&amp;#8217;s some magic moment there. It collapses down into the one column. That&amp;#8217;s super useful. That&amp;#8217;s great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:40:54] David Waumsley: So sometimes we just, bring in grid and all of that stuff where we could simply do it with CSS columns. It&amp;#8217;s been there for some time. I think the spec&amp;#8217;s been tightened up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think, It&amp;#8217;s, Rachel, Andrew has been working on this as well, who worked on grid quite a lot. So anyway, it&amp;#8217;s just a really cool trick which gets ignored. And I think there are lots of other little things which I&amp;#8217;m just becoming aware of. So I&amp;#8217;ve put a drop shadow in there. It&amp;#8217;s another little bit of, on the t on my paragraph there, it&amp;#8217;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you see that it&amp;#8217;s, I&amp;#8217;ve styled it slightly different, used a different font, and it&amp;#8217;s going over one and a half of the text a little bit more because I&amp;#8217;ve put a little border around it on there. And this is something, though, it&amp;#8217;s not very well supported at the moment. So it&amp;#8217;s a combination of using first letter as a, pseudo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Element. Or class, I think. And then initial letter as a drop cap to do that. So these kind of things. Yeah. And then there&amp;#8217;s a whole thing, I won&amp;#8217;t go into too much here else, we&amp;#8217;ll go on forever, but I think there&amp;#8217;s a whole lot of HTML, which we underuse. So I&amp;#8217;ve just given one example here where I&amp;#8217;m using the keyboard one, rather than having to pull in an image, I can style the the.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KBD tag and create this kind of little control shift, enter keys or any key that I want. Just with CSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:42:19] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;They&amp;#8217;re nice, aren&amp;#8217;t they? They look really nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:42:22] David Waumsley: Yeah. I think all the pros, the people who&amp;#8217;ve been in this game longer than me will put these in their explanations, but I think it&amp;#8217;s, definitely worth looking at lots of, HTML because we just don&amp;#8217;t use many of the tags.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Mark, we don&amp;#8217;t use, we don&amp;#8217;t often put a. Different styling for time. All of these are tags which we often forget about, particularly if we&amp;#8217;ve come from a background of A CMS, we just put those in. and, I&amp;#8217;m using one actually on the top of the title there, so I&amp;#8217;m actually using one which I&amp;#8217;d entirely forgotten about until I started writing this, which is, the, let me just find it on the notes so I get it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one called. Somewhere. There it is. It&amp;#8217;s WBR, which is, there it is. It&amp;#8217;s basically, yes. It is given a width, it&amp;#8217;s width break opportunity, I think. And if you go to the top of the site here as I&amp;#8217;ve got a huge, typography here. I&amp;#8217;m actually using that to separate typo and graph. So if you slim in on that one when it hasn&amp;#8217;t got the room, oh, this is good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is, we&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:30] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;didn&amp;#8217;t do, we didn&amp;#8217;t try this before the show started. No. So I&amp;#8217;m making it smaller. We got the word typography. It will eventually break. Yay. Look at that. That&amp;#8217;s so&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:39] David Waumsley: great. So you could tell us where, if you really do want to keep your massive font or something, you might want to decide where it breaks, and that&amp;#8217;s an opportunity to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike a regular break, which will just break it for everybody. This breaks when there&amp;#8217;s the opportunity to break. You can set it wherever you like, multiple&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:54] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;things in one word or. Yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:43:57] David Waumsley: Yes. Yeah, exactly. So it&amp;#8217;s just sometimes you want your word to break in a different way. Yeah. If you&amp;#8217;re gonna keep it big, probably I should have just made it small, but, okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that&amp;#8217;s probably enough &amp;#8217;cause I&amp;#8217;m covering, yeah, the stuff. Let&amp;#8217;s talk about the new spec, shall we? okay, here we go. Couple of things here. That&amp;#8217;s, one that&amp;#8217;s only in Safari only, which I think is really handy, which is hanging punctuation, which will allow, and I&amp;#8217;ve heard this being talked about a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People get annoyed at that. If you&amp;#8217;ve got a block quote and the, you styled up your quotes on what, you&amp;#8217;re gonna put the quotes up there anyway, those quotes are going to indent your text. Yeah, And it&amp;#8217;s a lot easier if people keep. Running down vertically and see everything aligned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what hanging punctuation could do is to make sure that you get to choose that it goes outside. So you&amp;#8217;d have to use a lot of CSS to try and force your right. Yeah, there would be a lot of negative margins and all that nonsense. So that&amp;#8217;s quite cool, when it&amp;#8217;s supported. But it&amp;#8217;s safari only at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ve got font size adjust, which I talked about, about a year ago with doing stuff. Performance. it&amp;#8217;s just, it&amp;#8217;s the most useful thing is the fact that you can adjust, some of these fonts. Usually a fallback font, which might be a system font or something. So you can change its X shape, you can stretch it out a little bit so it can better match.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I. The custom font that is waiting to load. So it stops this sort of jarring when it&amp;#8217;s going from the system fallback font to the custom font loading in. So you can line them up a little bit better with that. it&amp;#8217;s limited availability at the moment, and there&amp;#8217;s, font ing, that&amp;#8217;s fully supported at the moment, which allows us to, Browsers Will, kerning is spacing basically between letters. Yeah. Yeah. Browsers will do that for themselves. If you want to force it, you can force it so that it&amp;#8217;s set by the font or you can let the browser do it, or you can just turn it off altogether if you are controlling that. So that&amp;#8217;s a, fully supported thing, but fairly new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, the thing that was. Making the, my title with the image coming through it is the background clip, which is beautiful. yeah, quite new but widely available now, and yeah, it&amp;#8217;s just used for clipping backgrounds on there and it&amp;#8217;s useful with text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:46:19] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Okay. Okay. So they&amp;#8217;re all in the show notes?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;no. All in the show notes, no script show slash 11. And then you&amp;#8217;ve got a little flourish at the end here, haven&amp;#8217;t you? You&amp;#8217;ve got something nice to. Yeah, if you scroll, scroll. Now. I scroll up. Scroll up. Hold on. I&amp;#8217;ll wait for it. You have to see this or go to the webpage. okay. I&amp;#8217;m gonna scroll up slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That little word typography, which is orientated at 90 degrees is fading in and out. I&amp;#8217;m noticing that. What am I waiting for? Oh, at that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;oh my. Yeah. Wow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:46:52] David Waumsley: You&amp;#8217;ve even got a little bounce going on there. Yeah, I borrowed it from somebody else. I must credit them, and I&amp;#8217;ve forgotten who it is. It&amp;#8217;s somebody I do follow and I&amp;#8217;ve forgotten, but I&amp;#8217;ve amended it slightly just for hours. But yes, really this is just to highlight just the last bit of change, if you like, in our history, and I think this is really significant, only in the Chrome at the moment, but we&amp;#8217;ve got scroll animation, which means that we can do a lot of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cool animations and stuff, with our text as I&amp;#8217;m just showing off here. It&amp;#8217;s a little bit over. It&amp;#8217;s great though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:47:21] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;Isn&amp;#8217;t, that brilliant. and again, obviously the purview of JavaScript forever, this was, the only way to do it and now all of this stuff is coming to CSS. Yeah. it is a bit flashy, isn&amp;#8217;t it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s quite a lot going on there to make you make your eyes water, but you get the point. It doesn&amp;#8217;t have to be quite so dramatic as that, but something subtle. Something just sort fading in or moving slightly to the left or the right could be very profound. That&amp;#8217;s lovely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:47:48] David Waumsley: I think it&amp;#8217;s really nice that it&amp;#8217;s coming to a lan, language that we can understand, rather than JavaScript and you really rely on languages and it makes it a lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if your, browser had been set to prefer reduced motion in some form or another, then you won&amp;#8217;t get that bounce and you&amp;#8217;ll get the fade in slightly. You won&amp;#8217;t get the bouncing because it can just wrap that in the CSS to be able to do that. I, I. That&amp;#8217;s great. And I&amp;#8217;ve also put the tilted text here just to show that we can have some fun with writing modes these days, and particularly if it that&amp;#8217;s combined with the better positioning that we&amp;#8217;ve got.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it, it&amp;#8217;s maybe not lined up perfectly &amp;#8217;cause they had to do it quickly, but it&amp;#8217;s using grid to put it side by side. So Grid and Subgrid given us the ability to place more accurately our texts and we can, as we&amp;#8217;re showing here with the writing mode changing that we can turn it on its side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s nice. It&amp;#8217;s really nice. Yeah. Yeah. And that&amp;#8217;s it. And I just think that&amp;#8217;s the way things are going. I think typography is becoming a big thing. People are using blending, filtering, masking, overlapping with other elements and all these kind of things to tell stories these days on their web and need less images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think you can do a lot with good typography, and it can all be. Fully accessible. You can turn off the styling and anyone can read the text document screen. Readers can read it. So I think typography just come such&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:49:15] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;a long way. I think this episode has been profoundly interesting. Can I urge you if you have listened to this or even watched it on the screen, go, to no script show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I keep saying I&amp;#8217;ve, I&amp;#8217;m sure I&amp;#8217;ve said episode 11 throughout this whole thing. And of course it&amp;#8217;s actually episode 12, isn&amp;#8217;t it? Yeah. I&amp;#8217;m sorry about that. anytime I&amp;#8217;ve said episode 11, ignore that it&amp;#8217;s actually episode 12 and go check it out. No script show slash 12. I&amp;#8217;ll correct that in the, in the transcript hopefully, and go and see, what marvelous things David has put together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s all there loads of links, loads of opportunity for you to learn and figure out all this stuff. Wow. For yourself. Learn with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:49:55] David Waumsley: Yeah, it&amp;#8217;s, yeah. We bitten off more than can chew really with this episode. It&amp;#8217;s gone on quite a long time, so we&amp;#8217;ll probably have to close up. It&amp;#8217;s been a long one,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[00:50:03] &lt;strong&gt;Nathan Wrigley: &lt;/strong&gt;so shall we.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shall we knock it on the head there? Yeah. Okay. We&amp;#8217;ll be back soon. Who knows when? We don&amp;#8217;t have a set schedule, but we&amp;#8217;ll be back at some point in the near future with episode 12, no 13 saving himself. So I&amp;#8217;ll see you next time. Thanks, David. Yeah, thank you. Cheers. Bye bye.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>